<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-docbookx.dtd">

<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.6.15
  Last modified: January, 2018
  Maintainers:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
               Chris Good <chris.good@ozemail.com.au>
               Christopher Lam
  Author:
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (Mechtilde Stehmann <ooo@mechtilde.de)
-->
 <chapter id="ch_reports">
   <title>Berichte</title>
   <para>&app; ist ein leistungsstarkes Softwarepaket für die doppelte
   Buchführung, mit dem Benutzer ihr Geld zuverlässig erfassen und verfolgen
   können. Die Eingabe dieser Informationen in &app; ist jedoch nur ein Teil
   des Prozesses. Um wirklich hilfreich zu sein, müssen Sie in der Lage sein,
   diese Informationen auf sinnvolle Weise zu extrahieren. &app;'s
   Berichtsfunktionen ermöglichen Ihnen genau das.</para>
   <para>Mit den Berichtsfunktionen von &app; können Sie nahezu jede Gruppe
   von Transaktionen in einer Vielzahl von Formaten anzeigen. Das macht es
   einfach, Fragen zu Ihren Finanzen zu beantworten, wie z. B. <quote>Wie viel
   habe ich letzten Monat für Lebensmittel ausgegeben?</quote> oder
   <quote>Wie viel habe ich in den letzten sechs Monaten verdient?</quote></para>
   <para>&app; enthält eine Reihe gängiger Berichtstypen, die an Ihre
   speziellen Bedürfnisse angepasst werden können. Wenn diese allgemeinen
   Berichte nicht ausreichen, ist es möglich, Ihre eigenen benutzerdefinierten
   Berichte zu ändern oder sogar zu schreiben (obwohl dies für Anfänger
   nicht empfohlen wird).</para>

 <sect1 id="rpt_concepts">
   <title>Übersicht</title>
   <para>Es gibt viele vorgefertigte Standardberichte in &app;, die alle
   über das Menü <guimenu>Berichte</guimenu> im Hauptfenster des
   Kontos verfügbar sind.</para>
   <para>Wenn Sie einen Bericht aus der Liste der Berichte auswählen, wird
   dieser Bericht zunächst mit seinen Standardeinstellungen ausgeführt.
   Nachdem Sie den Bericht geöffnet haben, können Sie seine Parameter ändern,
   indem Sie auf die Schaltfläche Optionen in der Symbolleiste klicken. Unter
   Optionen sehen Sie die verschiedenen Einstellungen, die Sie für jeden
   Bericht ändern können. Beachten Sie, dass die Optionen für verschiedene
   Berichte unterschiedlich sein werden.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="rpt_savedconfigsinfo">
   <title>Konzepte der gespeicherten Berichtskonfigurationen</title>
   <para>Wenn Sie einen Bericht an Ihre Bedürfnisse angepasst haben,
   möchten Sie diesen Bericht vielleicht speichern, um ihn später wieder
   zu verwenden. &app; ermöglicht das Speichern von benutzerdefinierten
   Berichten mit dem Befehl Berichtskonfiguration speichern.</para>
   <para>Eine Berichtskonfiguration speichern:</para>
     <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para>Gehen Sie zum Menü Berichte und wählen Sie den gewünschten
     Bericht.</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>Ändern Sie die Einstellungen des Reports, bis er das
     enthält, was benötigt wird.</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>Gehen Sie zur Registerkarte <emphasis>Allgemein</emphasis>
     der Berichtsoptionen und ändern Sie den Berichtsnamen in einen
     aussagekräftigen Wert (nicht zu verwechseln mit dem Berichtstitel).</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>Übernehmen Sie die Änderungen und schließen Sie den Dialog.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem><para>Klicken Sie auf die Schaltfläche Reportkonfiguration speichern
     oder Reportkonfiguration speichern unter…</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
   <para>Dadurch werden die Berichtsoptionen in einer Datei in Ihrem
   Benutzer-Verzeichnis gespeichert.</para>
   <para>Wenn Sie zum ersten Mal einen Report unter einem Namen speichern,
   der noch nicht gespeichert wurde, können Sie entweder die Schaltfläche
   Reportkonfiguration speichern oder die Schaltfläche Reportkonfiguration
   speichern unter… verwenden. Sie können den Namen des Reportes vor dem
   Speichern ändern.</para>
   <para>Sobald ein Bericht mit dem aktuellen Namen gespeichert wurde, wird
   die Schaltfläche Berichtskonfiguration speichern sofort die gespeicherte
   Berichtskonfiguration aktualisieren. Verwenden Sie die Schaltfläche
   Reportkonfiguration speichern unter, um die aktuelle Reportkonfiguration
   unter einem neuen Namen zu speichern.</para>
   <para>Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen sind unter dem Eintrag
   Berichte->Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen zur Verwendung verfügbar.
   Sie sind auch für die Verwendung in mehrspaltigen Berichten verfügbar.</para>
   <para>Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen können im Dialogfeld gespeicherte
   Berichtskonfigurationen durch Klicken auf das Mülleimer-Symbol
   gelöscht werden.</para>
   <para>Um gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen zu bearbeiten, öffnen
   Sie den Bericht über Berichte->Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen,
   bearbeiten und übernehmen die neuen Optionen und klicken auf
   Berichtskonfiguration speichern.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="rpt_standardrpts">
  <title>Übersicht der Standardberichte</title>
  <para>Die Standardberichte, die in &app; enthalten sind, werden in
  diesem Kapitel vorgestellt. Für jeden Bericht wird eine kurze Beschreibung
  gegeben, die erklärt, was der Bericht zeigen soll und was sein Hauptzweck ist.
  Wir beginnen mit einer Beschreibung des Transaktionsberichts, der ein
  Allzweckbericht mit vielen Funktionen und Einstellungen ist, die eine
  anspruchsvolle Untersuchung der Daten in einer Datei ermöglichen.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="rpt_txnrept">
    <title>Buchungsbericht</title>
    <para>Der Buchungsbericht ist ein grundlegender Bericht, mit dem
    Benutzer eine Vielzahl nützlicher Informationen aus den Finanzunterlagen
    abrufen können. Der Bericht enthält viele Funktionen, die eine
    leistungsstarke und flexible Berichterstellung aus dem einzelnen
    Basisbericht ermöglichen..</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Zwischensummen der Forderungen und Verbindlichkeiten können
        angezeigt werden, und innerhalb eines Gruppierungsabschnitts wird,
        wenn die Summe der Forderungen größer als die Summe der
        Verbindlichkeiten ist, die Zwischensumme der Gruppe in der
        Spalte der Forderungen angezeigt.</para>
        </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mehrere Datenspalten ermöglichen die Anzeige von
        Buchungsbeträgen in Berichtswährung und Originalwährung in
        separaten Spalten.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Zusätzliche Sortierschlüssel, z.B. Sortierung nach
        Abgleichstatus (unabgestimmt -> abgeglichen -> abgestimmt),
        Sortierung nach Wochen, erlauben zusätzliche Einblicke in die
        Finanzdaten.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Volltextfilter für Beschreibung, Notizen und Memo sowie
        für Kontovollnamen aktiviert. Dies ermöglicht eine einfachere
        Auswahl von Quellkontonamen und maßgeschneiderte Berichte. Filter
        können optional vollständige reguläre POSIX-Ausdrücke verwenden.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Die Einrückung von Spalten bewirkt eine Einrückung der
        Berichtsspalten zum besseren Verständnis der Gruppierung und
        Sortierung. (Dies ist jetzt standardmäßig für Gnucash 3.0 und
        höher aktiviert)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Die Tabelle der Zwischensummen ist nützlich, um die
        Beziehung in den Daten zu verstehen. Diese Funktion fasst die
        primären und sekundären Zwischensummen in einer Tabellenansicht
        zusammen und ermöglicht so zusätzliche Einblicke in Finanzdatensätze,
        z. B. Kontozwischensummen in verschiedenen Zeitreihen.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Weitere Ideen, wie Sie mit dem Buchungsbericht allgemeine
    Berichte erstellen können, finden Sie unter
    <link linkend='rpt_transaction'>Using the
    Transaction Report</link>.</para>
  </sect2>
<sect2 id="rpt_grp_assetsliabs">
<title>Gruppe der Aktiva &amp; Passiva</title>
<para>Berichte in dieser Gruppe liefern allgemeine Informationen über
Vermögenswerte und Verbindlichkeiten.</para>

<sect3 id="rpt_advport">
<title>Erweitertes Portfolio</title>
<para>Das erweiterte Portfolio erstellt einen Bericht über Wertpapierkonten
(Konten vom Typ Aktien und Investmentfonds) unter Verwendung von
Preisinformationen, die in der &app; Preisdatenbank und in den &app;
Buchungsdaten gespeichert sind. Wenn Sie keine Aktienkursinformationen
in Ihrer Datei haben, wird der Bericht einen Fehler anzeigen. Dieser
Bericht enthält erweiterte Informationen über Wertpapierbestände,
einschließlich Informationen über die Basis, den Gewinn und die Rendite
der einzelnen Wertpapiere.</para>

<!--  <sect4 id="rpt-advport-capgains">
    <title>Advanced Portfolio Capital Gains</title>
    <para>
      The Advanced Portfolio report doesn’t use the capital gain splits to
      calculate capital gains. It calculates the gains from the various buy and
      sell transactions in the account without regard to whether the gains and
      losses are recorded or not. Any realized gain splits are ignored.
      Realized gain splits are recognized as two splits, one in the stock’s
      account with a zero number of shares and a non-zero value, the other in an
      income or expense account with a value that is the negative of the split
      in the stock account. These two splits can be in a separate transaction
      (as created by scrubbing) or in the same transaction as the sale (this
      will cause incorrect future scrubbing). The income or expense split can
      be split into multiple splits, say for taxable/non-taxable or
      short/long term gains, without affecting this report.
    </para>
  </sect4>
  ToDo: Is it relevant anymore Mechtilde 2021-01-19-->
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_assetbarchart">
  <title>Aktiva-Diagramm</title>
  <para>Das Aktiva-Diagramm stellt den Wert der Vermögenswerte auf
  monatlicher Basis in Barchart-Form dar. Standardmäßig zeigt der Bericht
  die acht größten Konten an, denen bestimmte Vermögensarten zugeordnet
  sind, und er zeigt Balken für die aktuelle Finanzperiode an.</para>
  <para>Verschiedene Einstellungen in diesem Bericht können die
  enthaltenen Informationen stark beeinflussen..</para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Konten" ändert die Option
  "Konten anzeigen bis Ebene", wie der Bericht die Kontensummen aggregiert.
  Ändern Sie diesen Wert, um Informationen auf tieferen Ebenen der
  Kontostruktur zu sehen.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Anzeige" werden mit der Option
  "Maximale Balken" mehr Balken im Diagramm angezeigt, so dass
  Informationen für mehr Konten angezeigt werden können. Zusätzlich
  ermöglicht die Option "Tabelle anzeigen" die Anzeige von
  Diagramminformationen in tabellarischer Form unterhalb des Diagramms.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Allgemein" kann die Option
  "Preisquelle" den berichteten Wert der verschiedenen im Bericht
  enthaltenen Vermögenswerte erheblich beeinflussen.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_assetpiechart">
  <title>Aktiva Tortendiagramm</title>
  <para>Das Vermögenswertdiagramm stellt den Wert der Vermögenswerte auf
  monatlicher Basis in Form eines Tortendiagramms dar. Standardmäßig
  zeigt der Bericht die sieben größten Konten, denen bestimmte
  Aktiva-Typen zugewiesen sind, in absteigender Reihenfolge nach dem Wert
  zum Ende der aktuellen Buchhaltungsperiode.</para>
  <para>Mehrere Einstellmöglichkeiten in diesem Bericht können die
  enthaltenen Informationen stark beeinflussen.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Konten" ändert die Option
  "Konten anzeigen bis Ebene", wie der Bericht die Kontensummen
  aggregiert. Ändern Sie diesen Wert, um Informationen auf tieferen
  Ebenen der Kontostruktur zu sehen.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Anzeige" werden mit der Option
  "Maximale Segmente" mehr Segmente im Diagramm angezeigt, sodass
  Informationen für mehr Konten angezeigt werden können.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Allgemein" kann die Option
  "Preisquelle" einen erheblichen den berichteten Wert verschiedener im
  Bericht enthaltener Vermögenswerte erheblich beeinflussen.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<!--<sect3 id="rpt_avgbalance">
<title>Durchschnittlicher Kontostand</title>
<para>Der Bericht "Durchschnittlicher Kontostand" zeigt monatliche
Durchschnittswerte für den aktuellen Abrechnungszeitraum an.</para>
</sect3> -->

<sect3 id="rpt_balancesheet">
<title>Bilanz</title>
<para>Die Bilanz listet die Salden der Aktiv-, Passiv- und
Eigenkapitalkonten für alle diese Konten auf und liefert Summen zu einem
bestimmten Datum. Bilanzen werden in der Regel für den letzten Tag eines
Geschäftsjahres erstellt, um einen Gesamteindruck von der finanziellen
Lage des Unternehmens zu vermitteln.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_generaljournal">
<title>Hauptbuch Journal</title>
<para>Das Haupt-Journal erstellt ein Register aller Buchungen (vom Anfang
bis zum Ende), geordnet nach Datum, mit Angabe der Konten und der
beteiligten Beträge, und summiert die Nettoveränderung nach allen
Währungen und Vermögenswerten.</para>
<para>Dieser Bericht ist nicht nach Datum oder Konto anpassbar, obwohl
Sie mehr oder weniger Details über die einzelnen Buchungen einbeziehen
können, und ob Sie laufende Salden und Summen für die Gutschriften und
Belastungen einbeziehen wollen. Wenn Sie einen auf bestimmte Konten
beschränkten Bericht benötigen, sollten Sie den Buchungsbericht oder
öffnen Sie ein bestimmtes Konto und wählen Sie den Kontenbuchungsbericht.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_generalledger">
<title>Journal</title>
<para>Das Journal liefert Informationen über alle Buchungen für eine
ausgewählte Gruppe von Konten. Bei der ersten Ausführung lädt dieser
Bericht keine Daten, und die Berichtsoptionen müssen geändert werden,
um Informationen aus der Datei abzurufen.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_investport">
<title>Anlageportfolio</title>
<para>Das Anlageportfolio erstellt einen Bericht über Wertpapierkonten
(d. h. Konten mit dem Typ "Aktie" oder "Investmentfonds"), der
Informationen über Bestände, Preise und Werte der Wertpapiere in der
Datei enthält..</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_liabbarchart">
<title>Verbindlichkeit-Balkendiagramm</title>
<para>Das Verbindlichkeit-Balkendiagramm stellt den Wert der
Verbindlichkeiten auf monatlicher Basis in Balkendarstellung dar.
Standardmäßig zeigt der Bericht die acht größten Konten an, denen
bestimmte Vermögensarten zugeordnet sind, und er zeigt Balken für die
aktuelle Finanzperiode an.</para>
<para>Verschiedene Einstellungen in diesem Bericht können die enthaltenen
Informationen stark beeinflussen.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Konten" ändert die Option
"Konten anzeigen bis Ebene", wie der Bericht die Kontensummen aggregiert.
Ändern Sie diesen Wert, um Informationen auf tieferen Ebenen der
Kontostruktur zu sehen.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Anzeige" werden mit der Option
"Maximale Balken" mehr Balken im Diagramm angezeigt, so dass
Informationen für mehr Konten angezeigt werden können. Zusätzlich
ermöglicht die Option "Tabelle anzeigen" die Anzeige von
Diagramminformationen in tabellarischer Form unterhalb des Diagramms.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Allgemein" kann die Option
"Preisquelle" den berichteten Wert der verschiedenen im Bericht
enthaltenen Wertpapiere erheblich beeinflussen.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_liabpiechart">
<title>Verbindlichkeit - Tortendiagramm</title>
<para>Das Tortendiagramm "Verbindlichkeiten" stellt den Wert der
Verbindlichkeiten auf monatlicher Basis in Tortendiagrammform dar.
Standardmäßig zeigt der Bericht die sieben größten Konten, denen
bestimmte Aktiva-Typen zugewiesen sind, in absteigender Reihenfolge
nach dem Wert zum Ende der aktuellen Buchhaltungsperiode.</para>
<para>Mehrere Einstellungen in diesem Bericht können die enthaltenen
Informationen stark beeinflussen.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Konten" ändert die Option "Konten
anzeigen bis Ebene", wie der Bericht die Kontensummen aggregiert. Ändern
diesen Wert, um Informationen auf tieferen Ebenen der Kontostruktur zu
sehen.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Anzeige" werden mit der Option
"Maximale Schnitte" mehr Schnitte im Diagramm angezeigt, sodass
Informationen für mehr Konten angezeigt werden können.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Auf der Registerkarte "Allgemein" kann die Option
"Preisquelle" den berichteten Wert der verschiedenen im Bericht
enthaltenen Waren erheblich beeinflussen.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_networthbar">
<title>Reinvermögen Balkendiagramm</title>
<para>Das Reinvermögen Balkendiagramm fasst Aktivakonten,
Verbindlichkeitskonten und das gesamte Reinvermögensbestand als Balken
in einem Diagramm auf monatlicher Basis für die aktuelle Finanzperiode
zusammen. Dieser Bericht bietet einen grafischen Überblick über die Datei
im Zeitverlauf.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_networthline">
<title>Reinvermögen-Liniendiagramm</title>
<para>Das Nettowert-Liniendiagramm fasst Aktiva- und Verbindlichkeitskonten
sowie den gesamten Nettowert als Liniendiagramm auf monatlicher Basis für
die aktuelle Finanzperiode zusammen. Dieser Bericht bietet einen
grafischen Überblick über die Datei im Zeitverlauf.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_pricescatter">
<title>Kursdiagramm</title>
<para>Das Kursdiagramm zeigt den Wert eines Wertpapieres im Verhältnis
zu einem anderen Wertpapier an, zum Beispiel den Wert einer Aktie im
Verhältnis zu einer Währung. Bei der ersten Ausführung lädt dieser Bericht
keine Daten, und die Berichtsoptionen müssen geändert werden, um
Informationen aus der Datei abzurufen. Insbesondere muss die Einstellung
"Preis der Devise/Wertpapier" auf der Registerkarte "Kurs" an ein
bestimmtes Wertpapier gehängt werden.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="rpt_grp_budget">
<title>Gruppe Budget</title>
<para>Mit Budget-Berichten in &app; können Sie zusammenfassende Informationen
zu den von Ihnen erstellten Budgets sammeln. Damit diese Berichte funktionieren,
müssen Sie zuerst ein Budget erstellen. Die Berichte in dieser Gruppe basieren
speziell auf Budgetinformationen. Um diese Berichte zu verwenden, müssen
Sie ein Budget in Ihrer Datei gespeichert haben.</para>

<sect3 id="rpt_budbalsht">
<title>Budget Bilanz</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_budbarchart">
<title>Budget Diagramm</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_budflow">
<title>Budget Flow</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_budincstate">
<title>Budget Einnahmeüberschussrechnung</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_budprofloss">
<title>Budget Gewinn- und Verlustrechnung</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_budreport">
<title>Budget Bericht</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="rpt_grp_business">
<title>Gruppe Geschäft</title>
<para>Die Berichte in dieser Gruppe liefern allgemeine Informationen über
Aktivitäten im Zusammenhang mit einem Unternehmen.</para>

<sect3 id="rpt_customer">
<title>Kundenbericht</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_custsummary">
<title>Kundenübersicht</title>
<para>Die Kundenübersicht ist ein Kundengewinnbericht, der bei der 
Auftragsanalyse helfen kann, indem er die Einnahmen und Ausgaben für 
einen bestimmten Kunden vergleicht.</para>
<para>Zu allen Rechnungen gehört ein Besitzer in &app;, so dass 
Rechnungen, die erstellt werden, einen Kunden aufweisen und im Bericht 
angezeigt werden. Beim Erstellen einer Rechnung ist das Feld 
"Default Chargeback Customer" leer. Um den Gewinnbericht zu verwenden, 
benötigt dieses Feld einen Eintrag, da dies das Tag ist, das entscheidet, 
an welche Zeile der Aufwand angehängt wird. Bleibt es leer, wird die 
Rechnung "Kein Kunde" zugewiesen. Ähnlich verhält es sich, wenn Einnahmen 
direkt in ein Register eingegeben werden, anstatt eine Rechnung zu 
erstellen, werden sie ebenfalls "Kein Kunde" zugewiesen.
</para>
<para>Wenn dieser Bericht also einen Eintrag für "Kein Kunde" enthält, 
bedeutet dies, dass der Bericht möglicherweise ungenau ist, da die 
Ergebnisse nicht alle richtig beschriftet sind.</para>
<para>Mögliche Einsatzszenarien sind:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Verfolgung von Einzelhandelsumsätzen aus verschiedenen 
Städten</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Verfolgung von Mietobjekten</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Verfolgung von Geschäftsarten</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Verfolgung von Provisionsverkäufen</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Jedes dieser Szenarien setzt voraus, dass die Kontenstruktur 
Aufschlüsselungen für einzelne verfolgte Kategorien enthält. Durch Ändern 
der Einstellungen auf den Registerkarten "Einnahmen" und "Ausgaben" unter 
"Optionen" können die angezeigten Informationen verfeinert werden. 
Standardmäßig sind alle Einnahmen- und Aufwandskonten enthalten; da &app; 
jedoch die Namen und die Klassifizierung der Einnahmen- und Aufwandskonten 
nicht wirklich vorhersagen kann, muss es sie alle in den Eintrag "Kein Kunde" 
gruppieren.</para>
<para>Beachten Sie, dass bestandsorientierte Unternehmen aufgrund der Art 
dieses Berichts nicht davon profitieren werden.</para>
<para>Sinnvolle Optionen:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Die Registerkarte "Aufwandskonten" ermöglicht die Auswahl 
von einem oder mehreren Aufwandskonten.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Die Registerkarte Ertragskonten ermöglicht die Auswahl 
eines oder mehrerer Ertragskonten.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Die Registerkarte "Anzeige" ermöglicht die Sortierung 
nach Name, Gewinnprozentsatz oder Höhe des Gewinns.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_easyinv">
<title>Easy Invoice</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_employee">
<title>Employee Report</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_fancyinv">
<title>Fancy Invoice</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_payaging">
<title>Payable Aging</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_prtinv">
<title>Printable Invoice</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_recaging">
<title>Receivable Aging</title>
<para>This report provides a listing of all customers, their current balance, and
how much they have outstanding from invoices over different time periods&amp;mdash;how
much they owe from 0-30 days, from 31-60 days, from 61-90 days, and over 90 days.
The report also contains links to each customer and to their current customer report.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_vendor">
<title>Vendor Report</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="rpt_grp_incexp">
<title>Income and Expense Group</title>
<para>Reports in this group provide information about Income and Expense</para>

<sect3 id="rpt_cashflow">
<title>Cash Flow</title>
<para>This report shows the change in value for a set of accounts (the flow of cash)
over a given period of time. By default, this report is based on accounts in Assets and
Special Accounts, and covers the current financial period. The report enumerates
all money coming in to and going out of the base accounts, broken down by the
other account.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_equity">
<title>Equity Statement</title>
<para>This report can be seen as extension of the Balance Sheet report. The
Balance Sheet states the balance of Assets, Liabilities and Equity at a
specific point of time. The Equity Statement focuses on the Equity Accounts
by showing the cash flow to and from them for a given period of time.</para>
<para>By balancing this cash flow with income, the report shows the available
capital at the beginning and end of the selected time period.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_expbarchart">
<title>Expense Barchart</title>
<para>The Expense Barchart presents the value of expenses on a monthly basis in
barchart form. By default, the report displays the eight largest accounts that
have specific expense types assigned to them, and it displays bars for
the current financial period.</para>
<para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how
the report aggregates account totals. Change this value to see information at
deeper levels of the account structure.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Bars" option will display more bars in
the chart, allowing information for more accounts to display. Additionally,
the "Show table" option enables the display of chart information in tabular
form below the chart.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly
affect the reported value of various commodities included in the report.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_exppiechart">
<title>Expense Piechart</title>
<para>The Expense Piechart presents the value of expenses on a monthly basis in
piechart form. By default, the report shows the seven largest accounts, that
have specific expense types assigned to them, arranged in descending order by
value as of the end of the current accounting period.</para>
<para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how
the report aggregates account totals. Change this value to see information at
deeper levels of the account structure.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Slices" option will display more
slices in the chart, allowing information for more accounts to display.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly
affect the reported value of various commodities included in the report.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_expdayoweek">
<title>Expenses vs. Day of Week</title>
<para>Expenses vs. Day of Week presents a pie chart showing the totals for
selected expense accounts totaled by the day of the week of the transaction.
The report options enable you to make some adjustments (such as accounts,
display options, and the date range) but the account selector only allows
expense accounts to be chosen. The report aggregates expense transactions by
day of week, not by any other period or category. Due to these limitations,
the report may be considered a demonstration or an example to someone wanting
to examine the source code for composing a useful custom report.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_incomebarchart">
<title>Income Barchart</title>
<para>The Income Barchart presents the value of income on a monthly basis in
barchart form. By default, the report displays the eight largest accounts that
have specific income types assigned to them, and it displays bars for
the current financial period.</para>
<para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how
the report aggregates account totals. Change this value to see information at
deeper levels of the account structure.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Bars" option will display more bars in
the chart, allowing information for more accounts to display. Additionally,
the "Show table" option enables the display of chart information in tabular
form below the chart.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly
affect the reported value of various commodities included in the report.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_incexpchart">
<title>Income &amp; Expense Chart</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_incomepiechart">
<title>Income Piechart</title>
<para>The Income Piechart presents the value of income on a monthly basis in
piechart form. By default, the report shows the seven largest accounts, that
have specific income types assigned to them, arranged in descending order by
value as of the end of the current accounting period.</para>
<para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how
the report aggregates account totals. Change this value to see information at
deeper levels of the account structure.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Slices" option will display more
slices in the chart, allowing information for more accounts to display.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly
affect the reported value of various commodities included in the report.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_incstatement">
<title>Income Statement</title>
<para>This report lists Income and Expense account totals for a set period. By
default, it shows all Expense and Income accounts down to 3 levels of
sub-accounts for the current financial period.</para>
<para>An Income Statement is also called a "Profit and Loss" report or "Revenue Statement."</para>
<para>In earlier versions of &app;, this report was called
"Profit &amp; Loss," but with version 2, the report was renamed "Income Statement"
to use more common accounting terminology.</para>
<para>The Income Statement helps show where money is coming from and where it is
going for a given time period.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_incdayoweek">
<title>Income vs. Day of Week</title>
<para>Income vs. Day of Week presents a piechart showing the totals for selected
income accounts totaled by the day of the week of the transaction. The report
options enable you to make some adjustments (such as accounts, display options,
and the date range) but the account selector only allows income accounts to be
chosen. The report aggregates income transactions by day of week, not by any
other period or category. Due to these limitations, the report may be
considered a demonstration or an example to someone wanting to examine the
source code for composing a useful custom report.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_trialbal">
<title>Trial Balance</title>
<para>Trial Balance lists the ending balances in all accounts as of a particular
date. It is typically run at the end of an accounting period and is primarily
used to ensure that the total of all debits equals the total of all credits.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="rpt_gst_statement">
  <title>Income and GST Statement</title>
  <para>The Income and GST Statement is a specialised Transaction
  Report designed to print Business-related Sales and Receipts, as
  well as their GST or VAT components. This report is designed for use
  in Australia, but is also usable in any jurisdictions implementing
  value-added taxes (or goods and services taxes) during regular
  business sales and receipts; and the business owner is expected to
  submit periodic reports of total sales, purchases, and taxes
  collected on sales from clients or paid to a supplier.
  </para>
  <para>This report makes some assumptions upon the accounts used for
  sales, purchases, and taxes collected on sales, and paid on purchases.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Net Sales must be an Income-type account</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Net Purchases must be an Expense-type account</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>GST/VAT on Sales must be a Liability-type account</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>GST/VAT on Purchases must be an Asset-type account</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>There may be multiple GST accounts, e.g. reduced GST,
      standard GST etc. The GST accounts can be printed individually,
      or summarised for sales and purchases.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>There may be multiple sales and expenses accounts,
      e.g. Income:Sales, Income:Grants, Expenses:Suppliers,
      Expenses:Marketing, Expenses:Insurance. These amounts may be
      reported individually, or summarised for sales and purchases.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>The transactions may be entered manually as a multi-split
      transaction, or they may be entered via the Business Invoices
      and Bills tools.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>As an example, consider a business has the following
  transactions: It incurs sales of $1,000 plus 5% GST, receiving
  $1,050. It also incurs GST-exempt sales of $600. It purchases
  goods/services worth $400 plus 5% = $420. The following transactions
  will record the business activities:
  </para>
  <table>
    <title>Sample Chart of Accounts for Income and GST Statement</title>
    <tgroup cols="5" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
      <colspec colname="date"/>
      <colspec colname="desc"/>
      <colspec colname="account"/>
      <colspec colname="debit" align="right"/>
      <colspec colname="credit" align="right"/>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Date</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
          <entry>Account</entry>
          <entry>Debit</entry>
          <entry>Credit</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry morerows="2" valign="top">01/01/2018</entry>
          <entry morerows="2" valign="top">Sales $1,000 + 5% GST</entry>
          <entry>Income:Sales</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>$1,000</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>GST on Sales [Liability]</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>$50</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Asset:Bank</entry>
          <entry>$1,050</entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry morerows="1" valign="top">02/01/2018</entry>
          <entry morerows="1" valign="top">GST-Free Sales $600</entry>
          <entry>Income:Sales</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>$600</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Asset:Bank</entry>
          <entry>$600</entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry morerows="2" valign="top">03/01/2018</entry>
          <entry morerows="2" valign="top">Purchase $400 + 5% GST</entry>
          <entry>Expenses:Purchases</entry>
          <entry>$400</entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Asset:Bank</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>$420</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>GST on Purchases [Asset]</entry>
          <entry>$20</entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>
  <para>For the Income and GST Statement, the
  <option>Accounts</option> selected will be the Income and Expense
  Accounts, and the <option>Tax accounts</option> are used to select
  the GST accounts. The GST period is selected via the
  <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab. The resulting report is shown as
  follows:</para>
  <table>
    <title>Income and GST Statement</title>
    <tgroup cols="8" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
      <colspec colname="date"/>
      <colspec colname="desc"/>
      <colspec colname="tot-sales" align="right"/>
      <colspec colname="net-sales" align="right"/>
      <colspec colname="tax-sales" align="right"/>
      <colspec colname="tot-purch" align="right"/>
      <colspec colname="net-purch" align="right"/>
      <colspec colname="tax-purch" align="right"/>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Date</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
          <entry>Total Sales</entry>
          <entry>Net Sales</entry>
          <entry>Tax on Sales</entry>
          <entry>Total Purchases</entry>
          <entry>Net Purchases</entry>
          <entry>Tax on Purchases</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>01/01/2018</entry>
          <entry>Sales $1,000 + 5%</entry>
          <entry>$1,050</entry>
          <entry>$1,000</entry>
          <entry>$50</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>02/01/2018</entry>
          <entry>GST-Free Sales $600</entry>
          <entry>$600</entry>
          <entry>$600</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>03/01/2018</entry>
          <entry>Purchase $400 + 5% GST</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>$420</entry>
          <entry>$400</entry>
          <entry>$20</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Totals</entry>
          <entry></entry>
          <entry>$1,650</entry>
          <entry>$1,600</entry>
          <entry>$50</entry>
          <entry>$420</entry>
          <entry>$400</entry>
          <entry>$20</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>
  <para>This report would indicate that there was a total of $50 GST
  collected, and $20 GST on purchases, therefore a $30 GST liability
  is payable to the authorities.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="rpt_grp_sampcust">
<title>Sample &amp; Custom Group</title>
<para>The reports in this group offer examples on how reports can be customized
or podified to suit personal need.</para>

<sect3 id="rpt_custommulti">
<title>Custom Multicolumn Report</title>
<para>This report provides a base that allows several standard and custom
reports to be combined into one view. Note that this report opens with an empty
window; you must open the options and designate which reports to include for display.
Once the reports have been selected, the settings for individual reports in the
multicolumn display can be edited.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="rpt_sample">
<title>Sample Report with Examples</title>
<para>This is a sample report that users can examine to learn how to write their own reports.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_welcome">
<title>Welcome Sample Report</title>
<para>This report demonstrates how the Multicolumn Report can be use to create
custom dashboard-type reports.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="rpt_grp_miscrpts">
<title>Other Reports</title>
<para>Several reports are included on the main Reports menu. These are described
below.</para>

<sect3 id="rpt_acctsummary">
<title>Account Summary</title>
<para>This lists the balances of all accounts and subaccounts as of a
particular date. By default, this report shows accounts and totals
down to third-level subaccounts.</para>
<para>This report gives effectively the same information as the Chart of Accounts.
You can use this report to export and print the Chart of Accounts.</para>
<note>
  <para>To generate a report of account totals over a particular time period
  (especially if you do not close your books at regular intervals), you might
  consider using the Income Statement, or Cash Flow reports.</para>
</note>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_balance_forecast">
  <title>Balance Forecast</title>
  <para>This creates a balance chart which aims to track asset (or any
  other account type) balances, including amounts from future
  scheduled transactions. The balances will include all regular booked
  amounts and future amounts from numeric scheduled transaction
  templates.</para>
  <para>This report can also add additional data charts to forecast
  future minimum balances. Reserve line can be displayed to confirm if
  future minimum will dip below the reserve amount. A target line may
  also be displayed above the reserve line for financial planning.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_futsched">
<title>Future Scheduled Transactions Summary</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_taxtxf">
<title>Tax Report &amp; TXF Export</title>
<para>Generates a report and a downloadable .txf file of taxable income and
deductible expenses for a particular accounting period. To download the report
data, choose the Export button on the toolbar and choose between html and .txf
downloadable versions.</para>
<para>To use this report, you must use Edit --> Tax Options to identify which
form the taxing authority uses for each income or expense account. Note that
you can see but not modify the "Tax related" checkbox in Edit --> Edit Account.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_savedrpts">
<title>Saved Report Configurations</title>
<para>Selecting this will open a dialog with a list of available Saved Report
Configurations. "Saved Report Configurations" means sets of customized
settings for standard reports.</para>
<para>These sets must be saved by the user before they appear here. See
Report Concepts above for instructions on how to save report configurations.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_acctreport">
<title>Account Report</title>
<para>The Account Report menu entry only appears when an account register is
the active tab. This report produces a list of all transactions in the open
register.</para>
<para>Note that if you conduct a search that retrieves several transactions, the
results are displayed in a new search register, which can then be used to create
a report for just those transactions.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rpt_accttxnrept">
<title>Account Transaction Report</title>
<para>This report also only appears when an account register is the active tab.
However, this report only lists transactions that have been selected
(e.g. by mouse click) in the current register. If no transactions are selected,
an empty report will be generated.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="rpt_transaction">
  <title>Using the Transaction Report</title>
  <para>The Transaction Report can be heavily customised to produce most
  reports appropriate for personal finance and business bookkeeping purposes.
  It aims to retrieve and filter information from the database, and present
  transactions and totals, useful for the user and the accountant.</para>
  <para>The following guide to the Transaction Report will assume the
  user has set up the chart of accounts according to conventional bookkeeping
  practice. For example, the following describes a typical household book with
  skeleton accounts. Further accounts will undoubtedly be necessary.</para>
  <table>
    <title>Sample Chart of Accounts for the Transaction Report</title>
    <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Account Name</entry>
          <entry>Account Type</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>Asset</entry>
          <entry>ASSET (placeholder)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Asset:Bank</entry>
          <entry>BANK</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Asset:Property</entry>
          <entry>ASSET</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Liability</entry>
          <entry>LIABILITY (placeholder)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Liability:Credit Card</entry>
          <entry>CREDIT CARD</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Liability:Home Loan</entry>
          <entry>LIABILITY</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Income</entry>
          <entry>INCOME (placeholder)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Income:Salary</entry>
          <entry>INCOME</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Income:Interest</entry>
          <entry>INCOME</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Expense</entry>
          <entry>EXPENSE (placeholder)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Expense:Groceries</entry>
          <entry>EXPENSE</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Expense:Auto</entry>
          <entry>EXPENSE</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Expense:Medical</entry>
          <entry>EXPENSE</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Equity</entry>
          <entry>EQUITY (placeholder)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>Equity:Opening Balances</entry>
          <entry>EQUITY</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>
  <para>Conventionally, the oldest transaction would be equity transfers from
  Equity:Opening Balances to Asset and Liability Accounts. Most subsequent
  transactions would be transfers from Income/Expense accounts to
  Assets/Liability accounts (representing day-to-day activity e.g. receiving
  salary, paying utility bill), or transfers between assets and liability
  accounts (representing movements between loans and assets, e.g. paying
  credit card bill, receiving a loan).</para>  
    <para>The following use cases will be illustrated, and the options to be
    selected explained:</para>
    <sect3>
      <title>Using the Transaction Report to show previous year
      expenses</title>
      <para>The Transaction Report can show how much was spent on
      expense accounts last year. This will usually be the most useful
      basic transaction report format. To create this report:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open the report options, from the
          <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab, click the Expense
          placeholder account and <guibutton>Select
          Children</guibutton>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab, Choose
          relative dates “Start of Previous Year” and “End of Previous
          Year”.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>From the <guilabel>Sorting</guilabel> tab, set
          <guilabel>Primary Key</guilabel> to Accounts, and enable
          <guilabel>Primary Key Subtotal</guilabel>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Set the <guilabel>Secondary Key</guilabel> to Date,
          and set the <guilabel>Secondary Key Subtotal</guilabel> to
          None. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Secondary level grouping</title>
      <para>The following will modify the above Transaction Report to
      use a secondary grouping strategy. The first grouping
      (i.e. Primary Key = Accounts, Subtotal = enabled) will group
      transactions from the same accounts, whereas the secondary
      grouping (i.e. Secondary Key = Date, Subtotal = Monthly) will
      also calculate monthly sums within each account.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Select options as above</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>From the <guilabel>Sorting</guilabel> tab,
        set <guilabel>Secondary Key Subtotal</guilabel> to Monthly
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Using secondary grouping for periodic comparison</title>
      <para>The Display / Subtotal Table adds a subtotal summary
      table, which will ease comparison of accounts across date
      periods.  This displays the same subtotal calculations as the
      main table, presented in a grid structure.
      </para>
      <para>In addition, if there are multiple primary-key groups
      (e.g. Date grouping with monthly subtotals, across multiple
      months) the subtotal table will also compute and display the
      primary-key grouping Average. The average is computed as the
      total amount <emphasis>per row</emphasis>, divided by the
      <emphasis>number of columns</emphasis>. This may cause confusion
      when computing monthly spend averages, for instance, if a month
      has no transactions and is not displayed in the table, it will
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> create a corresponding column in the
      table, therefore the average amount will not reflect a true
      monthly average.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Select options as above</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>From the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab,
        enable the <guilabel>Subtotal Table</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Use filtering to limit accounts and transactions</title>
      <para>Accounts and transactions can be filtered for reporting
      according to account full name (e.g. ":Business:" will
      select account structure Income:Business:Sales, Income:Business:Grants,
      Expenses:Business:Rent, Expenses:Business:Utilities) or transaction
      description/notes/memo (select transactions tagged #gift).
      The filtering text may be either a standard string, or a POSIX regular
      expression.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>From the <guilabel>Filter</guilabel> tab,
        complete the <guilabel>Account Name Filter</guilabel>, or
        <guilabel>Transaction Filter</guilabel>. Optionally toggle the
        regular expression check boxes to toggle full POSIX regex
        matching. Regular expressions will allow more complex
        queries e.g. the transaction filter can be set to
        (#gift|#travel) which will filter transactions with either
        #gift or #travel. They can be complicated and are best learned
        from external guides.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Using the Transaction Report to generate a
      reconciliation statement.</title>
      <para>This sortkey 'reconcile status' will separate reconciled,
      cleared and unreconciled transactions. This report may be useful
      in producing a printable reconciliation report.</para>
      <para>Alternatively, the <guilabel>Reconciliation Report
      </guilabel> will preset these defaults and requires only the
      Accounts selection.
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>From the <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab,
        select the relevant bank or credit card account</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>From the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab,
        choose an appropriate date range e.g. past 3 months</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>From the <guilabel>Sorting</guilabel> tab,
        set the <guilabel>Primary Key</guilabel> to Reconcile
        Status, <guilabel>Primary Key Subtotal</guilabel> to enabled,
        and set the <guilabel>Secondary Key</guilabel> to Date. The
        <guilabel>Secondary Date Subtotal</guilabel> is left to None
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
