<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-gui-C.dtd">
<variablelist spacing="compact">
  <title>Dialogue guidance</title>

  <para>The left pane lists the individual steps of the wizard. Explanatory text and the control elements
    for carrying out the respective step are displayed in the right window area.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>The buttons are usually located in the <quote>Action Area</quote> at the bottom edge
      of the dialog. With some window managers they are integrated into the title bar.
    </para>
  </note>

  <important>
    <para>The buttons described below are always activated only when the navigation
      from the current step to the target step is valid. I.e. as long as not all necessary information
      have been made, some buttons are deactivated.
    </para>
  </important>

  <varlistentry>
    <term><guibutton><accel>C</accel>ancel</guibutton> or <keycap>ESC</keycap></term>

    <listitem>
      <para>Exits the wizard without making any changes to your data or, in the case of exports, to the file system.
      </para>

      <warning>
        <para>If you click this button, all changes you have entered in the wizard up to this point will be lost.
        </para>
      </warning>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term><guibutton><accel>B</accel>ack</guibutton></term>

    <listitem>
      <para>Goes to the previous step. If you are still in the first step of the wizard this
        is equivalent to <guilabel>Cancel</guilabel>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term><guibutton><accel>N</accel>ext</guibutton></term>

    <listitem>
      <para>Goes to the next step.
        <note>
          <para>If you are in the last step, the button
            <guibutton><accel>A</accel>pply</guibutton> will be displayed instead.
          </para>
        </note>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term><guibutton><accel>A</accel>pply</guibutton></term>

    <listitem>
      <para>When you have entered all the required data into the wizard, the last step will be the
        <guilabel>Apply</guilabel> button  appear instead of <guilabel>Next</guilabel>.
        Only when you click this button your entries will be processed
        and the data modified.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
