<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-gui-C.dtd">
<!-- (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.x
  Last modified: December 7th 2009
       modified: March 28th 2007
       modified: August 12th 2006
	   modified: February 28th 2005
  Maintainers:
    Alex Aycinena <alex.aycinena@gmail.com>
    Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
    Neil Williams <linux@codehelp.co.uk>
  Author:
    Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Translators:
    (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="setup-accounts"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Setting Up, Editing &amp; Working with Accounts</title>

  <para>This section describes the process of setting up, editing and working with &app; Accounts. In &app;
    an Account is used as the basic tool to organize the recording of where money comes from and
    goes to. &app; also extends the concept of real world accounts such as a bank account or loan
    account to grouping income and expense accounts. This allows you to quickly see where you spent
    your money and what your major income and expenses are. &app; sets Account Types (as described
    in the next section) to help in organizing and grouping accounts. Account Types can be used to
    create a Chart of Accounts.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="acct-types">
    <title>Types of &appname; Accounts</title>

    <para>&app; supports a number of different account types. It is recommended to choose an appropriate
      account type based on the list of account types described below.
    </para>

    <tip>
      <para>When creating new accounts, the available options for the account type are limited, depending on the
        account type of the parent (main) account.
      </para>
    </tip>

    <para>Besides the basic account types described in the
      <ulink url="&url-docs-build-C;guide/accts-types1.html">&app; tutorial and concepts</ulink>,
      &app; also offers a few special account types. These are characterised in particular by
      adapted proposal lists -interest or dividend payment- in the action field and adapted actions.
      payment of dividends - in the action field and adjusted actions - e.g. there is no share
      division.
    </para>

    <table frame="topbot" id="TypeAccounts">
      <title>Types of &appname; Accounts</title>

      <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
        <colspec colname="c1"></colspec>

        <colspec colname="c2"></colspec>

        <colspec colname="c3"></colspec>

        <colspec colname="c4"></colspec>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Basic Accounting Types
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Account Type
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Description
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Parent account
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody valign="top">
          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
              <para>Asset accounts
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3" nameend="c4">
              <para>The evaluation<menuchoice>
                  <guimenu><accel>R</accel>eport</guimenu><guisubmenu><accel>A</accel>ssets &amp;
                  Liabilities</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Ba<accel>l</accel>ance Sheet</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>gives you an overview on any <emphasis>reporting date</emphasis>.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1" morerows="8">
              <para>Active
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c2" nameend="c3">
              <para>Assets denotes the use of funds and is on the left-hand side of the balance sheet. At the next level
                of the account structure, it is useful to distinguish between current and fixed
                assets. This can help you to recognise liquidity bottlenecks early on.
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c4" morerows="12">
              <para>All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Asset
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Asset accounts are used for tracking things that are of value and can be used or sold to pay debts.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c2" nameend="c3">
              <para>(Current assets, short-term)
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Cash
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>The Cash account type is used to denote the cash that you store in your wallet, shoe box, piggyback,
                or mattress. In the case of business use, this can also mean the cash register.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Bank
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>The Bank account type denotes savings or checking accounts held at a bank or other financial
                institution. Some of these accounts may bear interest. This is also the appropriate
                account type for check (debit) cards, which directly withdraw payments from a
                checking account.<footnote>
                  <para>For some of these accounts, it is possible to send orders to the financial institution via online
                    banking and to retrieve and import bookings. (see
                    <xref linkend="trans-online" />)
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2" rowsep="1">
              <para>Accounts Receivable<footnote id="fn-receivables-kat">
                  <para><warning>
                      <para>The Accounts Payable and Accounts Receivable types are used internally by &app;&rsquo;s business
                        features. Transactions involving these accounts should not be added, changed
                        or deleted in any way other than by using<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                          <listitem>
                            <para>post/unpost bill/invoice/voucher or
                            </para>
                          </listitem>

                          <listitem>
                            <para>process payment
                            </para>
                          </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                      </para>
                    </warning><tip>
                      <para>Create only one account per required currency. The different customers or suppliers are
                        automatically by &app; keeps them apart.
                      </para>
                    </tip>
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>This is typically a business use only account in which you place outstanding debts owed to you. It
                is considered an asset because you should be able to count on these funds arriving.<footnote>
                  <para>Previous versions of this help defined A/P and A/R the other way round.
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c2" nameend="c3">
              <para>(Fixed assets; long-term)
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Stock
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>A share of ownership in a corporation, which entitles its owner to all the risks and rewards that go
                with it.<footnote>
                  <para><ulink url="&url-wp-en;Share_(finance)"/>
                  </para>
                </footnote><footnote>
                  <para><tip>
                      <para>As long as cryptocurrencies are not supported by &app; as currencies, it is recommended that they be
                        also be invested as shares.
                      </para>
                    </tip>
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Mutual fund
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>A professionally managed portfolio of stocks and bonds or other investments divided up into shares.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1" morerows="4">
              <para>Liabilities
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c2" nameend="c3">
              <para>The second balance sheet account is Liabilities, refers to what you owe, money you have borrowed and
                are obligated to pay back some day. These represent the rights of your lenders to
                obtain repayment from you.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Liability
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Liability accounts are used for tracking debts or financial obligations. (Normally a placeholder
                account)
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Credit Card
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>The Credit Card account type is used to denote credit card accounts, both for cards that allow
                floating lines of credit (e.g. VISA, MasterCard, or Discover) and with cards that do
                not permit continuing balances (e.g. American Express)
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Accounts Payable <footnoteref linkend="fn-receivables-kat" />
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Accounts Payable are used by businesses to record amounts that must be paid.<footnote>
                  <para>Previous versions of this help defined A/P and A/R the other way round.
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Equity
                <footnote id="fn-equity-kat">
                  <para><caution>
                      <para><computeroutput>Equity</computeroutput> and its temporary variants.
                        <computeroutput>Income</computeroutput> and
                        <computeroutput>Expense</computeroutput> should always be kept in the local
                        currency when official accounts are kept.
                      </para>
                    </caution>
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Equity Accounts represents your net economic value. This type of account is only posted at two
                times: When you start your book, the opening balances are offset here. (see
                <xref linkend="open-balance" />). And at the end of an posting period, &app; uses
                this account to make the <xref linkend="tool-close-book" /> to record. For a
                household, it is recommended to create one account/tree per resident.
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c4">
              <para>Only Equity accounts
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
              <para>Profit &amp; Loss<footnote id="fn-quick-kat">
                  <para>Often referred to as a <quote>Category</quote> in <application>Quicken</application> or
                    <application>Lexware FinanzManager</application> and other programmes that are
                    not based on double-entry bookkeeping.
                  </para>
                </footnote>
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3" nameend="c4">
              <para>If required, at the next account level you can insert the distinction between taxable/tax-free, or
                tax deductible or not. The evaluation<menuchoice>
                  <guimenu><accel>R</accel>eports</guimenu><guisubmenu><accel>I</accel>ncome &amp;
                  Expense</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>P<accel>r</accel>ofit &amp; Loss</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>gives you an overview for any <emphasis>period</emphasis> such as e.g. the business year.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry namest="c1">
              <para>Income <footnoteref linkend="fn-equity-kat" />
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Any income received from sources such as salary, interest, dividends, etc.
                <footnoteref linkend="fn-quick-kat" />
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c4" morerows="1">
              <para>Only Expense or Income accounts
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1">
              <para>Expense <footnoteref linkend="fn-equity-kat" />
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Any expense such as food, clothing, taxes, etc. <footnoteref linkend="fn-quick-kat" />
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The wizard <xref linkend="chart-create" /> offers a convenient method to configure a usable basic
      framework for configuring your account tree.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>In certain situations, &app; automatically creates some special other accounts. Below you will find
        a short list of why these accounts are suddenly included in your account structure and how
        to deal with them.
      </para>
    </note>

    <table frame="topbot">
      <title>Types of &appname;&rsquo;s internal accounts</title>

      <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
        <colspec colname="c1"></colspec>

        <colspec colname="c2"></colspec>

        <colspec colname="c3"></colspec>

        <colspec colname="c4"></colspec>

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Status
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Account type/ Account name
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Description
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Parent account
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
              <para>internal accounts
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3" nameend="c4">
              <para>Internal accounts are not created by the user, but by &app; if required.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1">
              <para>regular operation
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Trading
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>Multiple currency transactions have splits in “Trading” accounts to make the transaction balance
                in each currency as well as in total value. As soon as you make the first purchase,
                such as exchanging your home currency into that of the holiday destination, an
                account is created for both currencies, if it does not already exist. The details
                are described in <ulink url="&tit-sel-tut;"></ulink> and
                <ulink url="&tit-sel-gnc;"></ulink>.
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c4">
              <para>Trading accounts only
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row rowsep="1">
            <entry namest="c1">
              <para>Error case
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c2">
              <para>Orphan-<replaceable>XXX</replaceable>, Imbalance-<replaceable>XXX</replaceable>
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c3">
              <para>You have entered at least one unbalanced transaction. To correct this, move the contained
                transactions to the correct accounts. You can then delete the account.
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry namest="c4">
              <para>Only assets and liabilities accounts
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="chart-create">
    <title>Creating a Chart of Accounts</title>

    <para>The chart of accounts is the - hierarchically arranged - table of contents of your accounts. &app;
      can support you in your work with the <xref linkend="acct-hierarchy" /> wizard.
    </para>

    <para>The Chart of Accounts is like a table of contents for your finances. The best way to conceptualize a
      chart of accounts is as a tree. The main branches represent entire categories or groups, while
      the leaves of the tree denote individual bank accounts or expense categories. When a summary
      report is requested, typically only the main branches are shown in the report, rather than the
      individual accounts.
    </para>

    <para>For example, a chart of accounts might look like the following:<xi:include href="Help_chtacctseg.xml"/>
    </para>

    <tip id="accts-code">
      <title>Accounts codes</title>

      <para>Since it is difficult to visualise factual relationships with alphabetical sorting by account name,
        it is recommended to use and sort by alphanumeric account numbers. When a report is
        generated, the sort order is determined by the numbering. It&rsquo;s customary to have the
        leaf accounts end in non-zero digits, while parent nodes have increasing numbers of zeros
        and are marked as <xref linkend="accts-placeholder" />.
      </para>
    </tip>

    <tip>
      <para>&app; does not prevent duplicate numbering, but it is recommended that you avoid this in order to
        achieve uniqueness. It is advisable to use the digits first when defining the account
        numbers. If these are not sufficient, you can also use the letters <quote>a</quote> to
        <quote>z</quote>. &app; can help you with the numbering your accounts. To do this, use the
        wizard<menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu><guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>enumber
          subaccounts…</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>To help. An example is described in <xref linkend="chart-renumber" />.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect1>

<!-- FIXME moved von GettingStarted -->
<!-- FIXME After GettingStarted has been revised, change ID to id="acct-hierarchy"  -->
  <sect1 id="acct-hierarchy_new">
    <title>New Account Hierarchy Setup</title>

    <para>With the support of this wizard, you can create a complete chart of accounts for your daily work. A
      new, empty &app; file is created and the wizard <guilabel>New Account Hierarchy
      Setup</guilabel> is started.
    </para>

    <tip>
      <para>You can run the wizard again later. To do this, go to<menuchoice>
          <shortcut>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap>
          </keycombo>
          </shortcut> <guimenu><accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu> <guimenuitem>New <accel>F</accel>ile
          </guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>in the menu if you want to create a new file. If you want to run the wizard inside the open file,
        use<menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>A</accel>ction</guimenu><guimenuitem>New Account
          <accel>H</accel>ierarchy… </guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>instead when the account hierarchy tab is displayed.
      </para>
    </tip>

    <figure pgwide="1">
      <title>The wizard <quote>New Account Hierarchy Setup</quote></title><screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="figures/AccountTreeCreate.png" srccredit="Christian Wehling" width="&img-w;" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="figures/AccountTreeCreate.png" srccredit="Christian Wehling" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Dialogue guidance</title>

      <para>The buttons in the wizard will only be visible or activated after you have made the necessary
        settings in the dialog step.
      </para>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton><accel>C</accel>ancel</guibutton></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ends the operation and cancels the creation of a new account hierarchy.
          </para>

          <warning>
            <para>If you click on this button, all changes that you have made up to this point will be lost.
            </para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton><accel>B</accel>ack</guibutton></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Returns you to the previous display so that you can change your entries again.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton><accel>N</accel>ext</guibutton></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Press the key to confirm your entries and move on to the next screen.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton><accel>F</accel>inish</guibutton></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Skips the next step <guilabel>Setup selected accounts</guilabel> and brings you you directly to the
            last step of the wizard.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><guibutton><accel>A</accel>pply</guibutton></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This completes your entries and the new account structure is created in the &app;file.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <procedure>
      <title>Description of the steps in the wizard</title>

      <step>
        <title><guilabel>New Account Hierarchy Setup</guilabel></title>

        <para>The wizard starts with a short introduction page.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title><guilabel>New Book Options</guilabel></title>

        <para><note>
            <para>This dialog step is <emphasis>not</emphasis> displayed if you start the wizard in the account view
              of an existing &app;file with the menu item<menuchoice>
                <guimenu><accel>A</accel>ction</guimenu><guimenuitem>New
                Account<accel>H</accel>ierach… </guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>.
            </para>
          </note>In this step, you can make general settings for the &app;, which will be are saved in the file and
          thus apply to all users. The dialog is described in detail in
          <xref linkend="book-options" />.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title><guilabel>Choose Currency</guilabel></title>

        <para>In the next screen you can select the currency you want to use as default for the book-specific base
          currency.
        </para>

        <para>By default, the dropdown list is set to the currency specified in the
          <xref linkend="prefs-accounts"/> in the <guilabel>&appname; settings</guilabel>. You can
          reach this dialog in the menu<menuchoice>
            <guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Pr<accel>e</accel>ferences</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>. If you want to use a different default currency for your accounts instead, select it from the
          list.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title><guilabel>Choose accounts to create</guilabel></title>

        <para>This step is used to create the account structure. You will see a screen divided into three parts.
        </para>

        <substeps>
          <step>
            <title><guilabel>Categories</guilabel></title>

            <para>In the upper left part, there are two drop-down boxes that allow you to filter the language- and
              region-specific categories. Select from the list box below the selection boxes, the
              types of accounts you want to use for your work in &app;. This way you can select many
              of the categories from a locale for your accounts. If you want to mix accounts from
              different locales you have to go through the wizard once for each scheme.
            </para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <title><guibutton>Select all</guibutton></title>

            <para>The button allows you to select all account categories.
            </para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <title><guibutton>Clear all</guibutton></title>

            <para>Use this button to deselect all the selected categories.
            </para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <title><guilabel>Category Description</guilabel></title>

            <para>In the lower left area there is a field that displays a detailed description of the currently
              selected category. Here the creators of the region-specific modules provide detailed
              information on the individual modules.
            </para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <title><guilabel>Accounts in …</guilabel></title>

            <para>On the right side there is a preview of the accounts that correspond to the category highlighted on
              the left.
            </para>
          </step>
        </substeps>

        <tip>
          <para>In this step the wizard offers you a shortcut. The button
            <guibutton><accel>F</accel>inish</guibutton> takes you directly to the last step.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title><guilabel>Setup selected accounts</guilabel></title>

        <para>Continuing with the step where for each individual account you can, if needed, adjust the account
          name enter an opening balance or define whether an account should act as a placeholder.
        </para>

        <note id="placeholder-acct">
          <para><emphasis>Placeholder accounts</emphasis> form a kind of group heading and are used to create a
            hierarchy of accounts. The account book of accounts marked in this way is read-only.
          </para>
        </note>

        <note>
          <para>Since the opening balance account is an equity account, the entry for this type of account is is
            prevented and set to <guilabel>Null</guilabel> by &app;. The opening balance is entered
            into the account book as a normal entry and you can add to it, correct it or delete it.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>Follow the instructions on the display to select an account and enter an opening balance. A single
          click is used to highlight an account.
        </para>

        <variablelist>
          <title>The table column headers</title>

          <para>You can change some entries for the accounts by selecting the corresponding entry in the column and
            then clicking in the cell you want to edit.
          </para>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Account Name</guilabel></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The first column contains the names for the accounts. You can change the account name according to
                your needs.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Type</guilabel></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The entries in this column are for your information and cannot be changed.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The third column contains a checkbox that allows you to specify whether this account should be a
                placeholder account. This gives you the possibility to create a hierarchical
                structuring of your accounts.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><guilabel>Opening Balance</guilabel></term>

            <listitem>
              <para>In this field of the fourth column, you can enter an opening balance, if necessary, by entering it
                in the cell. Furthermore, a note is entered here by &app;, whether this account
                already exists in an existing account structure and therefore will not be created.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Use Existing</term>

            <listitem>
              <para><note>
                  <para>This column is displayed only if you want to add more accounts to an existing account structure.
                  </para>
                </note>The last column informs you whether an account with this name already exists in your structure or
                not.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>The final step <guilabel>Finish Account Setup</guilabel> is the last screen and gives you a final
          overview of the three choices to complete the Wizard to finish.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <para>You now have a structure of accounts in your &app; accounts overview.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="chart-edit">
    <title>Editing a Chart of Accounts</title>

    <para>Editing the Chart of Accounts is done within the <guilabel>Parent Account</guilabel> pane of the
      <guilabel>Edit Account</guilabel> dialog. It is possible to move an account to any part of the
      Chart of Accounts. It is recommended to keep accounts generally under the related types of
      accounts as described in <xref linkend="acct-types" />. This helps to preserve the Chart of
      Accounts structure.
    </para>

    <para>To move the selected account to a different parent account just select the account in the
      <guilabel>Parent Account</guilabel> pane. If <guilabel>New top level account</guilabel> is
      selected then the account will be moved to the top level.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="acct-create">
    <title>Creating a New Account</title>

    <para>To create a new account go to<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>New Account...</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>or click the <guibutton>New</guibutton> <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> icon in the Account Tree
      Window. The <guilabel>New Account</guilabel> dialog will be opened.
    </para>

    <para>The <guilabel>New Account</guilabel> properties dialog consists of two tabs, the
      <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab and the <guilabel>Opening Balance</guilabel> tab.
    </para>

    <para>Creating a New Account involves planning in advance several details that are used in the
      <guilabel>New Account</guilabel> dialog.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What type of account is needed.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Where it fits in the structure of the Chart of Accounts.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If there is an Opening Balance.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If there is a Commodity (security/currency) needed for the account.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If online updating of the commodity price is needed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>These details are described below.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="gen-info">
      <title>General Information Tab</title>

      <para>The <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab is used to access the basic information about the account. It
        provides a way of connecting the account to stock information if it is one of the currency,
        mutual fund or stock account types. It can also be flagged as a
        <link linkend="accts-placeholder">Placeholder</link> account. It displays if it is flagged
        as a <guilabel>Tax Related</guilabel> account (which is set through the<menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Tax Report Options</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>dialog).
      </para>

      <para>There are seven fields in the <guilabel>Identification</guilabel> section of this tab.
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Account Name:</guilabel> The name for the account such as First Bank Checking.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Account Code:</guilabel> The optional number code as described in
            <xref linkend="accts-code" />.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Description:</guilabel> Optional description for the account.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Security/Currency:</guilabel>
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>The <guilabel>Type</guilabel> field in the <guilabel>Select Security</guilabel> is determined by the
              selection of <guilabel>Account Type</guilabel> panel in the <guilabel>New
              Account</guilabel> screen.
            </para>
          </note>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>For accounts other than <emphasis>Stock</emphasis> or <emphasis>Mutual Fund</emphasis> this should
                be the default currency, USD (US Dollar) or your local currency symbol. If this
                account is for a foreign currency then use the <guibutton>Select...</guibutton>
                button to choose a different currency from the currencies pull-down list.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For Accounts containing a <emphasis>Stock</emphasis> and <emphasis>Mutual Fund</emphasis>; first
                select <guilabel>stock</guilabel> or <guilabel>mutual fund</guilabel> in the
                <guilabel>Account Type</guilabel> panel, then the <guilabel>Parent
                Account</guilabel>, then use the <guibutton>Select...</guibutton> button, to choose
                the <guilabel>Type</guilabel> (usually the exchange the security is traded on) and
                security from the <guilabel>Select Security</guilabel> window.
              </para>

              <para>If the required security/fund is not on the list, and you have the correct <guilabel>Type</guilabel>
                you will need to create the security/fund. To create a commodity for mutual fund and
                stock accounts select the <guibutton>New...</guibutton> button in the
                <guilabel>Select Security</guilabel> screen, to bring up the <guilabel>New
                Security:</guilabel> screen. The options are described in detail in the Security
                Editor <xref linkend="tool-security-edit"></xref> section. Fill in a
                <guilabel>name</guilabel>, <guilabel>symbol</guilabel> and <guilabel>type</guilabel>
                and <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to create the security. After the security is
                created select the <guilabel>Type:</guilabel> (usually the exchange the security is
                traded on) and the name in the <guilabel>Currency/security:</guilabel> drop down
                list and <guibutton>Close</guibutton> the screen.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Smallest Fraction:</guilabel> The smallest fraction that will be tracked.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Account Color:</guilabel> The color to assign to the account&rsquo;s register tab. Click
            on the color button to open the <guilabel>Pick a Color</guilabel> screen. To reset the
            account color click the <guibutton>Default</guibutton> button.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Notes:</guilabel> This is a free form text box that can be used for any additional notes
            about the account.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Below the panes are 3 check-boxes: one to show if the account is <guilabel>Tax Related</guilabel>,
        one to mark the account as a <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel>, and one to mark an account
        <guilabel>Hidden</guilabel>.
      </para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Tax Related</guilabel> check-box means that an account has been flagged to be included
        in the Tax Schedule Report. This flag is only displayed on the <guilabel>Edit
        Account</guilabel> dialog and is set in the <guilabel>Income Tax Information</guilabel>
        dialog (<menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Tax Report Options</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>). For related reports see the examples like <guilabel>Tax Schedule Report and TXF Export</guilabel>
        in (<xref linkend="report-regional"/>).
      </para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel> check-box sets an account to read-only status and prevents the
        addition of transaction data to the account.
      </para>

      <note id="accts-placeholder">
        <para>Setting an account to <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel> will also hide that account in the pop-up
          account list in a register. Sub-accounts to the placeholder account will still display in
          the pop-up, however.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>The <guilabel>Hidden</guilabel> check box hides an account (and any sub-accounts) in the account
        tree. To reset this option, you will first need to open the<menuchoice>
          <guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Filter By...</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>dialog for the account tree and check the <guilabel>Show hidden accounts</guilabel> option. Doing so
        will allow you to select the account and reopen this dialog.
      </para>

      <note id="accts-hidden">
        <para>Hidden accounts still appear in the pop-up account list in a register. To remove an account from
          this pop-up account list as well, check the <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel> check box.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>Below these checkboxes is a pane that contains a list of <guilabel>Account Types</guilabel>. Select
        a type from the descriptions in <xref linkend="acct-types" />.
      </para>

      <para>The next pane contains an account tree to choose a <guilabel>Parent Account</guilabel>. To create a
        new account tree select <guilabel>New top level account</guilabel>.<note>
          <para>The available choices in the <guilabel>Account Type</guilabel> pane depends on the selected account
            in the <guilabel>Parent Account</guilabel> pane. For example if the <guilabel>Parent
            Account</guilabel> is <emphasis>Assets</emphasis> you will see only
            <emphasis>Equity</emphasis> in the <guilabel>Account Type</guilabel> pane. This is to
            help maintain a proper account structure for the Chart of Accounts.
          </para>
        </note>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="accts-online-quotes">
      <title>Steps to enable Online Quotes updating</title>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>&app; uses an external tool to retrieve online courses. This tool is a Perl module called &app-fq;
            and must be installed independently of &app; on your computer.
          </para>

          <tip>
            <para>The installation of &app-fq; is described under <xref linkend="finance-quote-install" />.
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create the Account for the mutual fund or stock with it listed in the
            <guilabel>Security/Currency</guilabel> field, as described above.
          </para>

          <tip>
            <para>When creating these accounts it is a good time to create income accounts to track dividends, capital
              gains (long and short) and expense account(s) for tracking commissions and losses (if
              you track losses as expenses).
            </para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create the mutual fund or stock with either the <guilabel>Security Editor</guilabel> for existing
            stock/funds or the <guilabel>New Security/Currency</guilabel> dialog for a new
            stock/fund.
          </para>

          <para>Select <guilabel>Get Online Quotes</guilabel>, <guilabel>Type of Quote Source</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>Timezone.</guilabel>
          </para>

          <para>Online currency quotes require that the check-box for Online quotes and the timezone be selected in
            the Security screen and the Security Editor check-box for "get quote" box is checked for
            those currencies that are to be downloaded.
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Get Online Quotes</guilabel> This check-box is to enable this security/fund to have quotes
                downloaded from an online source.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Type of Quote Source</guilabel> use the radio buttons to select the type of source for the
                Online quotes. <guilabel>Multiple:</guilabel> quote sources like
                <quote>Europe</quote> should be used if fail-over to multiple sites are desirable.
                <guilabel>Single:</guilabel> selections will only return information from the
                specified source.
              </para>

              <para>After selecting the type of source for price quotes, select a quote source from the pull-down menu.
                For details on currently supported sources see <xref linkend="fq-sources"></xref>.
              </para>

              <note>
                <para>Note that Yahoo will provide price quotes for many mutual funds including Fidelity, T.Rowe Price and
                  Vanguard, and that the quoted prices at Yahoo should be identical to those that
                  may be found at the source sites.
                </para>
              </note>

              <para>If you are outside the US and use one of the different Yahoo sources or multiple sources containing
                Yahoo, you should append the market code for the security such as PA for Paris, BE
                for Berlin, etc. Example: 12150.PA (a Peugeot security in the Paris market).
                <xref linkend="gnc-tbl-fq-yahoo-exchange-codes"></xref> below lists suffixes for
                various markets around the world.
              </para>

              <para>Pseudo-symbols for TIAA-CREF funds are listed in table <xref linkend="PsSymbs-TIAA-CREF"></xref>.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Timezone for these quotes:</guilabel> Select the timezone for the source of the online
                quotes you are receiving. For example, Yahoo normally quotes Eastern timezone, so
                choose America/New York if you use that quote source.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select a commodity to the Price Editor.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select <guibutton>Get Quotes</guibutton> in the Price Editor.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Check the latest price for the selected security.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Remember that Mutual Fund <quote>prices</quote> are really <quote>Net Asset Value</quote> and
        require several hours after the exchange closes before being available. If NAVs are
        downloaded before the current days NAVs are determined, yesterday&rsquo;s NAVs are
        retrieved.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="open-balance">
      <title>Opening Balance tab</title>

      <para>The <guilabel>Opening Balance</guilabel> tab is visible only when creating a new account, and is
        disabled for <guilabel>Stock</guilabel> and <guilabel>Mutual Fund</guilabel> accounts. In
        the latter case, opening balances must be created by hand. Please see Section 8.5.1 in the
        <emphasis role="italic">Tutorial and Concepts Guide</emphasis> for instructions if you need
        to create an opening balance in a <guilabel>Stock</guilabel> or <guilabel>Mutual
        Fund</guilabel> account. It is used to record the beginning balance for an account. This
        allows it to be used for two different scenarios. If using &app; for the first time to
        record transactions, it can be used as a beginning balance. If the accounts in use are
        closed at the end of a period and new accounts are created, it is used to close and carry
        balances forward.
      </para>

      <para>There are three panes in this tab. The top pane contains the <guilabel>Balance
        Information</guilabel>.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Balance:</guilabel> The balance to start the account with.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Date:</guilabel> The date the opening balance should be recorded.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The next pane is the <guilabel>Transfer Type</guilabel> pane.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Use Opening Balances Equity account:</guilabel> This transfers the opening balance for the
            account from a standard Equity account called Opening Balances.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guilabel>Select Transfer Account:</guilabel> This enables the pane below so a different account can
            be used to transfer the opening balance.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The last pane is the <guilabel>Transfer Account</guilabel> pane. Select the account to use for
        opening balances from the list of accounts in this pane.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="acct-edit">
    <title>Editing an Account</title>

    <para>The <guilabel>Edit Account</guilabel> dialog consists of just the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab.
      This tab has the same information that was described in <xref linkend="acct-create"></xref>.
      To access the <guilabel>Edit Account</guilabel> dialog go to<menuchoice>
        <shortcut>
        <keycombo>
          <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>E</keycap>
        </keycombo>
        </shortcut> <guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit Account</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>or click the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> icon in the Account Tree
      Window.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="chart-renumber">
    <title>Renumbering Subaccounts</title>

    <para>Use <guilabel>Renumber Subaccounts</guilabel> to rewrite the account codes for all children of the
      current account. For example, you have the following account structure:
    </para>

    <table frame="topbot" id="table-renumber1">
      <title>Starting account numbers.</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Code
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Name
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Colors
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-1
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Red
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-2
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Orange
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-3
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Yellow.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-4
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Blue
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-5
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Violet
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>You now need to add the <quote>Green</quote> account, but you want it to sort between the Yellow and
      Blue accounts. Instead of having to manually renumber all the accounts starting with Blue, you
      can use the <guilabel>Renumber subaccount</guilabel> command on the Colors account. In the
      pop-up dialog the prefix value should default to <quote>10</quote>, the account code for the
      colors account. If you set an interval value of <quote>5</quote> and click
      <guilabel>Renumber</guilabel> you will end up with the following account structure:
    </para>

    <table frame="topbot" id="table-renumber2">
      <title>Renumbered account numbers</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Code
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Name
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Colors
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-05
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Red
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-10
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Orange
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-15
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Yellow.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-20
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Blue
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-25
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Violet
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>Now you have room in the account code numbering space to add the Green account with an account code
      to force the proper ordering.
    </para>

    <table frame="topbot" id="table-renumber3">
      <title>Final account numbers.</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Code
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Name
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Colors
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-05
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Red
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-10
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Orange
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-15
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Yellow.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-18
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Green
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-20
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Blue
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>10-25
              </para>
            </entry>

            <entry>
              <para>Violet
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="acct-delete">
    <title>Deleting an Account</title>

    <para></para>

    <para>Deleting an Account means removing all transaction information and information about this account
      from the file. This cannot be undone. You will be prompted to verify that you wish to remove
      the account. If the account still contains transaction information you will be warned that
      this account contains transactions.
    </para>

    <para>A side effect of removing an account that contains transactions is that you will end up with
      unbalanced accounts. This will be indicated in the account by a gray check-box next to the
      debit and credit amounts. You can automatically repair these unbalanced accounts by using the<menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Actions</guimenu><guimenuitem>Check &amp; Repair</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>menu. This will automatically assign the unbalanced amounts to a new account named
      <emphasis role="bold">Imbalance. </emphasis>
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="acct-reconcile">
    <title>Reconciling an Account to a Statement</title>

    <para>Reconciliation of Accounts in &app; with statements from a bank or other institution is a way of
      double checking the accuracy of your (and your banks) transactions and the balance of your
      accounts. It also is useful to track uncleared checks and other outstanding transactions.
    </para>

    <para>The reconciling process in &app; involves two dialogs: the <xref linkend="tool-reconcile" /> dialog
      followed by the <xref linkend="rec-win" /> window. They provide access to various &app;
      functions to make it easy to enter and update account information during the reconciliation.
    </para>

    <tip>
      <para>The Reconcile window is accessed from the account tree window or the account register window by
        selecting<menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>A</accel>ctions</guimenu><guimenuitem><accel>R</accel>econcile…</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
    </tip>

    <note>
      <para>If you are reconciling an Liability Account of type <guilabel>credit card</guilabel> using a credit
        card statement you have the option of using the <guilabel>Transfer Funds</guilabel> dialogue
        that opens automatically and enter a credit card payment. You can change this behaviour in
        the <guilabel>&appname; Preferences</guilabel> from the menu<menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>E</accel>dit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Pr<accel>e</accel>ferences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>in the <guilabel>Register</guilabel> tab by activating the checkbox <guilabel>Automatic credit card
        payment</guilabel>. (see <xref linkend="prefs-reg" />)
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>The <emphasis>Summary Bar</emphasis> at the bottom of the Account Register Window indicates the
      amounts of <guilabel>Present</guilabel> (Balance), <guilabel>Future</guilabel> (Balance),
      <guilabel>Cleared</guilabel> (Transactions), <guilabel>Reconciled</guilabel> (Transactions)
      and <guilabel>Projected Minimum</guilabel>. Online account information can be used to mark
      which transactions the bank has processed by changing the <guilabel>R</guilabel>
      (reconciliation status) column in the register from <guilabel>n</guilabel> (new) to
      <guilabel>c</guilabel> (cleared). The bank statement is then used with the
      <guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> window to reconcile the account which changes the
      <guilabel>R</guilabel> field to <guilabel>y</guilabel> (reconciled).
    </para>

    <sect2 id="tool-reconcile">
      <title>Reconciling Information</title>

      <para>The <guilabel>Reconcile Information</guilabel> dialog is used to indicate the closing
        <guilabel>Statement Date</guilabel> and the <guilabel>Starting Balance</guilabel> (fixed
        from last reconciliation) and <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> from the statement. The
        <guilabel>Include Sub-accounts</guilabel> check-box is used if one or more subaccounts are
        used to track the account you are reconciling. The <guibutton>Enter Interest
        Payment</guibutton> button is used to add a transfer to the accounts for an interest
        payment. If selected a dialog will be displayed to add the <xref linkend="tool-ent-int" />
        to the account.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>The <guibutton>Enter Interest Payment</guibutton> button is shown only if you are reconciling an
          account of <emphasis>Bank</emphasis> type.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>When you have entered all relevant data, press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> to proceed to the
        <xref linkend="rec-win" /> dialog or <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> to discard the
        reconciliation process.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="tool-ent-int">
        <title>Interest Payment</title>

        <para>There are three panes in the <guilabel>Interest Payment</guilabel> dialog. At the bottom is a button
          called <guibutton>No Auto Interest Payments for this Account</guibutton> which will cancel
          the dialog. The top pane contains the <guilabel>Payment Information</guilabel>.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Amount:</guilabel> Enter the amount of the interest payment.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Date:</guilabel> Select the date for the interest payment.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Num:</guilabel> Enter a number for the transaction (optional).
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Description:</guilabel> Enter an informational description for the transaction.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guilabel>Memo:</guilabel> Enter a note about the transaction (optional).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The <guilabel>Reconcile Account</guilabel> pane highlights in the tree the account that the interest
          payment will be transferred to or from.
        </para>

        <para>The <guilabel>Payment From</guilabel> pane contains a list of accounts where you can select the
          source account.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>If the payment is for a credit or loan account then usually the payment would be from an
            <emphasis>Expense</emphasis> account. If the payment is for a checking or savings
            account then usually this would be from an <emphasis>Income</emphasis> account.
          </para>
        </note>

        <tip>
          <para>The <guibutton>Show Income/Expense</guibutton> check-box shows or hides the
            <emphasis>Income</emphasis> and <emphasis>Expense</emphasis> accounts.
          </para>
        </tip>

        <para>Select <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to enter the interest transaction (or <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>
          the payment) and return to the initial reconciliation screen.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rec-win">
      <title>Reconcile</title>

      <note>
        <para>For a detailed description of menu items and buttons on the reconcile window, see
          <xref linkend="gui-reconcile" />.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>The <guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> dialog is where the actual process of matching your statement to
        &app; data takes place on a per transaction basis.
      </para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> dialog is composed of a <emphasis>toolbar</emphasis> and three
        panes; <guilabel>Funds In</guilabel> on the left, <guilabel>Funds out</guilabel> on the
        right and a balance pane.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>If you enabled the option <guilabel>Use formal accounting labels</guilabel> in the
          <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> section of the &app; preferences, you will see
          <guilabel>Debits</guilabel> and <guilabel>Credits</guilabel> panes instead of
          <guilabel>Funds In</guilabel> and <guilabel>Funds Out</guilabel> panes.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>The <guilabel>Funds In</guilabel> and <guilabel>Funds Out</guilabel> pane shows all unreconciled
        deposits to the account. Both panes are composed of five columns.
      </para>

      <tip>
        <para>To order the listed transactions with a preferred criteria, click on the relevant column header. To
          reverse the selected order click a second time on the column header.
        </para>
      </tip>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Date</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The date of the unreconciled transaction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Num</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The number of the unreconciled transaction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Description</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Description of the unreconciled transaction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Amount</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Amount of the unreconciled transaction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>R</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Shows a check if the transaction will be reconciled when done.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>To mark a transaction as reconciled just click on it and a checkmark will appear on the relevant
        <guilabel>R</guilabel> column.
      </para>

      <tip>
        <para>You can check or uncheck the reconcile status of all transactions in either pane by clicking on a
          transaction in the required pane then clicking <keycap>Ctrl-A</keycap> followed by
          <keycap>space</keycap>. This will toggle the reconcile status of all transactions in the
          pane to either checked or unchecked state. This procedure can be repeated to achieve the
          desired status for the transactions in the pane.
        </para>
      </tip>

      <note>
        <para>Under each pane a <guilabel>Total</guilabel> for reconciled transactions is shown.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>The balance pane shows a summary of the balances used in reconciliation.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Statement Date</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The date on the statement set on the <xref linkend="tool-reconcile" />.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Starting Balance</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The balance at the end of the last reconciliation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The balance entered from the statement.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Reconciled Balance</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The balance of selected transactions.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><guilabel>Difference</guilabel></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The difference between the <guilabel>Reconciled</guilabel> and <guilabel>Ending</guilabel> balances.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The set of unreconciled transactions in the <guilabel>Funds In</guilabel> and <guilabel>Funds
        Out</guilabel> panes can be changed by using the menus and <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> to
        access the account and transaction information. You can create a <guibutton>New</guibutton>
        transaction, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> a selected transaction, add a
        <guilabel>Balance</guilabel> transaction (of the same amount as listed under
        <guilabel>Difference</guilabel> in the balance pane), and delete the selected transaction.
      </para>

      <tip>
        <para>To modify a listed transaction, double click on it.
        </para>
      </tip>

      <para>By pressing the <guilabel>Open</guilabel> icon the register of the account to reconcile will be
        opened.
      </para>

      <para>If you wish to postpone the reconciliation until later use the<menuchoice>
          <shortcut>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>P</keycap>
          </keycombo>
          </shortcut> <guimenu><accel>R</accel>econcile</guimenu><guimenuitem>Postpone</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>menu item or pressing the <guibutton>Postpone</guibutton> icon. If you wish to cancel the
        reconciliation use the<menuchoice>
          <guimenu><accel>R</accel>econcile</guimenu><guimenuitem>Cancel</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>menu item or press the <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> icon.
      </para>

      <para>All previous commands are also available in the <guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> dialog menu.
      </para>

      <para>Select each unreconciled transaction matching a transaction on the statement so a green tick appears
        in the <guilabel>R</guilabel> column. The <guilabel>Balance</guilabel> pane changes to
        reflect each selected transaction until the <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel>
        <emphasis>equals</emphasis> the <guilabel>Reconciled Balance</guilabel> and the
        <guilabel>Difference</guilabel> is <emphasis>zero</emphasis>. Once this is done select the
        <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> button or<menuchoice>
          <shortcut>
          <keycombo>
            <keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>W</keycap>
          </keycombo>
          </shortcut> <guimenu><accel>R</accel>econcile</guimenu><guimenuitem>Finish</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>to finish the reconcile process.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
