<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 1.6.5
  Last modified: November 24, 2001
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Written by Chris Lyttle
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
 <chapter id="appendix-a">
 <title>Appendix A Migration Guide</title>
 <para>
This appendix is to help current users of other financial software packages in their migration to GnuCash.  We address the conceptual differences between the layout of GnuCash accounts versus other software packages.
  </para>

<sect1 id="accts_vs_cats1">
<title>Using Accounts vs. Categories</title>
<para>
If you are familiar with other personal finance programs, you are already accustomed to tracking your income and expenses as categories. Since Gnucash is a double-entry system (refer to section 2.1), incomes and expenses are tracked in accounts. The basic concept is the same, but the account structure allows more consistency with accepted business practices. So, if you are a business user as well as a home user, Gnucash makes it easy to keep track of your business as well as your personal accounts.
</para>
<para>
Income and expense accounts give you the same information you would get with categories, but they also give you more flexibility in entering your transactions.    In GnuCash, you have the option to enter transactions directly into income and expense accounts through their account registers.   Other programs that use categories do not offer this option, because there is no <quote>account register</quote> for a category.
</para>
<para>
You also have the option in GnuCash to treat income and expense accounts exactly as you would treat categories, if you are more comfortable with that method.  In <trademark class="registered">Quicken</trademark> and similar programs,  transactions require an account and a category.   Substitute an income or expense account name in GnuCash where you would normally enter a category name in the other programs, and the result should be the same.   We will discuss transaction entry in Chapter 4 in greater detail.
</para>
</sect1>

 <sect1 id="qif1">
 <title>Organization of QIF Files (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="entercharge1">
 <title>Common Duplication Issues (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="enterpay1">
 <title>Checking QIF Data (Discussion)</title>
 <para>
 </para>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>

 <chapter id="appendix-b">
 <title>Appendix B Frequently Asked Questions</title>
 <para>
 (Notes: How to treat taxes (payable or expense?), how to record a txn on different 
dates (actual date and bank date), how to provide security for GC data using CFS, 
etc.)
  </para>
 <sect1 id="faq1">
 <title>FAQ</title>
 <para>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>

 <chapter id="appendix-c">
 <title>Appendix C Troubleshooting Guide</title>
 <para>
   </para>
 <sect1 id="trouble1">
 <title>I'm in Trouble</title>
 <para>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 </chapter>
