<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 1.6.5
  Last modified: November 24, 2001
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Written by Chris Lyttle
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
 <appendix id="appendixb">
 <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
 <para>This is a list of questions asked on the mailing lists for which there really is no section in the documentation covering the subject.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: How can I move the transactions from account A into account B, thus combining them?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: There is no easy way to do this, you will need to change every transaction reference for account A to account B.  Use the "Find Transactions" feature and search for splits where Account = account A.  This will list all of them in a single journal-style register window where you can actually edit the
accounts.  Change the transfer account in each from A to B.  As you edit the transactions they will be removed from the register. When the register is empty, account A will be empty and you can remove it.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: How can I save a template of my account structure?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: This is available from the menu: <guimenu>File</guimenu> -> <guimenu>Export</guimenu> -> <guimenu>Accounts</guimenu></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: When I search for customers (or anything else for that matter), how can I return a list of everything?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: Enter a search criteria of <guilabel>matches regex</guilabel>, and place a single dot "." in the text field area. Then, click <guibutton>Find</guibutton>. The regular expression "." means to match anything.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: Can I run GnuCash on Windows?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: No, GnuCash is not developed on (or for) Windows.</para>
  <para>If you must run GnuCash from a Windows machine, your best bet is to use VNC to run GnuCash remotely from a UNIX server.  Another possibility would be to install VMWare (www.vmware.com) on your windows machine and run a copy of Linux within VMWare.  We don't have many (any?) windows developers, so nobody is really working hard on a port to windows....</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: Is there a batch mode (non-interactive) available for GnuCash, for building reports, etc?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: No, for now GnuCash must be run interactively.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: Can multiple people access the same datafile in GnuCash?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: You can have multiple people with access to the same datafile, but they cannot use the data file simultaneously.</para>
  <para>To setup multi-person access, all the people must have read/write access to the directory containing the file (to read the other's created files, and to create new files).  One way to do this is by creating a user group and setting the data directory to be owned by the shared group and set to mode 2775. The '2' makes the directory setgid which copies the permissions to all files.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: How to treat taxes?  As an account payable or as an expense?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: This is a loaded question, and you should really talk to your accountant.  How you treat taxes really depends on what kind of taxes they are, and how you WANT to treat them..  In some cases they are expenses, in some cases they are liabilities.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: How to record a transaction on different dates (actual date and bank date)?</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: You record the transaction on the date you write the check or initiate the transaction.  When it "clears" the bank, you can click in the "Reconciled" field to "clear" the transaction (change the "n"on-reconciled to "c"leared).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para><emphasis>Q: How to provide security for GC data using CFS, 
etc.)</emphasis></para>
  <para>A: Unanswered</para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  
 </appendix>
