<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.0
  Last modified: October 25th 2010
       modified: January 12th 2007
       modified: July 9th 2006
  Maintainers: 
               Cristian Marchi <cri.penta@gmail.com> 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Author:
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
  	Updated	Bengt Thuree <bengt@thuree.com>
  Originally written by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="chapter_basics">
  <title>The Basics</title>

  <para>This chapter will introduce some of the basics of using <application>&app;</application>. It is
  recommended that you read through this chapter, before starting to do any
  real work with <application>&app;</application>. Next chapters will begin to show
  you hands on examples.</para>

  <sect1 id="basics-accounting1">
    <title>Accounting Concepts</title>

    <para><application>&app;</application> is easy enough to use that you do not need to have a
    complete understanding of accounting principles to find it useful.
    However, you will find that some basic accounting knowledge will prove to
    be invaluable as <application>&app;</application> was designed using these principles as a
    template. It is highly recommended that you understand this section of the
    guide before proceeding.</para>

    <sect2 id="basics-accounting52">
      <title>The 5 Basic Accounts</title>

      <para>Basic accounting rules group all finance related things into 5
      fundamental types of <quote>accounts</quote>. That is, everything that
      accounting deals with can be placed into one of these 5 accounts:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Assets</emphasis> &mdash; things you own.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Liabilities</emphasis> &mdash; things you owe.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Equity</emphasis> &mdash; overall net worth.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Income</emphasis> &mdash; increases the value of your
          accounts.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Expenses</emphasis> &mdash; decreases the value of your
          accounts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>It is clear that it is possible to categorize your financial world
      into these 5 groups. For example, the cash in your bank account is an
      asset, your mortgage is a liability, your paycheck is income, and the
      cost of dinner last night is an expense.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-accountingequation2">
      <title>The Accounting Equation</title>

      <para>With the 5 basic accounts defined, what is the relationship
      between them? How does one type of account affect the others? Firstly,
      equity is defined by assets and liability. That is, your net worth is
      calculated by subtracting your liabilities from your assets:</para>

      <para><emphasis>Assets - Liabilities = Equity</emphasis></para>

      <para>Furthermore, you can increase your equity through income, and
      decrease equity through expenses. This makes sense of course, when you
      receive a paycheck you become "richer" and when you pay for dinner you
      become "poorer". This is expressed mathematically in what is known as
      the Accounting Equation:</para>

      <para><emphasis>Assets - Liabilities = Equity + (Income -
      Expenses)</emphasis></para>

      <para>This equation must always be balanced, a condition that can only
      be satisfied if you enter values to multiple accounts. For example: if
      you receive money in the form of income you must see an equal increase
      in your assets. As another example, you could have an increase in assets
      if you have a parallel increase in liabilities.</para>

      <figure pgwide="1">
        <title>The basic accounts relationships</title>
        <screenshot id="basics-AccountRelationships">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_AccountRelationships.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Geert Janssens" ></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_AccountRelationships.svg"
                         format="SVG" srccredit="Geert Janssens"
                         contentwidth="4in"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>The basic accounts relationships</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>A graphical view of the relationship between the 5 basic
              accounts. Net worth (equity) increases through income and
              decreases through expenses. The arrows represent the movement of
              value.</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-accountingdouble2">
      <title>Double Entry</title>

      <para>The accounting equation is the very heart of a <firstterm>double entry
      accounting system</firstterm>. For every change in value of one account in the
      Accounting Equation, there must be a balancing change in another. This
      concept is known as the <firstterm>Principle of Balance</firstterm>, and
      is of fundamental importance for understanding <application>&app;</application> and other double
      entry accounting systems. When you work with <application>&app;</application>, you will always be
      concerned with at least 2 accounts, to keep the accounting equation
      balanced.</para>

      <para>Double entry accounting serves two purposes. The first is to
      create an accounting trail; money always has to come from somewhere and
      go to somewhere. Additionally, double entry accounting historically
      served to double check the math of an accountant. Because the numbers
      are entered into multiple accounts simultaneously, there are multiple
      places to check to make sure the totals match. Of course, with the
      advent of computers, the chances of a mathematical problem are low, but
      it is good to know that the concept still exists!</para>

      <para>Double entry accounting has been around since the late 15th
      century, when it was described by an Italian friar, Luca Pacioli.
      Traditional double entry accounting involves recording each transaction
      in a book called a ledger, then copying each part of the transaction to
      separate books called journals. This method is still used in businesses
      today as a way to avoid entry errors and to track the source of those
      errors. <application>&app;</application> simplifies this traditional accounting by copying part
      of each transaction for you, so it may not catch some of the entry
      errors that would show up in traditional accounting. But it will flag
      transactions that are not balanced, and it will let you know when an
      account name is missing.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Calling this double-entry bookkeeping is a bit misleading; it
        would be somewhat more accurate to call it multiple- entry
        bookkeeping, since a transaction can affect more than two accounts.
        Unfortunately, there&rsquo;s 700 years of history of use of the term, which
        sufficiently discourages changing it.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics-entry1">
    <title>Data Entry Concepts</title>

    <para>When entering data in <application>&app;</application>, you should be aware of the 3 levels
    of organization in which <application>&app;</application> divides your data: files, accounts and
    transactions. These levels are presented in their order of complexity, one
    file contains many accounts and one account contains many transactions.
    This division is fundamental to understanding how to use <application>&app;</application>.</para>

    <sect2 id="basics-files2">
      <title>Files</title>

      <para><application>&app;</application> stores information at the
      highest level in files. A file can be stored on your computer either
      as a single <acronym>XML</acronym> file (in all versions of
      <application>&app;</application>), or in a <acronym>SQL</acronym>
      database (in version 2.4 and higher).</para>

      <note>
        <para><acronym>SQL</acronym> is pronounced <quote>sequel</quote>,
        so in spoken and written language we would say <quote>a SQL
        database</quote>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>With the <acronym>XML</acronym> file format,
      <application>&app;</application> stores your data in an
      <acronym>XML</acronym> data file, usually in compressed format
      (although this can be changed in preferences).</para>

      <para>With <acronym>SQL</acronym> storage,
      <application>&app;</application> stores your data in a
      <acronym>SQL</acronym> database under the database application you
      select.</para>

      <para>You will need one main file or database for each set of
      accounts you are maintaining. To learn how to create and manage
      <application>&app;</application> files, see <xref
      linkend="basics-files1"/>.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you think you might need more than one set of accounts,
        you might want to consult a professional accountant or bookkeeper
        before proceeding. Most users will probably have only one data
        file.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Backup files and log files are automatically generated by
      <application>&app;</application> when appropriate. Backup and log
      files are described in <xref linkend="basics-backup1"/>.</para>
    </sect2> <!-- basics-files2 -->
    <sect2 id="basics-accounts2">
      <title>Accounts</title>

      <para>An <firstterm>account</firstterm> keeps track of what you own,
      owe, spend or receive. Each <application>&app;</application> file can
      contain any number of accounts, and each account can contain many
      sub-accounts up to an arbitrary number of levels. This simple feature
      gives <application>&app;</application> much of its power in managing
      your finances, as you will see in later chapters.</para>

      <para>Examples of accounts include: checking accounts, savings
      accounts, credit card accounts, mortgages, and loans. Each
      <application>&app;</application> account tracks the activity for that
      <quote>real</quote> account, and can inform you of its status.</para>

      <para>In addition, accounts are also used to categorize the money you
      receive or spend. For example, you can create expense accounts to
      track the money you pay on utilities or groceries. Even though these
      are not accounts that receive statements, they allow you to determine
      how much money is being spent in each of these areas.</para>

      <para>Accounts will be covered in more detail in <xref
      linkend="chapter_accts"/>.</para>
    </sect2> <!-- basics-accounts2 -->
    <sect2 id="basics-transactions2">
      <title>Transactions</title>

      <para>A <firstterm>transaction</firstterm> represents the movement of
      money among accounts. Whenever you spend or receive money, or
      transfer money between accounts, that is a transaction.</para>

      <para>Examples of transactions are: paying a phone bill, transferring
      money from savings to checking, buying a pizza, withdrawing money,
      and depositing a paycheck. <xref linkend="chapter_txns"/> goes more
      in depth on how to enter transactions.</para>

      <para>In double entry accounting, transactions always involve at
      least two accounts&ndash;a source account and a destination account.
      <application>&app;</application> manages this by inserting a line
      into the transaction for every account that is affected, and
      recording the amounts involved in each line. A line within a
      transaction that records the account and amount of money involved is
      called a <firstterm>split</firstterm>. A transaction can contain an
      arbitrary number of splits.</para>

      <para>Splits in transactions will be covered in <xref
      linkend="txns-registers-multiaccount2"/></para>
    </sect2> <!-- basics-transactions2 -->
  </sect1> <!-- basics-entry1 -->

  <sect1 id="basics-interface1">
    <title>Interface</title>

    <para>The very first time you open <application>&app;</application>, you will see the
    <interface>Welcome to &app;!</interface> screen. From there, <application>&app;</application>
    provides other tools to help you easily find what you are looking for.
    Let&rsquo;s take a look at some of the common screens and screen boxes you will
    see.</para>

    <sect2 id="basics-setup2">
      <title>Create a new set of accounts</title>

      <para>The <interface>New Account Hierarchy Setup</interface> assistant allows
      you to create several accounts at once. When you open <application>&app;</application> the first
      time, you will get this screen:</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-NewAccountHierarchySetup">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_NewAccountHierarchySetup.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The New Account Hierarchy Setup assistant</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the first screen of the <interface>New
            Account Hierarchy Setup</interface> assistant.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> and follow the instructions
      provided in the screen. The screen provides a default set of accounts
      with predefined account types, and you simply select the accounts you
      want. For more information on account types, see 
      <xref linkend="accts-types1"></xref>.</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-NewAccountHierarchySetup-currency">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_NewAccountHierarchySetup_currency.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The New Account Hierarchy Setup assistant - Currency</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the second screen of the <interface>New
            Account Hierarchy Setup</interface> assistant where you select the
            currency.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The currency you select here, will be assigned to all the
      <guilabel>accounts</guilabel> created in this assistant.</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-NewAccountHierarchySetup-Accounts">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_NewAccountHierarchySetup_Accounts.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The New Account Hierarchy Setup assistant - Choose
            accounts</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the third screen of the <interface>New
            Account Hierarchy Setup</interface> assistant where you choose the
            various accounts.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Select one or more of the predefined account-groups here. For more
      information on account types, see 
      <xref linkend="accts-types1"></xref>.</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-NewAccountHierarchySetup-Setup.png">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_NewAccountHierarchySetup_Setup.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The New Account Hierarchy Setup assistant - Configure</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the fourth screen of the <interface>New
            Account Hierarchy Setup</interface> assistant where you can set
            <guilabel>Opening Balance</guilabel>.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>In this screen you will be able to set an <guilabel>Opening
      Balance</guilabel> on each of the accounts, as well as indicate if
      the account should be a <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel> (only
      sub-accounts allowed, no transactions. Like Current Assets in above
      image).</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-NewAccountHierarchySetup-Finish">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_NewAccountHierarchySetup_Finish.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The New Account Hierarchy Setup assistant - Finish</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the last screen of the <interface>New
            Account Hierarchy Setup</interface> assistant.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to create all the accounts and
      leave the assistant.</para>

      <para>If you intend to import your data from another program and you
      want to keep the same account names you used in that program, you may
      want to delay setting up default accounts at this time. You can simply
      import the data and the account names into <application>&app;</application> from the other
      program (<xref linkend="basics-import1"></xref> explains how to do this).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-tip2">
      <title>Tip of the Day</title>

      <para><application>&app;</application> provides a <interface>Tip of the Day</interface> screen to
      give helpful hints for using the program:</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-TipOfDay">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_TipOfDay.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The Tip of the Day</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the <guilabel>Tip of the
            Day</guilabel>.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>These tips provide useful information for beginning users. To view
      more of the tips, click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to continue. If you
      do not wish to see this screen box on start-up, deselect the box next to
      <guilabel>Show tips at startup</guilabel>. When you have
      finished viewing the helpful tips, click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to
      close the <interface>Tip of the Day</interface> screen.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-main2">
      <title>Account Tree Window</title>

      <para>You should now see the <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> window, which
      appears as shown below. The exact layout of the account tree will depend
      on which default accounts you selected during the New Account Hierarchy
      Setup. In this example, the "Common Accounts" are shown.</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-Accounts">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_Accounts.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The Account Tree Window</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the <interface>Accounts</interface>
            window.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The Account Tree window provides an overview of the data contained
      in the current file. It contains a list of account names and their
      current balances. From this window, you can open any of the accounts.
      The individual account windows are called account registers. <application>&app;</application>
      allows you to have as many account registers open as you wish.</para>

      <para>At the top of this window is the title bar, which displays the
      file name (once you have saved the file.) Below that is the menu bar.
      You can access the menu options by either clicking on these menu
      headings or by using shortcuts and access keys (see <xref linkend="basics-shortcut2" />). 
      Next is the Toolbar, which contains buttons
      for the most common functions.</para>
      
      <para>The account tree appears below the Toolbar. Once you have
      started creating accounts, the account names will appear in the account
      tree. You can customize which headings show up by using the
      small <guiicon>down-arrow</guiicon> at the far right just above the account tree.</para>

      <para>At the bottom is the status bar, which tells you
      information about what you own (Net Assets) and how much money you have
      made (Profits).</para>


    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-register2">
      <title>Account Register Window</title>

      <para>The Account Register windows are used to enter and edit your
      account data. As the name suggests, they look similar to a checkbook
      register. When you double-click an account name in the
      <interface>Accounts</interface> window, the <interface>Register</interface>
      window for that account will open.</para>

      <screenshot id="basics-CheckAccount">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_CheckAccount.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>The Checking Account Register</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>This image shows the <guilabel>Checking Account - Register
            </guilabel> with several transactions.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para><xref linkend="chapter_txns"></xref> explains more about account 
      register windows and how to
      enter data into them. For now, note that the parts of an account
      register window are similar to the parts of the account tree window
      described earlier. The title bar at the top contains the account name.
      Below that, the menu bar contains menu options related to the account
      register. Toolbar buttons simplify common data entry functions. The
      status bar at the bottom of the window, displays some account balances
      covered in <xref linkend="chapter_txns"></xref>. At the bottom of the 
      account register window,
      information appears about the current location of the cursor.</para>
      
      <note>
      <para>In the register windows, you can resize the various columns that 
        <application>&app;</application> displays, but keep in mind that 
        the description column will automatically expand to fill all unused
        space.  Therefore you should increase the size of all your other columns
        first and then decrease the size of the description column.</para>
      </note>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-toolbar2">
      <title>Toolbar Buttons</title>

      <para>Both the account tree window and the account register window
      contain Toolbar buttons. These buttons provide quick access to common
      functions such as <guibutton>Save</guibutton> and
      <guibutton>Open</guibutton> in the account tree window and
      <guibutton>Record</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> in the
      account register window. If you are not sure what a button does, move
      the mouse pointer over that button, and you should see a description of
      the function appear.</para>

      <para>Here is a summary of the account tree window buttons:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><guibutton>Save</guibutton> &mdash; Save
          the current file to disk.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guibutton>Close</guibutton> &mdash; Close the
          current notebook page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><guibutton>Open</guibutton>, <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>,
          <guibutton>New</guibutton> and <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> &mdash; These
          are functions related to accounts. They are discussed in 
          <xref linkend="chapter_accts"></xref>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>Register buttons are discussed in <xref linkend="chapter_txns"></xref>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-options2">
      <title>Menu Items</title>

      <para>The account tree window and the account register window both
      contain menu headings in a menu bar. Clicking on a menu heading brings
      up the menu items for that heading.</para>

      <para>You can click on the account tree menu headings and then move the
      mouse pointer over the menu items to see what they do. As the pointer
      moves over a menu item, a description of the item appears in the lower
      left-hand corner of the window (inside the Status bar). To select a menu item, click on
      it.</para>

      <para>You can also access the most common menu items in a window by
      right-clicking the mouse anywhere in that window. In the account tree
      window, this will bring up a list of account items. In the account
      register window, this will bring up a list of transaction items.</para>

      <para>Other ways of accessing menu items are through keyboard shortcuts
      and access keys, described next.</para> </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-shortcut2">
      <title>Menu Shortcuts</title>

      <para>All of the menu items have access keys which are
      marked by underlined characters in the menu names. Pressing the
      <keycap>Alt</keycap> key with the underlined character in the menu
      heading will bring up the menu items for that heading. Once the menu
      items are displayed, type the underlined character in the menu item to
      activate it. For example, typing <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
      <keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> in the main window brings up the <guimenu>File</guimenu>
      menu, then typing <keycap>S</keycap> will save the file.  Access keys
      are fixed and cannot be changed by users.</para>

      <para>Some of the more commonly used menu items also have shortcut keys
      that directly activate the command without having to traverse the menu
      structure.  These shortcuts typically use the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
      key, although they can use any key combination.  Menu shortcuts are
      displayed at the end of each menu item.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics-help1">
    <title>Getting Help</title>

    <para><application>&app;</application> offers help in many ways. We have already covered the <link linkend="basics-TipOfDay">
    <interface>Tip of the Day</interface></link> screen that gives you helpful hints
    upon start-up of your <application>&app;</application> session. <application>&app;</application> also offers an extensive
    help manual.</para>

    <sect2 id="basics-manual2">
      <title>Help Manual</title>

      <para>Once you have opened <application>&app;</application>, you will see the <guilabel>Account
      Tree</guilabel> window <guilabel>Help</guilabel> menu heading, which
      opens the on-line manual. The on-line manual is organized by topic, and
      you can expand each topic into its subtopics.</para>

      <para>Topics are listed on the left side. To select a topic or subtopic,
      click on it, and you should see the text for that topic appear on the
      right. Use the <guibutton>Back</guibutton> and
      <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> buttons to navigate through your topic
      choices, and print any text using the <guibutton>Print</guibutton>
      button.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-web2">
      <title>Web Access</title>

      <para>The <guilabel>&app; Help</guilabel> window also acts as a simple
      web browser, so you can pull up a web site for additional information.
      You can open any web site under this window by clicking the
      <guibutton>Open</guibutton> Toolbar button and then typing in the URL.
      Use the <guibutton>Back</guibutton>, <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>,
      <guibutton>Reload</guibutton>, <guibutton>Stop</guibutton>, and
      <guibutton>Print</guibutton> buttons as you would in a standard
      browser.</para>

      <para>The <ulink
      url="http://www.gnucash.org"><citetitle>&app;</citetitle></ulink> web
      site contains helpful information about the program and about any
      updates to it. It also contains links to the <application>&app;</application> mailing lists for
      developers and users, and you can search the <ulink
      url="https://lists.gnucash.org/cgi-bin/namazu.cgi"><citetitle>archives
      of <application>&app;</application> mailing lists</citetitle></ulink> for discussions on a
      particular topic. If you don&rsquo;t find the answers you are looking for, you
      can post your question to the <ulink
      url="https://lists.gnucash.org/mailman/listinfo/gnucash-user"><citetitle>&app;
      user list</citetitle></ulink>, and someone on the list will attempt to
      answer you.</para>

      <para>The most updated <guilabel>&app; FAQ</guilabel> is also located
      on the <ulink url="http://wiki.gnucash.org/wiki/FAQ"><citetitle>&app;
      FAQ website</citetitle></ulink>, and contains answers to the popular
      questions.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-topic2">
      <title>Topic Search</title>

      <para>The online manual also provides a search function. To search for a
      particular topic, click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> tab at the
      bottom of the help window and type in your topic in the field provided.
      Click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button to complete your search.
      A list of choices should appear in the box below, clicking a choice will
      bring up its text on the right.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics-files1">
    <title>Creating and Saving Files</title>

    <para>If you are using <application>&app;</application> for the first time, it will automatically
    open a new file when you begin. Follow these steps to save the file under
    a new name:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Save
        As...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menu bar or select the
        <guibutton>Save</guibutton> toolbar button. <application>&app;</application> will bring up this
        window:</para>

        <screenshot id="basics-SaveAs">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_SaveAs.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>The Save screen</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>This image shows the <interface>Save</interface>
              screen.</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the text box below <guilabel>Selection</guilabel> type your
        chosen file name (e.g. gcashdata).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to save the
        file.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>If you are keeping track of finances for a single household, you
    need only one file. But if you are also tracking business finances or want
    to keep data separate for some reason, then you will need more than one
    file. To create a new file:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the main menu, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>New File</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Follow the steps above for saving a file under a new
        name.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Before ending each <application>&app;</application> session, be sure to save your data
    changes using <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
    <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem></menuchoice> or the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> toolbar
    button.
    <note>
        <para>As it is very important to save your data frequently to avoid losing them for whatever reason,
        <application>&app;</application> is able to automatically save the opened file every a certain amount of time.
        This interval can be set in the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab under 
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. 
        Keep in mind that this option is relevant only if you are saving in <acronym>XML</acronym> format.
        If you are working with a database, the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button and the <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
        menu entry will be grayed out because changes are stored right away.</para>
    </note>
    </para>
    <para>To open an existing file, select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
    <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menu and choose your file from the list.</para>

    <para><application>&app;</application> stores its data with the extension <filename>.gnucash</filename>.</para>
      <note>
        <para>The <filename>.gnucash</filename> extension was introduced in the 2.3 series of <application>&app;</application>.
        For already existing files, the extension will never be changed. So if you open an existing file named 
        <filename>Myoldfile</filename>, that name won&rsquo;t be changed if the file is saved. You might use the 
        <guimenuitem>Save As...</guimenuitem> command and give the file a new name in order to have it saved with the 
        extension <filename>.gnucash</filename>.</para>
      </note>
    
    <para>If you name your <application>&app;</application> file to <filename>MyBudget</filename>, the actual file name
    will be <filename>MyBudget.gnucash</filename></para>
      <note>
        <para>It is not necessary to specify an extension when you write
        the file name. Per the above example, it is enough to only specify
        <filename>MyBudget</filename> as the filename.</para>
      </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics-import1">
    <title>Importing QIF Files</title>

    <note>
      <para>This section tells you how to initially import data from other
      financial programs that use QIF (<trademark
      class="registered">Quicken</trademark> Interchange Format). 
<!--
      Section 11.5
      addresses importing QIF data from online bank statements.
-->
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>To import data from <trademark
    class="registered">Quicken</trademark>, MS Money, or other programs that
    use QIF(<trademark class="registered">Quicken</trademark> Interchange
    Format), you must first export your data to a QIF file. One way to do this
    is to export each account as a separate QIF file. An easier way, available
    in <trademark class="registered">Quicken</trademark> 98 and beyond, is to
    export all accounts at once into a single QIF file. Check your program&rsquo;s
    manual to determine if this option is available.</para>

    <para>Once your data is in QIF form, follow the easy 3-step import process
    described below. Before you get started, though, please note that part of
    the import process involves checking for duplicate transactions, so it is
    very important that you load <emphasis>all</emphasis> of your QIF files
    before importing. Duplicate transactions result when more than one account
    is involved. For example, if one of your transactions transferred money
    from savings to checking, you would end up with this same transaction
    recorded twice - once in the savings account and once in the checking
    account.</para>

    <para>To import QIF files:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Load all of the QIF files containing data you wish to
        import.</para>

        <para>To do this, select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Import</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Import
        QIF...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menu. When the <interface>QIF
        Import</interface> screen box appears, click
        <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> and follow the instructions to guide you
        through the process of loading your files.</para>

        <screenshot id="basics-QIF-Import-welcome">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_QIF_Import_welcome.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>The QIF Import assistant</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>This image shows the start of the <interface>QIF
              Import</interface> assistant.</para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>You will be prompted for a filename to load. Use the
        <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button to select your QIF file and click
        <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to load it. Once the file is loaded,
        select <guibutton>Load another file</guibutton> if you have more files
        to load. When you have loaded all your QIF files, click
        <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to continue with the import
        process.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Review the <application>&app;</application> accounts to be created.</para>

        <para>The importer then matches up your QIF accounts and categories
        with <application>&app;</application> accounts and gives you a brief description of the
        matching process. Clicking <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> will bring you
        to a view comparing your QIF accounts with the corresponding <application>&app;</application>
        accounts created. To change an account name, select the row containing
        that account name and edit the name in the screen box provided. Click
        <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> when you have finished making changes, and
        proceed through a similar category matching process. QIF income and
        expense categories import as <application>&app;</application> income and expense accounts (see
        <xref linkend="accts-concepts1"></xref> for more on this). 
        Make changes to these account names if
        necessary, and click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to continue.</para>

        <note>
          <para>If you are not sure what changes are needed, it is safe to
          accept the <application>&app;</application> account names. It is easy to edit the accounts
          later if you find you need to make a change.</para>
        </note>

        <para>From the drop-down list, select a standard currency to be used
        for imported accounts and click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to
        continue. If you have stocks, mutual funds, or other securities, you
        will be prompted for additional information. The importer screen will
        ask for the exchange or listing (e.g. NASDAQ), the security&rsquo;s full
        name, and the ticker symbol. If you do not have this information
        handy, you can edit the account information later, once the import is
        complete. Click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to continue.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tell <application>&app;</application> to import the data.</para>

        <para>The last step of the import. Once you have verified your account
        names and investment information, click <guibutton>Finish</guibutton>
        in the <guilabel>Update your &app; accounts</guilabel> page to
        complete the import process. Depending upon the size of your file, the
        import might take a few minutes to complete, so a progress bar
        displays the percentage finished. When the import process is complete,
        <application>&app;</application> will return you to the main window, which should now display
        the names of the accounts you have imported.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics-backup1">
    <title>Backing Up and Recovering Data</title>

    <para><application>&app;</application> creates several types of files to help ensure that your data
    is not lost. If you look in the folder where your saved <filename>.gnucash</filename> file resides, you may see other
    files generated by <application>&app;</application> with the following extensions: <filename>.gnucash</filename>,
    <filename>.log</filename>, <filename>.LCK</filename>, <filename>.LNK</filename> in the same directory 
    as your primary data file. What each of these files does is presented below.</para>
    
    <note>
    <para>The following sections are relevant only if you are saving your financial data in the xml format</para>
    </note>
 
    <programlisting>
      $ ls 
      myfile.gnucash
      myfile.gnucash.20100414185747.gnucash
      myfile.gnucash.20100414223248.log
      myfile.gnucash.20100415114340.gnucash
      myfile.gnucash.20100415154508.log
      myfile.gnucash.20100415173322.gnucash
      myfile.gnucash.20100415194251.log
      myfile.gnucash.7f0982.12093.LNK
      myfile.gnucash.LCK
    </programlisting>

    <sect2 id="basics-backupxac2">
      <title>Backup file (.gnucash)</title>

      <para>Each time you save your data file, a backup copy will also be
      saved with the extension <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename>. This backup file is a complete copy of
      your previous data file, and the filename format refers to the data
      file, year, month, day and time of the backup. For example, the filename
      <filename>myfile.gnucash.20100414185747.gnucash</filename> indicates this is a
      backup copy of the file <filename>myfile</filename> saved in the year 
      2010, April 14, at 6:57:47 p.m.</para>

      <para>To restore an old backup file, simply open the <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename> file with the
      date to which you wish to return. Be sure to save this file under a
      different name.</para>
      
      <note>
       <para><application>&app;</application> versions 2.3.15 and older creates backup files with the extension
         <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename> instead of the old extension <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.xac</filename>. 
         So if you upgrade from the 2.2 series to the 2.4 series, you may end up with both <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.xac</filename> 
         and <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename> backup files in your directory.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-backuplog2">
      <title>Log file (.log)</title>

      <para>Each time you open a file in <application>&app;</application>, a <filename>.log</filename> file is created and saved
      with the same name format as the <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename> backup files. As you make changes
      to the open data file, the log file saves only those changes. Log files
      are not a full backup of your data file - they simply record changes you
      have made to the data file in the current <application>&app;</application> session.</para>

      <para>In case you exit <application>&app;</application> inadvertently, possibly due to a power
      outage or a system wide crash, it is possible to recover most of your
      work since the last time you saved your <application>&app;</application> file using this log
      file. This is the procedure:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open the last saved <application>&app;</application> file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Go to <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guisubmenu>Import</guisubmenu> 
          <guimenuitem>Replay &app; .log file</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
          and select the one .log file with the same date as the saved file
          you just opened. Make sure that you picked the right .log file, or
          you will possibly wreak havoc in your accounts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Log replaying will recover any transaction affecting the balance
      entered since the last save, including those created from scheduled
      transactions and business features (invoices, bills, etc.).</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Changes to the scheduled transactions, invoices or
        bills themselves are NOT recovered, and their transactions that were
        recovered may not be properly associated with them, and should thus be
        double-checked. Especially for business transactions, you may have to
        delete and re-create some of them. If you do not, although the balance
        will be correct, some reports may not.</para>
      </warning>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-backuplock2">
      <title>Lock files (.LNK and .LCK)</title>

      <para>You may occasionally see <filename>.LNK</filename> and <filename>.LCK</filename> files appear. These do not
      store any data, but they are created to prevent more than one user from
      opening the same file at the same time. These files are automatically
      created when you open the file, to lock it so no one else can access it.
      When you close your <application>&app;</application> session or open another file, <application>&app;</application>
      unlocks the first data file by deleting the <filename>.LCK</filename> and <filename>.LNK</filename> files.</para>

      <para>If <application>&app;</application> crashes while you have a data file open, the <filename>.LCK</filename> and
      <filename>.LNK</filename> files are not deleted. The next time you try to open <application>&app;</application>, you
      will get a warning message that the file is locked. The warning message
      appears because the <filename>.LNK</filename> and <filename>.LCK</filename> files are still in your directory. It is
      safe to choose <guibutton>Yes</guibutton> to open the file, but you should delete the <filename>.LNK</filename> and
      <filename>.LCK</filename> files (using a terminal window or your file manager). Once those
      files are deleted, you will not get the warning message again unless
      <application>&app;</application> crashes.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="basics-backupmanage2">
      <title>File Management</title>

      <para>So which files should you keep around? Keep your main data file,
      of course. It&rsquo;s a
      good idea to keep some of the more recent <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename> backup files, but you can safely
      delete the <filename>.log</filename> files since they are not complete copies of your data.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you upgraded from a <application>&app;</application> version prior to 2.4, you may also have backup files
        in the old <filename>.xac</filename> format. For these files you can apply the same principle described above for
        <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename> backup files.</para>
      </note>

      <para>You should also delete any <filename>.LCK</filename> and <filename>.LNK</filename> files that you see after
      closing <application>&app;</application>. If you decide to back up your data file to another
      disk manually, it's enough to back up the main data file - not the <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename>
      backup files.</para>

      <note>
        <para>By default <application>&app;</application> will automatically delete any <filename>.log</filename> and <filename>.YYYYMMDDHHMMSS.gnucash</filename>
        backup files that are older than 30 days. You can change this behavior in the <application>&app;</application>
        preferences in the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab under <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
      </note>
      
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="basics-together1">
    <title>Putting It All Together</title>

    <note>
      <para>This section begins a tutorial that will continue throughout this
      book. At the end of each chapter, you will see a <guilabel>Putting It
      All Together</guilabel> section that walks you through examples to
      illustrate concepts discussed in that section. Each <guilabel>Putting It
      All Together</guilabel> section builds on the previous one, so be sure
      to save your file for easy access.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Let&rsquo;s get started!</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>First, let&rsquo;s create a file to store your real data. Open <application>&app;</application>
        and go through the <interface>New Account Hierarchy Setup</interface>
        screen. You will create a file and accounts to be used for your home
        finances, so choose the accounts that pertain to you. If you are not
        sure what accounts you will need, click the <guibutton>Select
        All</guibutton> option to create all of the accounts provided. When
        you have completed the setup, save this file with a filename you want
        to use for your home data.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Next, create a file to store test data. This is the file that
        will be used in the tutorials throughout this manual. Click
        <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>New File</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to create
        a new file, and name it <filename>gcashdata_1</filename>. Your main
        window should now look something like this:</para>

        <figure pgwide="1">
          <title>A new Account Tree window </title>
          <screenshot id="basics-EmptyAccounts">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_EmptyAccounts.png"
                           format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
              </imageobject>

              <textobject>
                <phrase>The Main windows showing the test file</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>This image shows the Account Tree window with a set of
              accounts loaded from the assistant.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Now, adjust some preferences in the account tree window. Select
        <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
        <guimenuitem>Windows</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and change the toolbar Style
        so that they display only text, not icons. The change will take place
        immediately, so look at the Toolbar buttons in the main window. Return
        to the <interface>Preferences</interface> screen and change the Toolbar
        buttons back to the default setting by clicking <guibutton>Use system
        default</guibutton>. From the column header row, select
        <guibutton>Arrow down</guibutton> and select <quote>Type</quote>
        (which means view column "Type"). The main window should now look like
        this:</para>

        <figure pgwide="1">
          <title>The Main window with changed display options</title>
          <screenshot id="basics-EmptyAccounts2">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_EmptyAccounts2.png"
                           format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
              </imageobject>

              <textobject>
                <phrase>The effect of changing the display options</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>Save your file.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If you plan to import QIF data from another program, let&rsquo;s try a
        practice file first. (If not, skip to <xref linkend="chapter_accts"/>.)</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>First, create a new file called
            <filename>gcashimport</filename>. It is up to you if you would
            like to specify accounts (like Common Accounts) directly or not.
            If the QIF importer does not find an account, it will create it
            automatically (or allow you to create it manually)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the main menu, select <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Import</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Import
            QIF...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to start the import.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select the appropriate currency</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select <filename>gnc_Sample_QIF.qif</filename> as QIF file
            to load.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the following screens, ensure that each transaction has a
            valid account, if in doubt, just use the default ones.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Complete the import.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The main window should now look like this:</para>

        <figure pgwide="1">
          <title>The Main window after QIF import</title>
          <screenshot id="basics-AccountsSampleQIF">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/basics_AccountsSampleQIF.png"
                           format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" ></imagedata>
              </imageobject>

              <textobject>
                <phrase>After importing the provided sample QIF file</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <note>
          <para>If after the import the screen is blank, go to <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>New Accounts Page</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
           to display a new Accounts tab.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Save your file.</para>

      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
