<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-docbookx.dtd">
<!-- (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.6.15
  Last modified: December 6, 2016
  Maintainers:
    Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Author:
    Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
    Updated Bengt Thuree <bengt@thuree.com>
    Updated Geert Janssens <janssens-geert@telenet.be>
    Revised David T. <sunfish62@yahoo.com>
    Revised 2020: David Cousens <davidcousens@bigpond.com>
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
    (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="chapter_currency">
  <title>Multiple Currencies</title>

  <para>This chapter will show how to set up &app; accounts to use multiple currencies.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="currency_concepts1">
    <title>Basic Concepts</title>

    <para>&app; supports over a hundred currencies, from the Andorran Franc to the Zimbabwe Dollar. For
      example, you can have a bank account set up in Euros, and another using Hong Kong Dollars.
    </para>

    <para>Some of the issues which arise when using multiple currencies are, how do you transfer funds between
      accounts with different currencies? How do you calculate the overall value when you have mixed
      currency accounts? How do reports deal with mixed currencies?
    </para>

    <para>You can either deal with multiple currencies using manually entered transactions to record currency
      gains and losses as described in <xref linkend="currency_manual" /> or you can utilize
      currency trading accounts introduced with &app; version 2.3.14 to automatically record the
      gains and losses on transactions between currencies as described in the subsequent section.
      Trading accounts are not enabled by default in &app; and must be explicitly enabled as
      described in <xref linkend="currency_trading_accts" />.
    </para>
<!-- TODO: add sections
    <para>The following sections are common to both manually recording gains
      and losses from multiple currency transactions and using trading accounts
      to record such gains and losses.</para>
TODO -->
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="currency_manual">
    <title>Manually Recording Currency Transaction</title>

    <sect2 id="currency_acct1">
      <title>Account Setup</title>

      <para>Your default account currency is set in the <guilabel>Account</guilabel> tab under
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        (
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>&appname;</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        on MacOS).
      </para>

      <para>Similarly, &app; offers an option to set your preferred currency for displaying reports (like the
        balance sheet and income statement). The option is called <guilabel>Default Report
        Currency</guilabel>, and is in the <guilabel>Reports</guilabel> tab of the
        <guilabel>&appname; Preferences</guilabel> screen. You&rsquo;ll want to set both options
        when you start using &app; because if (for example) your accounts are all in Canadian
        Dollars but the generated reports are all in US Dollars, the reports will just say that
        there are <quote>no data/transactions (or only zeroes) for the selected time period</quote>.
      </para>

      <para>When you create a new account, you have the option to define the commodity in which that account is
        denominated. For accounts denominated in a currency, you can specify any of the currencies
        supported by &app; by simply selecting it from the currency commodity list. You will notice
        that the default currency is the currency that is defined for the parent account of the new
        account.
      </para>

      <para>As an example, let&rsquo;s set up a bank account scenario where you mostly work in US Dollars, but
        do also have a European bank account using the Euro currency, as well as one bank account in
        Hong Kong using Hong Kong Dollars. So, set up 3 bank accounts, one denominated in US
        Dollars, one using Euros, and the third in Hong Kong Dollars. One possible account structure
        for this would be:
      </para>
<screen>
-Assets (USD)
   -Current Assets (USD)
      -US Bank (USD)
      -European Bank (EUR)
      -HK Bank (HKD)
-Equity (USD)
   -Opening Balances (USD)
      -USD (USD)
      -EUR (EUR)
      -HKD (HKD)</screen>
      <note>
        <para>The currency of each account is shown in parenthesis.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>Since in this example you mostly work in USD, all of the parent accounts are set to USD. Of course,
        if you mostly work in Euros, you could change the currency of these parent accounts to EUR.
        The totals shown in the account tree window will always be converted to the currency of each
        particular account. Notice, we also set up 3 Starting Balances equity accounts, used to
        initially populate the 3 banks.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>You could also set up just a single Starting Balance account and use a currency transfer to populate
          the <quote>different currency</quote> accounts. However, this is more advanced option,
          which is explained in a later section (<xref linkend="currency_purchase2" />).
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>Below you see the result of this example, in which you start with USD 10,000, EUR 10,000 as well as
        HKD 10,000 in the three bank accounts. Notice that the total of the parent accounts only
        shows the value of the currency of sub-accounts with matching currencies. In other words,
        the Total Assets and Total Equity values only reflect USD amounts, because &app; has no way
        of evaluating the value of EUR or HKD yet. Once you set up exchange rates between the
        currencies, the parent accounts will calculate the converted value of all sub-accounts. See
        the later section (<xref linkend="currency_howto1" />) on ways to do this.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="currency_main1">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_main1.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Initial multi currency Account Bank Setup</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Initial setup of 3 bank accounts with different currencies.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Notice that the "Total (Report)" column is being displayed. This is configured in the column header
        row, select <guibutton>Arrow down</guibutton> and select <quote>Total(USD)</quote>.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="currency_acct_user2">
        <title>User-Defined Currencies</title>

        <para>Usually when we talk about currencies, we mean government-backed currencies (or more precisely,
          currencies defined in <ulink
        url="&url-wp-en;ISO_4217">ISO 4217</ulink>). &app;
          does not allow you to create your own currencies. If you want to track
          non-<acronym>ISO</acronym> currencies, you can use either of two workarounds, depending on
          which fits your needs better.
        </para>

        <para>The <emphasis role="strong">first method</emphasis> is to treat these as if they were a
          security&mdash;that is, like a stock or mutual fund. The second method is to use one of
          the <quote>dummy</quote> currencies for them.
        </para>

        <para>Let&rsquo;s say for example that you want to track loyalty points you&rsquo;ve earned by buying from
          a certain group of businesses. The account which tracks your loyalty points will be
          <emphasis>Assets:Other:LoyaltyGroupRewardMiles</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <para>In the first method, you define a new security, of type <guilabel>FUND</guilabel>, called
          RewardMiles. This is pretty straightforward&mdash;when you create the new
          <emphasis>LoyaltyGroupRewardMiles</emphasis> account, just set the account type to
          <guilabel>Stock</guilabel> or <guilabel>Mutual Fund</guilabel>, click the
          <guibutton>Select...</guibutton> button next to the
          <guilabel>Security/currency:</guilabel> box, and click <guibutton>New</guibutton> to
          define a new security of type <guilabel>FUND</guilabel>.
        </para>

        <para>This is not really what the stock and mutual fund account types are meant for, but &app; will allow
          it. The downside is that you&rsquo;ll have to enter a <quote>price</quote> for every
          transaction involving this account, because &app; needs the prices to figure out the
          monetary value of the points and treat them as one of your assets.
        </para>

        <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">second method</emphasis>, you use one of the dummy currencies to
          track the loyalty points. These currencies are <quote>XTS (Code for testing
          purposes)</quote> and <quote>XXX (No currency)</quote>. If you use one of these for your
          LoyaltyGroupRewardMiles account, you can enter transactions into the account without
          having to enter share prices for every transaction. And, you can keep using the same two
          dummy currencies to track all sorts of amounts&mdash;vacation dollars earned and used so
          far this year, vacation hours earned and used, health insurance benefits allowance used
          and remaining, and so on.
        </para>

        <para>The drawback with this second method is that you cannot define exchange rates for the dummy
          currencies to convert them to <acronym>ISO</acronym> currencies. If you want to do that,
          you really should use the first method.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="currency_howto1">
      <title>Recording and Updating Currency Exchange Rates</title>

      <para>&app; allows you to update the Currency Exchange Rates both manually and automatically. This process
        is essentially the same as setting share prices for investments (see
        <xref linkend="invest-stockprice1"/>). In the following two sections we will work through
        both methods.
      </para>

      <para>Before we start, let&rsquo;s have a quick look at the Chart of Accounts
      </para>

      <screenshot id="currency_main1a">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_main1.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Initial multi currency Account Bank Setup</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Initial set up of 3 bank accounts with different currencies.
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>As you see, the overall balances do not yet reflect any value for EUR or HKD holdings. Adding
        currency exchange rates will fix this.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="currency_howto_Manual">
        <title>Manually Updating Exchange Rates</title>

        <para>Open the <guilabel>Price Editor</guilabel> by going to
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Price Editor</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          .
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_peditor">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_peditor.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Price Editor window</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Price Editor Window.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Click on the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to add a new currency exchange rate. A window will
          appear in which you can set up a new exchange rate. This window should appear like this:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_addcurr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_addcurr.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Set up Euro Exchange Rate</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Add Price Editor Window
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Set the <guilabel>Namespace</guilabel> to Currency and the <guilabel>Security</guilabel> to EUR
          (Euro). Then set the exchange rate between the selected security and the selected
          currency. The price box defines how many units of currency are required to purchase one
          unit of the security. In this case, how many dollars it will take to purchase on Euro. In
          this example, you will set the exchange rate to 1 EUR for 1 USD.
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_manualpriceadded">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_BeforeGetOnlineQuotes.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Price Editor Window</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>The Price Editor window after setting the exchange rate between Euros and US Dollars
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <screenshot id="currency_main2">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_main2.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Chart of Accounts</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Chart of Accounts after setting the exchange rate between Euros and US Dollars.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Observe that since you have no exchange rate for HKD, &app; doesn&rsquo;t convert the HKD accounts
          to USD. This will be added in the next section.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="currency_howto_Auto">
        <title>Automatic Updating Exchange Rates (How-To)</title>

        <para>In the previous section you saw how to manually define a new currency exchange rate, but &app;
          includes an automatic price update feature, which will now be described.
        </para>

        <para>Open the <guilabel>Price Editor</guilabel> by going to
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Price Editor</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          .
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_BeforeGetOnline">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_BeforeGetOnlineQuotes.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Price Editor window</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Price Editor Window before you obtain online quotes.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Click on the <guibutton>Get Quotes</guibutton> button to automatically load the various exchange
          rates you need.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>If the <guibutton>Get Quotes</guibutton> button is disabled, that means that the
            <application>Perl</application> module <application>Finance::Quote</application> is not
            installed. For information on how to install it, please see
            <xref linkend="invest-stockprice-auto2" ></xref>
          </para>
        </note>

        <para><screenshot id="currency_AfterGetOnlineQuotes">
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_AfterGetOnlineQuotes.png"
                           format="PNG" srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
              </imageobject>

              <textobject>
                <phrase>Price Editor window</phrase>
              </textobject>

              <caption>
                <para>Price Editor Window after we obtained online quotes.
                </para>
              </caption>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </para>

        <para>&app; downloads exchange rates for all currencies that are in use in your various accounts. This
          will happen every time you click on <guibutton>Get Quotes</guibutton> or request &app; to
          download quotes as per <xref linkend="invest-stockprice-auto2" />
        </para>

        <para>Now when you check the main Chart of Accounts you will see that &app; has automatically converted
          the HKD amount to USD amount on the parent accounts that are in USD, as well as on the
          Total (USD) column. Also the Euro accounts have been been updated with the latest exchange
          rate.
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_main3.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_main3.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="Geert Janssens" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Price Editor window</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Chart of Accounts after we obtain online quotes.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="currency_howto_disable">
        <title>Disabling Exchange Rate Retrieval</title>

        <para>Whenever you create an account that uses a non-default currency, exchange rate retrieval will be
          automatically enabled for that currency. However, if you later delete that account, &app;
          will not automatically disable exchange rate retrieval for that currency.
        </para>

        <para>If you have deleted the last account for a particular currency, and you do not wish to retrieve
          exchange rates for that currency anymore, do the following:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the Securities window by selecting
              <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>Security Editor</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice>
              .
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure the <guilabel>Show National Currencies</guilabel> box is selected.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Expand the CURRENCY row.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Double click on the currency for which you want to disable exchange rate retrieval.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Deselect the <guilabel>Get Online Quotes</guilabel> box and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="currency_purchase1">
      <title>Recording Purchases in a Foreign Currency</title>

      <para>Purchases in a foreign currency can be managed in two different ways.
      </para>

      <para>1) Use &app;'s built-in currency exchange functions when you do your transactions. This is mainly
        used for one-time transactions, and nothing which happens regularly.
      </para>

      <para>2) Use separate accounts to track transactions, where all involved accounts use the same currency.
        This is the recommended method, since it allows much better tracking and follow up. In this
        way, you do one currency exchange transaction, and after that you do normal transactions in
        the native currency.
      </para>

      <para>The rest of this section will explain more based upon option 2).
      </para>

      <sect3 id="currency_purchase2">
        <title>Purchase of an Asset with Foreign Currency</title>

        <para>You are using USD as your default currency. But, you decide to purchase a boat in Jamaica. To do
          this, you opened a bank account in Jamaica, moved some money from the US, and then
          purchased your boat.
        </para>

        <para>To record this in &app; we use the following basic account structure:
        </para>
<screen>
-Assets (USD)
   -Current Assets (USD)
      -US Bank (USD)
      -Jamaican Bank (JMD)
   -Fixed Assets (USD)
      -Boat (JMD)
-Equity (USD)
   -Opening Balances (USD)
      -USD (USD)</screen>
        <note>
          <para>The currency of each account is shown in parenthesis.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>First you need to transfer some money ($10,000) to Jamaica, and you use your US bank account (with a
          balance of $100,000) for that. The bank gives you an exchange rate of USD 1 = JMD 64, but
          charges you USD 150 to transfer the money.
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_MoveMoney.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_MoveMoney.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Currency transfer</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Transfer money to Jamaica
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Select the Jamaica transaction line ($9,850.00), right click and select <guilabel>Edit Exchange
          Rate</guilabel>
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_SetExchangeRate.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_SetExchangeRate.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Edit Exchange rate</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>A dialog window where the exchange rate in a currency transaction is specified
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>As Exchange Rate, you enter 1 USD = 64 JMD, since this is the rate your bank gave. Press ok in the
          Transfer Funds (Edit Exchange Rate) window, and then save this split transaction. Below is
          how it now looks in the main Chart of Accounts.
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_BeforeBoat.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_BeforeBoat.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Chart of Accounts before purchasing the boat</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Chart of Accounts before purchasing the boat
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>You choose to buy a boat for JMD 509,000. To record this transaction in &app;, you will need to
          enter a simple transaction in <emphasis>Assets:Current Assets:Jamaican Bank</emphasis>
          withdrawing JMD 509,000 and transferring it to <emphasis>Assets:Fixed
          Assets:Boat</emphasis>
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_AfterBoat.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_AfterBoat.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Chart of Accounts after purchasing the boat</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Chart of Accounts after purchasing the boat
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The Chart of Accounts now reflects that your bank account has been reduced by JMD 509,000, and that
          your Fixed Assets boat account has been increased by the same amount. If you also have
          turned on the CoA (Column Choice) "Total (USD)" you will see the corresponding value in
          USD. The USD value will always reflect the latest currency exchange rate you have either
          automatically or manually retrieved.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="currency_purchase3">
        <title>Purchasing Foreign Stocks</title>

        <para>This example will show how to purchase stocks that are priced in a currency other than your primary
          currency.
        </para>

        <para>Assume that you live in New York and therefore you have set the default currency to USD. You decide
          to purchase a stock traded in Hong Kong that is priced in HKD. You would also like to be
          able to track the various income and expense amounts per stock and broker.
        </para>

        <para>You decide to purchase stock in the Beijing Airport (Hong Kong). The ticker for this stock is
          0694.HK on Yahoo! Since you wanted to track all various income and expense amounts, here
          is the necessary account structure:
        </para>
<screen>
Assets:Investments:Brokerage Accounts:Boom:0694.HK (0694.HK)
Assets:Investments:Brokerage Accounts:Boom:Bank (HKD)
Equity:Opening Balances:HKD (HKD)
Expenses:Commissions:Boom.0694.HK (HKD)
Income:Investments:Dividend:Boom:0694.HK (HKD)</screen>
        <para>The Chart of Accounts looks like this after creating all the needed accounts:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_BeforeStocks.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_BeforeStocks.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Chart of Accounts for international stocks</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Chart of Accounts for international stocks
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The stock definition can be seen in the Security Editor. (
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenu>Security Editor</guimenu>
          </menuchoice>
          )
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_Commodities.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_Commodities.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>International securities</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>International securities
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>If you have not moved money (HKD 50,000) into the brokerage cash account
          (<emphasis>Assets:Investments:Brokerage Account:Boom:Bank</emphasis>), do so now, either
          using the Equity (HKD) account, or an existing bank account (Currency Transfer).
        </para>

        <para>There are two ways to enter the actual purchase transaction: you can enter it from the cash account
          (shown below), or you can enter it from the stock account. <emphasis>If entered from the
          stock account, the stock is assumed to be priced in the currency of the parent
          account</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <para>Let&rsquo;s assume that the stock price is HKD 3 per share. To record the purchase, open the
          brokerage&rsquo;s HKD cash account (<emphasis>Assets:Investments:Brokerage
          Account:Boom:Bank</emphasis>), and enter the following:
        </para>

        <bridgehead renderas='sect4'>
          Buy Stocks
        </bridgehead>

        <informaltable frame='none' colsep='0' rowsep='0'>
          <tgroup cols='3'>
            <colspec colwidth='3*' align='left'/>

            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='left'/>

            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='right'/>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Brokerage Account:Boom:Bank
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Withdrawal
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  50,000
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Expenses:Investments:Commission:Boom_HKD
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Deposit
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  500
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Brokerage Account:Boom:0694
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Deposit
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  49,500 (16,500 shares)
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <para>If the exchange rate dialog box does not appear automatically, right-click on the stock row, and
          select <guilabel>Edit Exchange Rate</guilabel>. Enter the number of shares (16,500) as the
          <guilabel>To Amount</guilabel>.
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_ToAmount.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_ToAmount.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Transfer Funds</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Setting the number of shares in the Transfer Funds dialog
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>When you return to the Chart of Accounts, you will see the purchased shares reflected in the stock
          account&rsquo;s total.
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_purchase_AfterStocks.png">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_purchase_AfterStocks.png"
                         format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Purchased international stocks</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Chart of Accounts with some international stocks
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>However, as you can see, the USD totals may be zero if &app; doesn&rsquo;t have an exchange rate
          between USD and HKD. To fix this, go to
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>Price Editor</guimenuitem>
          </menuchoice>
          and click the <guibutton>Get Quotes</guibutton> button to automatically retrieve the
          exchange rates you need.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>To reiterate, this example shows how stock can be purchased in any currency by entering the
            transaction in the register of the cash account used to make payment. It is also
            possible to enter the purchase in the stock account&rsquo;s register, but be aware that
            the stock is assumed to be priced in the currency of the stock account&rsquo;s parent.
          </para>

          <para>In this example, the stock account&rsquo;s parent (<emphasis>Assets:Investments:Brokerage
            Account:Boom</emphasis>) is denominated in HKD. Since this is same currency as the stock
            price, the purchase can be safely entered in the stock account&rsquo;s register.
          </para>
        </note>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="currency_invest1">
      <title>Tracking Currency Investments</title>

      <para>Currency investment is when you decide to invest in a different country's currency, and hope that it
        will rise in value relative your own currency.
      </para>

      <para>When you enter these transactions into &app;, you will have to decide on how much detail you would
        like to have.
      </para>

      <para>If you are not interested in detail at all, a very simple account structure would suffice:
      </para>
<screen>
Assets:Investments:Currency:Bank (USD)
Assets:Investments:Currency:XXX (XXX)</screen>
      <para>You would simply enter transfers between the two accounts, noting exchange rates as you went.
      </para>

      <para>But, if you do want to be able to track capital gains or losses, as well as any fees, you do need a
        more complex account structure, such as:
      </para>
<screen>
Assets:Investments:Currency:Bank (USD)
Assets:Investments:Currency:Currency Bank:XXX (XXX)
Expenses:Investments:Currency:Currency Bank:XXX (XXX)
Income:Investments:Currency Bank:Capital Gains:XXX (XXX)</screen>
      <sect3 id="currency_invest12">
        <title>Purchasing Currency</title>

        <para>When purchasing another currency, you will buy a certain number of units of foreign currency with
          your own currency, at a particular rate. For example, you might buy USD 10,000 worth of
          Andorran Francs, at 5 Francs to the dollar, with a transaction fee of $150.
        </para>

        <bridgehead renderas='sect4'>
          Buy Currency
        </bridgehead>

        <informaltable frame='none' colsep='0' rowsep='0'>
          <tgroup cols='3'>
            <colspec colwidth='5*' align='left'/>

            <colspec colwidth='2*' align='left'/>

            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='right'/>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Currency:Bank
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Withdrawal
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  10,000
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Expenses:Investments:Currency:Currency Bank:ADF
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Deposit
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  150
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Currency:ADF
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Deposit
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  49,250
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        <para>The Exchange Rate window should pop up when you leave the last row in the split above (Currency
          Transaction). If this window does not pop up, right click on the row or select
          <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>, and select <guilabel>Edit Exchange Rate</guilabel>. In the
          Exchange Rate window you specify the exchange rate you got from the bank.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="currency_invest13">
        <title>Selling a currency investment</title>

        <para>Entering a currency sale is done in the same way as a currency buy except that you are now
          transferring money from the Currency account to your Savings account (very similar to
          <xref
        linkend="invest-sell1" />).
        </para>

        <para>The proper recording of the currency sale *must* account for realized gains or losses. This can be
          done using a split transaction. In the split transaction, you must account for the profit
          (or loss) as coming from an <emphasis>Income:Capital Gains</emphasis> account (or
          <emphasis>Expenses:Capital Loss</emphasis>). To balance this income, you will need to
          enter the Currency asset twice in the split&mdash;once to record the actual sale (using
          the correct amount and correct exchange rate), and once to balance the income profit
          (setting the amount to 0).
        </para>

        <para>In short, a selling Currency transaction should look something like below, seen again from the
          <emphasis>Assets:Investments:Currency:Bank</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <table>
          <title>Selling a currency with a Split Transaction Scheme</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth='3*' align='left'/>

            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='center'/>

            <colspec colwidth='1*' align='center'/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Account
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Deposit
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Withdrawal
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Currency:Bank
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Sold Amount - Exchange Fee
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Expenses:Investments:Currency:Currency Bank:XXX
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Exchange Fee
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Currency:XXX
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  Sold Amount
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Income:Investments:Currency Bank:Capital Gains:XXX
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  [LOSS]
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  PROFIT
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Assets:Investments:Currency:XXX
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  PROFIT (with To Amount = 0)
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  [LOSS (with To Amount = 0) ]
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="currency_reconcile1">
      <title>Reconciling Statements in a Foreign Currency</title>

      <para>Reconciling foreign statement are done in the same manner as when you reconcile your local bank
        statement. If you have created a Chart of Accounts structure which allows you to have the
        same currency per account as your statement, it is actually exactly the same as reconciling
        your local bank statement.
      </para>

      <para>If you have different currencies you might have to manually convert the amounts from one currency to
        another while you reconcile the accounts.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="currency_trading_accts">
    <title>Automatically Recording Currency Transactions using Trading Accounts</title>

    <para>Trading accounts were introduced as a feature from &app; version 2.3.14. The conceptual basis for
      trading accounts is described in <ulink url="&url-selinger;accounting/tutorial.html">
      &tit-sel-tut;</ulink> by Peter Selinger. A second tutorial
      <ulink url="&url-selinger;accounting/gnucash.html"> &tit-sel-gnc;</ulink> by Peter Selinger
      describes the manual creation and use of trading accounts in &app; prior to version 2.3.14.
    </para>

    <para>Trading accounts are not enabled by default in &app;. To enable them go to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> <guimenuitem>Accounts
        tab</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      and check the <guilabel>Use Trading Accounts</guilabel> checkbox.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="trading_acct_concepts">
      <title>Trading Account Concepts</title>

      <para>In accounting terms, trading accounts are specialized equity accounts to record changes in revenue
        which result from transactions between two or more currencies. In &app; they are implemented
        as a top level account type of Trading. When trading accounts are enabled the required sub
        accounts of Trading are automatically created if they do not already exist when a
        transaction between one or more currencies is created.
      </para>

      <para>In the extended Accounting Equation, Trading accounts would appear as follows:
        <equation>
          <mathphrase>Assets = Liabilities + Equity (+ Income -Expenses) + Trading </mathphrase>
        </equation>
      </para>

      <caution>
        <para>The user is prevented from manually making entries directly to the registers for any of the accounts
          in the Trading top level account group. All entries to these accounts are automatically
          generated when transactions between currencies are created in other account registers
          within the &app;account heirarchy.
        </para>
      </caution>

      <para>The Trading account group is structured below the top level account <guilabel>Trading</guilabel>
        with a sub-account <guilabel>CURRENCY</guilabel> which in turn has a sub-account for each
        currency between which transactions have been made. For the example previously used in
        <link linkend="currency_manual">Manually Recording Currency Transactions</link>, the
        additional accounts which will be created automatically when transactions are created
        between different currencies with trading accounts enabled are:
      </para>
<screen>
Trading
    CURRENCY
        EUR
        HKD
        USD</screen>
      <caution>
        <para>The names of these accounts are again assigned automatically and cannot be changed by a user without
          disrupting the functionality of the trading accounts in &app;.
        </para>
      </caution>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="currency_trading">
      <title>Recording Foreign Currency Transactions with Trading Accounts</title>

      <sect3 id="currency_trading_account_setup">
        <title>Setup of Accounts for Trading Accounts</title>

        <para>The same account structure useds in the manual recording of currency transactions in the previous
          section is required. The initial account configuration for Assets and Equity accounts are
          as follows:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency__trading_acct_setup">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_acct_setup.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_acct_setup.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Initial multi currency Account Bank Setup</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Initial setup of bank accounts in multiple currencies.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The following prices were entered in the Price Database (
          <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Tools</guimenu><guisubmenu>Price Database</guisubmenu>
          </menuchoice>
          ) as at 01/01/2020 to convert the account balances for the foreign currency accounts to
          USD:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency__trading_price_database">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_Price_Database_initial.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_Price_Database_initial.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>The Price Database initial entries</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Price Database window after setting initial exchange rates between USD and HKD and EUR.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>With the currency prices set as shown, the Accounts tab will now display the values of the foreign
          accounts in USD in the <guilabel>Total(USD)</guilabel> column:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_acct_setup_2">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_acct_setup_2.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_acct_setup_2.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Initial multi currency setup after entering exchange rates between USD and HKD
              and EUR </phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para><guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab after setting exchange rates to USD.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="currency_trading_transfer">
        <title>Transfer of Funds to a Foreign Currency</title>

        <para>Let us assume we wish to purchase at item in Hong Kong using the Hong Kong bank account for $20000
          HKD on 01/02/2020. The current funds in the Hong Kong account are insufficient and we will
          need to transfer another $10200 HKD from the US bank account. The exchange rate at the
          time of the transfer is 1 USD = 7.7884 HKD and we will have to transfer $1309.64 USD for
          which the bank charges a $40 USD transfer fee. The transaction to effect this is created
          with the transfer funds dialog as shown below:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency__trading_tfr_dialog">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_transfer_funds.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_transfer_funds.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Transfer dialog to create transactionfor transfer from USD to HKD</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Transfer of 10200 HKD from US Bank account to Hong Kong bank account.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The debit amount has been specified in HKD and the transaction amount being transferred in USD.
          There is no provision to enter the transfer fee in the dialog. On closing the dialog the
          following transaction as viewed in the US Bank Account register has been created:
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>Entering the Amount for the account that the funds are being transferred from the selected Credit
            Account and selecting the Debit Amount radio button and then entering the foreign
            currency amount to be debited generally provides a transaction recording the correct
            amounts whereas entering an exchange rate will often not give the exact value actually
            transferred in the foreign currency because of rounding errors.
          </para>
        </note>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_transfer_trans1">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_transfer_trans1.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"  width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_transfer_trans1.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Transaction after transfer displayed in US Bank account register</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Transaction to transfer from US bank account to Hong Kong Bank account after closing transfer
                dialog.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The transaction can be opened in the US Bank Account register and may then be edited to add splits
          for the transfer fee as follows:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_transfer_trans2">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_transfer_trans2.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"  width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_transfer_trans2.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Transaction after adding the splits for the transfer fee</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Transaction to transfer from US bank account to Hong Kong Bank account after adding the splits for
                the transaction fee.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>Returning to the Accounts tab we can see the result of the transfer transaction on the accounts:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_accts_after_tfr">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_accts_after_tfr.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_accts_after_tfr.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Account tab balances after completion of USD to HKD transfer</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Account balances in the Accounts tab after the transfer of funds from the US Bank account to the
                Hong Kong bank account.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The balances of the Asset and Equity accounts are presented with values set by the exchange rate
          entered in the transaction to transfer funds on 01/02/2020.
        </para>

        <para>The trading accounts have been automatically created and the amounts of the transfer have been
          entered into the accounts. There are no entries associated with the pre-existing opening
          balances of the accounts prior to the transfer. This reflects that the trading accounts
          only reflect gains and losses since the book was opened.
        </para>

        <para>At this point there have been no trading gains or losses. The balances of the USD and HKD trading
          accounts are the same when converted to USD. The HKD trading account has a debit (-ve
          balance) and the USD trading account has a credit balance (+ve balance). The nett balance
          of the CURRENCY sub account of Trading, and Trading itself, is 0 indicating that at this
          point no gains or losses have been recorded in the trading of currencies.
        </para>

        <para>The hypothetical purchase in Hong Kong fails to take place and a month later on 01/03/2020 the funds
          are required in the US account for another purpose. A transfer of $10200.00 HKD is made
          from the Hong Kong bank account back to the US bank account. The exchange rate at the time
          of the transfer is 1USD = 7.7933 HKD and a fee of $20.00 USD is charged for the transfer.
          The transaction to effect the transfer is:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_tfr_back">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_trf_back.png" format="PNG"
                         srccredit="David Cousens"  width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_trf_back.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Transaction to transfer funds from Hong Kong to US Bank account.</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>The transaction transfers $10200.00 HKD from the Hong Kong Bank account to the US Bank account.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>After transferring the funds back to the US Bank account, the prices database entries are as
          follows:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_prices_after_trf_back">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_prices_after_trf_back.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_prices_after_trf_back.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Price database after transfer of funds back to US account</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>The price database showing prices for the transfer of funds to HKD and back to USD.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The Accounts tab balances after transferring the funds back are:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_accts_after_trf_back">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_accts_after_trf_back.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_accts_after_trf_back.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Accounts tab after transfer back</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>State of the accounts after the funds have been transferred back.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The Assets and Equity balances now reflect the the values of the accounts at the exchange rate for
          the transfer of funds back to the US Bank account. The Trading accounts now indicate a
          modest realized loss of US$0.82 on the currency transactions indicated by the balances in
          the CURRENCY and Trading placeholder accounts. The associated transfer fees appear in the
          Expenses total. Not a profitable exercise but still illustrative.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>The gains or losses reported using trading accounts are realized gains and losses.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>Finally we have the balance sheet after the above sequence of transactions reporting the Trading
          Loss incurred:
        </para>

        <screenshot id="currency_trading_balance_sheet">
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_balance_sheet.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens" width="510"/>
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="figures/currency_trading_balance_sheet.png"
                format="PNG" srccredit="David Cousens"/>
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>Balance sheet after above transactions</phrase>
            </textobject>

            <caption>
              <para>Balance Sheet after these transactions reflecting the trading loss incurred.
              </para>
            </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
