<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-docbookx.dtd">

<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.0
  Last modified: December 7th 2009
       modified: July 9th 2006
  Maintainers:
  Author:

  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="chapter_importing">
  <title>Importing Data into <application>&app;</application></title>
  <para>This chapter will detail procedures for importing data into <application>&app;</application>.</para>
  <sect1 id="importing-from-files">
  <title>Importing Transactions from Files</title>

  <para>Imported transactions will generally be to a specific account in your account tree. In the following
          this will be referred to as the <emphasis role="bold">import</emphasis> or
          <emphasis role="bold">base</emphasis> account. It may or may not be
          specified in the data being imported, depending on the import format. It is usually the first split
          of a transaction being imported.
  </para>
  <para>All transactions will also must have a <emphasis role="bold">destination</emphasis> account for
          at least matching splits. This may or may not be supplied in the imported data. If it is not,
          an account can be assigned on the basis of the previous import history by matching to infomation in
          the imported data. The user may always over-ride this assignment.
  </para>
  <para>Multi-split data previously exported from GnuCash may have both the import and destination accounts
          for transaction splits specified in the data file.
  </para>
  <sect2>
    <title>File Import Formats</title>
    <para>Gnucash allows transactions to be imported in the following formats:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="importing-qif">QIF</link></emphasis>
             (.qif) Quicken Interchange format - import data from Quicken financial software;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="importing-ofx">OFX/QFX</link></emphasis>
             (.ofx,.qfx) Open Financial eXchange format (QXF is an Intuit/Quicken proprietary version of OFX);
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="importing-csv">CSV</link></emphasis>
             (.csv)  Comma Separated Values;</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="importing-mt940">MT940</link></emphasis>
              MT940</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="importing-mt942">MT942</link></emphasis>
               MT942</para></listitem>
           <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold"><link linkend="importing-dtaus">DTAUS</link></emphasis>
                DTAUS</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    <para>These import methods can be accessed from <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Import ...</guisubmenu></menuchoice>.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="importing-matcher">
    <title>Import Matcher</title>
    <para>Several of the Import Assistants use an Import Matcher to implement a Bayesian approach to assign
        destination accounts, if such accounts are not specified in
        the imported data, to each imported transaction based on the previous import history of the import account.
        It also attempts to match the transactions being imported to any existing transactions
        based on the date and the description fields<!-- FIXME add any other fields used in matching -->.
    </para>
    <para>Transaction rows which match existing transactions already in the import account are flagged not to be imported. They
      will have a light green background and the A and U+R checkboxes will be unchecked and the R checkbox will be
      checked. To override and import the transaction, check the A checkbox. The U and R boxes will be unchecked
      automatically. The reliability of the match is indicated by a bar display in the Info column. If a destination
      account for the second split is assigned by the matcher if will be appended to the info column.
    </para>
    <para>Transaction rows which do not match existing transactions in the import account, for which an assignment
      of a destination account cannot be made on the basis of the previous import history to the account, will be
      displayed with an orange-yellow background and the A box will be checked and U+R and R unchecked. A destination
      account must be specified for these transactions.
    </para>
   <sect3><title>Assign a Destination Account to a Single Transaction</title>
      <para>The currently selected row is selected by Left-clicking it. It is displayed with a mid dark green background.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Double click</emphasis> on a row. This will select it and open an Account Selection
            dialog. Select the desired destination account in the dialog and click <guilabel>OK</guilabel>. The row
            background will change to a light green and the assigned destination account will be displayed
            in the Info column.
      </para>
      <para>or alternatively, <emphasis role="bold">Left-click</emphasis> on a row to select it followed by a
         <emphasis role="bold">Right-click </emphasis>to bring up a popup menu then select
        "Assign a transfer account" to display the Account Selection dialog, select the destination account and
         click the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Assign a Destination Account to Multiple Transactions</title>
      <para>Sometimes you will have several transactions which will have the same destination account. Gnucash
            allows you to select multiple transactions and apply the same destination account to all transactions
            in the selection.
      </para>
      <para>Rows in a selection are displayed with a mid dark green background.</para>
      <para>Multiple rows may be selected to have the same destination account assigned to them.</para>
      <para>To select rows either:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Left click</emphasis> on first row and then
        <emphasis role="bold">Ctrl-Left click</emphasis> on other rows to add to the selection or</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Left-click</emphasis> on a first row and then
        <emphasis role="bold">Shift-Left-click</emphasis> on another row to select all rows between them.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>then <emphasis role="bold">Right-click</emphasis> to display a popup menu and then select
        <emphasis role="bold">"Assign a transfer account"</emphasis> to open the Account
         Selection dialog. Select the desired destination account and click the <guilabel>OK</guilabel>
         button in the Account Selection dialog.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Completing the Import</title>
    <para>Once you have assigned destination accounts for all the imported transactions using the above methods
      (all row backgrounds will be a light green colour), check that the assigned destination acounts are correct
      and then press the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button at the bottom of the Generic Import Matcher
      window. The transactions selected for import will have their splits added to the selected source
      and destination accounts.
    </para>
    <para>The choices made for the destination accounts and description/memo fields are remembered and stored and
      used for future imports to the same account to automatically assign a destination account for transaction
      records not containing destination account information.
    </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="importing-qif">
    <title>Import QIF</title>
    <para>To import data from Quicken®, MS Money, or other programs that use QIF(Quicken® Interchange Format),
          you must first export your data to a QIF file. One way to do this is to export each account as a
          separate QIF file. An easier way, available in Quicken® 98 and beyond, is to export all accounts at
          once into a single QIF file. Check your program's manual to determine if this option is available.
    </para>
    <sect3><title>To import QIF files:</title><para> </para></sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Load all of the QIF files containing data you wish to import</title>
      <para>To do this, select <emphasis role="bold">File -> Import -> Import QIF...</emphasis> from the menu. When the QIF Import dialog
            box appears, click <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis> and follow the instructions to guide you through the process of loading
            your files.
      </para>
      <para>This image shows the start of the QIF Import assistant.<!--FIXME put an image of the import druid in --> </para>
      <para>You will be prompted for a filename to load. Use the Select button to select your QIF file and
           click Next to load it. Once the file is loaded, select Load another file if you have more files
           to load. When you have loaded all your QIF files, click Next to continue with the import process.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Review the GnuCash accounts to be created.</title>
      <para>The importer then matches up your QIF accounts and categories with GnuCash accounts and gives
            you a brief description of the matching process. Clicking Next will bring you to a view comparing
            your QIF accounts with the corresponding GnuCash accounts created. To change an account name, select
            the row containing that account name and edit the name in the dialog box provided. Click Next when
            you have finished making changes, and proceed through a similar category matching process. QIF
            income and expense categories import as GnuCash income and expense accounts <!--(see section 3.1 FIXME for
            more on this).--> Make changes to these account names if necessary, and click Next to continue.
      </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> If you are not sure what changes are needed, it is safe to
            accept the GnuCash account names. It is easy to edit the accounts later if you find you need to make
            a change.
      </para>
      <para>From the drop-down list, select a standard currency to be used for the  imported accounts and click <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis>
            to continue. If you have stocks, mutual funds, or other securities, you will be prompted for additional
            information. The importer dialog will ask for the exchange or listing (i.e. Nasdaq), the security's
            full name, and the ticker symbol. If you do not have this information handy, you can edit the account
            information later, once the import is complete. Click <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis> to continue.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Tell GnuCash to import the data.</title>
      <para>The last step is the import. Once you have verified your account names and investment information,
            click <emphasis role="bold">Finish</emphasis> in the Update your GnuCash accounts page to complete the import process. Depending
            upon the size of your file, the import might take a few minutes to complete, so a progress bar
            displays the percentage finished. When the import process is complete, GnuCash will return you
            to the main window, which should now display the names of the accounts you imported.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <!--
  <sect2 id="importing-qif-from-help">
    <title>Importing Quicken QIF Files</title>

        <para>Many users seek to import their financial data from Quicken.</para>
        <para>This Assistant helps you import Quicken <acronym>QIF</acronym> files. It will appear if
        you choose <guibutton>Import my QIF files</guibutton> in the
        <guilabel>Welcome to &app;!</guilabel> menu, as well as from <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guisubmenu>Import ...</guisubmenu> <guimenuitem>Import QIF...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>

            <para>The import process involves several steps, which are presented in a
                series of screens that are described below.</para>

      <orderedlist>
      <listitem>

            <para><guilabel>Import QIF files</guilabel> screen briefly describes the assistant.
            The three buttons at the very bottom of the screen are used throughout the process
            to navigate.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>: exit the process and cancel importing
              <acronym>QIF</acronym> files.</para>
              <warning>
                <para>If you choose to cancel at any point in the assistant, any selections you have made up to
                this point will be lost.</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Back</guibutton>: return to the previous screen.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Next</guibutton> move to the next screen.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>

            <para><guilabel>Select a QIF file to load</guilabel> allows you to choose the
            source <acronym>QIF</acronym> file. The <guibutton>Select...</guibutton> button on this
            screen is used to access a list of files in your system. The
            <guibutton>Select...</guibutton> button brings up the <guilabel>Select
            QIF File</guilabel> dialog.</para>

            <para>Navigate to where you have stored your <acronym>QIF</acronym> files and select the
            first one then click <guibutton>Import</guibutton>. The next screen will
            display it in the <guilabel>Select a QIF File to Load</guilabel>
            field.</para>

            <note>
              <para>If the file you are loading does not have an <acronym>QIF</acronym> date listed
              in it you will see the <guilabel>Set a date format for this QIF file</guilabel>
              screen. Select the proper format from the pull down list and continue.</para>
            </note>

            <note>
              <para>If the file you are loading does not have an account name listed
              in it you will see the <guilabel>Set the default QIF account
              name</guilabel> screen. Otherwise you will skip this screen and go on
              to the screen in the next section that shows loaded <acronym>QIF</acronym> files.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The <guilabel>Account name:</guilabel> field is used to set
                  an account name for this <acronym>QIF</acronym> file.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </note>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
            <para>The next screen shows you the <guilabel>QIF files you have
            loaded</guilabel>. You can use this screen to return to the previous
            screen and load more <acronym>QIF</acronym> files. It will also let you unload any files
            you have loaded by mistake.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The top panel shows the list of <guilabel>QIF Files</guilabel>
                you have loaded.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>Load another file</guibutton> button takes you
                back to the previous screen to load another <acronym>QIF</acronym> file.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>Unload selected file</guibutton> button allows you to
                select a file from the top panel and remove it from the list.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>When you have selected all the <acronym>QIF</acronym> files to be imported, click the
            <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> button.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>

            <para>Depending on the type of data contained in the
            <acronym>QIF</acronym> files to be imported, you may see only one or all of the following screens:</para>

      <variablelist termlength="8">
        <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Accounts and stock holdings</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This screen gives a description of the <guilabel>Accounts and stock
            holdings</guilabel> matching process on the following <guilabel>Match QIF
            accounts with &app; accounts</guilabel> screen.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>This and other informational screens in the
              <guilabel>Import QIF files</guilabel> assistant
              can be turned off in the <guilabel>Online Banking</guilabel> tab (see <xref linkend="configuring-preferences-online-banking"/>)
              under <guilabel>&app; Preferences</guilabel>.</para>
            </tip>

            <para>The next screen lets you <guilabel>Match QIF accounts with &app;
            accounts</guilabel>. You will see a list of <guilabel>QIF account
            names</guilabel> on the left and suggested <guilabel>&app; account
            names</guilabel> on the right. The <guilabel>New?</guilabel> column
            indicates if the <application>&app;</application> account name will be created by the <acronym>QIF</acronym>
            Import.</para>

            <para>To change the <application>&app;</application> account to a different one select the <acronym>QIF</acronym>
            account. A screen will pop up to select another account or create a new
            one.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Select an account from the list to choose a already existing
                account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>New Account</guibutton> button allows you to
                add a new account name as a sub-account (child of selected) of the
                selected account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button is used to confirm your
                selection.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button is used to exit the
                dialog without using any changes you have made.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Income and Expense categories</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This screen gives a description of the <guilabel>Income and
            Expense categories</guilabel> matching process on the following <guilabel>Match
            QIF categories with &app; accounts</guilabel> screen.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>This and other informational screens in the
              <guilabel>Import QIF files</guilabel> assistant
              can be turned off in the <guilabel>Online Banking</guilabel> tab (see <xref linkend="configuring-preferences-online-banking"/>)
              under <guilabel>&app; Preferences</guilabel>.</para>
            </tip>

            <para>The next screen lets you <guilabel>Match QIF categories with
            &app; accounts</guilabel>. You will see a list of <guilabel>QIF
            category names</guilabel> on the left and suggested <guilabel>&app;
            account names</guilabel> on the right. The <guilabel>New?</guilabel>
            column indicates if the <application>&app;</application> account name will be created by the QIF
            Import.</para>

            <para>To change the <application>&app;</application> account to a different one select the QIF
            category. A dialog will pop up to select another account or create a new
            one.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Select an account from the list to choose a already existing
                account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>New Account</guibutton> button allows you to
                add a new account name as a sub-account (child of selected) of the
                selected account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button is used to confirm your
                selection.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button is used to exit the
                dialog without using any changes you have made.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Payees and memos</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
            <para>This screen gives a description of the <guilabel>Payees and
            memos</guilabel> matching process on the following <guilabel>Match payees/memos to
            &app; accounts</guilabel> screen.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>This and other informational screens in the
              <guilabel>Import QIF files</guilabel> assistant
              can be turned off in the <guilabel>Online Banking</guilabel> tab (see <xref linkend="configuring-preferences-online-banking"/>)
              under <guilabel>&app; Preferences</guilabel>.</para>
            </tip>

            <para>The next screen lets you <guilabel>Match payees/memos to &app;
            accounts</guilabel>. You will see a list of <guilabel>QIF payee/memo
            names</guilabel> on the left and suggested <guilabel>&app; account
            names</guilabel> on the right. The default <application>&app;</application> account used is
            called <guilabel>Unspecified</guilabel>. The <guilabel>New?</guilabel> column indicates if
            the <application>&app;</application> account name will be created by the QIF Import.</para>

            <para>To change the <application>&app;</application> account to a different one select the QIF
            payee/memo. A dialog will pop up to select another account or create a
            new one.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Select an account from the list to choose a already existing
                account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>New Account</guibutton> button allows you to
                add a new account name as a sub-account of the selected
                account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button is used to confirm your
                selection.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button is used to exit the
                dialog without using any changes you have made.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>

            <para>The next screen allows you to <guilabel>Enter the QIF file
            currency</guilabel>. The drop down list defaults to the currency
            configured in the <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab (see <xref linkend="configuring-preferences-accounts"/>) under
            <guilabel>&app; Preferences</guilabel>. If you wish the new accounts
            to use a different currency, select one from the list.</para>

            <para>When you have selected the currency, click the
            <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> button.</para>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>

            <para>Depending on the type of data contained in the
            <acronym>QIF</acronym> files to be imported, you may or may not see one or more of the following screens:</para>

      <variablelist termlength="8">
        <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Tradable Commodities</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This screen gives a description of the <guilabel>Tradable
            Commodities</guilabel> process on the screen.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>This and other informational screens in the
              <guilabel>Import QIF files</guilabel> assistant
              can be turned off in the <guilabel>Online Banking</guilabel> tab (see <xref linkend="configuring-preferences-online-banking"/>)
              under <guilabel>&app; Preferences</guilabel>.</para>
            </tip>

            <para>A series of screens, one for each of the stock, mutual fund, or
            commodity, displays the exchange, full name, and symbol for each of the commodities
            listed in the <acronym>QIF</acronym> file you are importing so that you can
            check them before proceeding.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Match duplicate transactions</guilabel></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This screen gives a description of the <guilabel>Match
            duplicate transactions</guilabel> process on the following <guilabel>Select
            possible duplicates</guilabel> screen.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>This and other informational screens in the
              <guilabel>Import QIF files</guilabel> assistant
              can be turned off in the <guilabel>Online Banking</guilabel> tab (see <xref linkend="configuring-preferences-online-banking"/>)
              under <guilabel>&app; Preferences</guilabel>.</para>
            </tip>

            <para>The next screen lets you <guilabel>Select possible duplicate
            transactions</guilabel>. Imported transactions are shown on the left
            panel and possible matches to each selected transaction are shown on the
            right.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The left panel shows the list of Imported transactions to
                select from for matching duplicates</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The right panel shows the list of <emphasis>possible</emphasis> duplicates for the
                selected imported transaction. Select the one that most closely
                matches</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>

            <para>The last screen, <guibutton>Update your &app;
            accounts</guibutton>, gives you a list of three choices to finish the
            assistant.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Cancel:</guibutton> exit the process and cancel importing
              <acronym>QIF</acronym> files.</para>
              <warning>
                <para>If you click this button, any selections you have made up to
                this point will be lost.</para>
              </warning>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Back:</guibutton> brings up the previous screen so
              that you can change a previous selection until the first screen.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guibutton>Forward:</guibutton> imports the data and creates the
              accounts you have specified.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

            <para>You should now have successfully imported your accounts.</para>

            <tip>
              <para>Imported transactions might need to be <emphasis role="strong">reconciled</emphasis>.
              This process is described in the <application>&app;</application> Tutorial and Concepts guide.</para>
            </tip>

        </sect2>
      -->

  <sect2 id="importing-ofx">
    <title>Import OFX/QFX</title>
    <para>This opens a file selection dialog. Navigate to the file you wish to import, select a file with
      the appropriate extension (.ofx  or .qfx), then press the <emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis> button.</para>
    <para>Gnucash opens an Account Selection dialog to select an account in your CoA corresponding to data source. Select
      the appropriate account from the account tree and press the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button. On subsequent import of files from the
      same source (identified by tags in the file), the source is remembered and the account selection dialog is not
      displayed.</para>
    <para>The generic import transaction matcher dialog is opened next. See the <link linkend="importing-matcher">
          Import Matcher</link> section (common to both OFX/QFX and CSV import formats) following the Import CSV
          section to continue the import process.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="importing-csv">
    <title>Import CSV</title>
    <para>Clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Import CSV</emphasis> in the Import menu will bring up the Import Assistant dialog. The first step brings up a file selection
          dialog. Navigate to the location where the file you wish to import is located and select the file to import then click the
          <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button.
    </para>
    <para>The next window will allow you to set parameters for the importing of the file. All widgets have tooltips which explain what
          the setting affects and the options for the setting.
    </para>
    <sect3 id="importing-csv-save">
        <title>Load and Save Settings</title>
        <para>If this import is a regular occurrence, once you have set the other import paramters, you can save these settings by typing
              in a setting name in the <emphasis role="bold">Load and Save Settings Entry</emphasis> combo box and pressing the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button just to the right of the box.
              Previously defined settings can be retrieved by selecting the appropriate setting name from the dropdown list activated by
              the down arrow at the right end of the text box. The trash can button to the right of the Save button can be used to remove
              the settings selected from the drop down list for the box. The settings group <emphasis role="bold">"GnuCash Export Settings"</emphasis> define a setting
              group for the export and reimport of GnuCash transaction data - use this if importing data previously exported from GnuCash.
        </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Account</title>
      <para>This combo box allows you to select the base or import account into which the transactions will be imported.  It may be left unset
            if the imported data contains a column listing the accounts associated with each split or the import data
            specifies the account for first split of the transaction.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>File Format</title>
      <para>This section allows you to define whether the file has:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Fixed width columns</emphasis> Selecting this radio button will allow you to define
               column boundaries by double clicking at the appropriate positions in the sample records displayed in the
               panel below. Single clicking in a column will narrow, widen or merge the column.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Separators</emphasis> Selecting this radio button will allow you to define characters
                which will be used to distinguish columns in the input file. The default is comma separated however spaces,
                tabs,colons or semicolons or any combination of them may be used to separate columns in the input file by
                selecting the appropriate check boxes. You may also define custom separators by typing the required characters
                into the text box and selecting the <emphasis role="bold">Custom</emphasis> checkbox. This may be used in combination with any of the
                predefined separators.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Multi-split</emphasis> Selecting this check box allows the splits for a single transaction
               to be defined on consecutive lines within the file with each line defining a single split. If not selected each
               line is assumed to contain the information for a single transaction including one or two splits.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
      <para>The miscellaneous settings allow you to set:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Encoding</emphasis>This is usually the UTF-8 variant for your locale;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Date Format</emphasis> This does not default to the Locale setting so check it matches the data you are importing;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Currency Format</emphasis>;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Leading Lines to Skip</emphasis>;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Trailing Lines to Skip</emphasis>;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Skip alternate lines</emphasis>;</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
       <para>to match the settings for the file you are importing. Tooltips may also contain information on the setting and options.</para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Import Panel</title>
      <para>The import panel shows the data being imported as it is interpreted using the settings chosen to define columns and formats.
          The dropdown lists in the headers for each column of the import allow you to associate a specific column in the imported data
          with a specific field in the display of a transaction in an account register. At a minimum to import data, columns in the
          imported data containing the following information <emphasis role="bold">must</emphasis> be specified:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Date </emphasis>of transaction;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Account</emphasis> into which transaction is to be imported (or alternatively set the base account as above);</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis> of the transaction;</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Deposit or Withdrawal</emphasis> column.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Skip Errors</emphasis> check box will skip trying to import any rows with errors in matching the columns.
      </para>
      <para>When you are happy with all the import settings, <link linkend="importing-csv-save">save</link> them
           if you will use the same settings again, then press the <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis> button.
          This will bring up a window which allows you to map the accounts identified in the account column (Account Id) with accounts
          in the GnuCash account tree (Account name). Double click on a row to bring up a dialog to select the matching GnuCash account.
          When you have selected a match for all accounts, click on the <emphasis role="bold">Next</emphasis> button.
      </para>
      <para>The Transaction Information panel allows review of data entry settings so far.
      </para>
      <para>Clicking on Match Transactions will then bring up the main <link linkend="importing-matcher">Import Matcher</link>
            window described in the next section.
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="importing-mt940">
    <title>Import MT940</title>
    <para>Use this option to import MT940 data.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="importing-mt942">
    <title>Import MT942</title>
    <para>Use this option to import MT942 data.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="importing-dtaus">
    <title>Import DTAUS</title>
    <para>Use this option to import DTAUS data.</para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
