<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.0
  Last modified: July 9th 2006
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Author:
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
  	Updated	Bengt Thuree <bengt@thuree.com>
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="chapter_loans">
  <title>Loans</title>

  <para>This chapter explains how to manage your loans with GnuCash.</para>

  <sect1 id="loans_concepts1">
    <title>Basic Concepts</title>

    <para>A loan is defined as a financial transaction in which someone pays
    for the use of someone else's money. There are many familiar examples of
    loans: credits cards, auto loans, house mortgages, or a business
    loan.</para>

    <sect2 id="loans_conceptsterms2">
      <title>Terminology</title>

      <para>Before discussing tracking loan in GnuCash specifically, it will
      be helpful to present a glossary of terminology. The terms presented
      below represent some of the basic concepts found concerning loans. It is
      a good idea to become familiar with these terms, or at least, refer back
      to this list if you encounter an unfamiliar word in the later
      sections.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Amortization</emphasis> - the repayment plan which
          will insure that a loan is eventually paid off, typically utilizing
          equal valued monthly payments. These payments are usually split into
          principal and interest, where the amount of principal per payment
          increases (and interest decreases) as the amortization period
          elapses.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Borrower</emphasis> - the person or company that
          receives the money from a loan.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default</emphasis> - when a borrower fails to repay
          a loan according to the terms agreed upon with the lender.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Deferment</emphasis> - a temporary delay in the
          repayment of a loan.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Delinquency</emphasis> - is the term that refers to
          late payments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Disbursement</emphasis> - amount of the loan paid to
          the borrower. Some loans have multiple disbursements, meaning the
          borrower does not receive the full amount of the loan at one
          time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Interest</emphasis> - the expense charged by the
          lender to the borrower for the use of the money loaned. This is
          typically expressed in terms of a yearly percentage charged on the
          principal borrowed, known as the <emphasis>Annual Percentage
          Rate</emphasis> or APR.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Lender</emphasis> - the company or person who lends
          money to a borrower.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Loan Fee</emphasis> - a processing fee removed from
          the principal at the time the borrower receives a loan.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Principal</emphasis> - the original amount of the
          loan, or the amount of the original loan that is still owed. When
          you make a monthly payment on a loan, part of the money pays the
          interest, and part pays the principal.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Promissory Note</emphasis> - the legal agreement
          between the borrower and lender concerning the loan.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_accounts1">
    <title>Setting Up Accounts</title>

    <para>When a borrower obtains a loan, it is usually with the intention to
    make a purchase of something of value. In fact, most loans require the
    borrower to buy some predetermined asset, such as a house. This asset is
    insurance against the borrower defaulting on the loan. There are, of
    course, examples of loans which do not necessarily have an associated high
    value asset, such as educational loans.</para>

    <para>For the account structure presented here, we will assume the loan
    was used to purchase a compensating asset.</para>

    <para>A loan is a liability, the interest you accrue on the loan is an
    on-going expense, and any administrative fees you may have to pay would be
    another expense. The thing purchased with the money from a loan is an
    asset. With these parameters, we can now present a basic loan account
    structure:</para>

    <literallayout>
Basic Loan Account Structure

-Asset
    -Current Assets
        -Savings Account
    -Fixed Assets
        -Asset Purchased
-Liability
   -Loans
       -Mortgage Loan
-Expenses
   -Interest
       -Mortgage Interest
   -Mortgage Adm Fees
  </literallayout>

    <para>GnuCash has a number of predefined loan account hierarchies
    available, including Car Loans and Home Mortgage Loans. To access these
    predefined account structures, click on 
    <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>New Account Hierarchy</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> and select the loan types in which you are interested.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_calcs1">
    <title>Calculations</title>

    <para>Determining loan amortization schedules, periodic payment amounts,
    total payment value, or interest rates can be somewhat complex. To help
    facilitate these kinds of calculations, GnuCash has a built-in Financial
    Calculator. To access the calculator, go to <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Tools</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Financial Calculator</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.</para>

    <screenshot id="loans_fcalc">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_fcalc.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>Financial Calculator</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption><para>The GnuCash Financial Calculator.</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The Financial Calculator can be used to calculate any one of the
    parameters: <guilabel>Payment Periods</guilabel>, <guilabel>Interest
    Rate</guilabel>, <guilabel>Present Value</guilabel>, <guilabel>Periodic
    Payment</guilabel>, or <guilabel>Future Value</guilabel> given that the
    other 4 have been defined. You will also need to specify the compounding
    and payment methods.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Payment Periods</emphasis> - the number of payment
        periods.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Interest Rate</emphasis> - the nominal interest rate
        of the loan, ie: the yearly interest rate.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Present Value</emphasis> - the present value of the
        loan, ie: current amount owed on the loan.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Periodic Payment</emphasis> - the amount to pay per
        period.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Future Value</emphasis> - the future value of the
        loan, ie: the amount owed after all payment periods are over.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Compounding</emphasis> - two interest compounding
        methods exist, discrete or continuous. For discrete compounding select
        the compounding frequency from the popup menu with a range from yearly
        to daily.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Payments</emphasis> - the popup menu allows you to
        select the payment frequency with a range from yearly to daily. You
        can also select whether your payments occur at the beginning or end of
        the period. Payments made at the beginning of the payment period have
        interest applied to the payment as well as any previous money paid or
        money still owed.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="loans_calcsexample1_2">
      <title>Example: Monthly Payments</title>

      <para>What is your monthly payment on a $100000 30 year loan at a fixed
      rate of 4% compounded monthly?</para>

      <para>This scenario is shown in the example image above. To perform this
      calculation, set Payment Periods to 360 (12 months x 30 years), Interest
      Rate to 4, Present Value to 100000, leave Periodic Payment empty and set
      Future Value to 0 (you do not want to owe anything at the end of the
      loan). Compounding is Monthly, Payments are Monthly, assume End of
      Period Payments, and Discrete Compounding. Now, click on the
      <guibutton>Calculate</guibutton> button next to the Periodic Payment
      area. You should see $-477.42.</para>

      <para>Answer: You must make monthly payments of 477.42.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="loans_calcsexample2_2">
      <title>Example: Length of Loan</title>

      <para>How long will you be paying back a $20000 loan at 10% fixed rate
      interest compounded monthly if you pay $500 per month?</para>

      <para>To perform this calculation, leave Payment Periods empty, set
      Interest Rate to 10, Present Value to 20000, Periodic Payment is -500,
      and set Future Value is 0 (you do not want to owe anything at the end of
      the loan). Compounding is Monthly, Payments are Monthly, assume End of
      Period Payments, and Discrete Compounding. Now, click on the
      <guibutton>Calculate</guibutton> button next to the Payment Periods
      area. You should see 48.</para>

      <para>Answer: You will pay off the loan in 4 years (48 months).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="loans_calcsdetails2">
      <title>Advanced: Calculation Details</title>

      <para>In order to discuss the mathematical formulas used by the
      Financial Calculator, we first must define some
      variables.
<literallayout>
 n  == number of payment periods
 %i  == nominal interest rate, NAR, charged
 PV  == Present Value
 PMT == Periodic Payment
 FV  == Future Value
 CF == Compounding Frequency per year
 PF == Payment Frequency per year

Normal values for CF and PF are:
   1   == annual
   2   == semi-annual
   3   == tri-annual
   4   == quaterly
   6   == bi-monthly
   12  == monthly
   24  == semi-monthly
   26  == bi-weekly
   52  == weekly
   360 == daily
   365 == daily
</literallayout>
      </para>

      <sect3 id="loans_calcsdetails_i2">
        <title>Converting between nominal and effective interest rate</title>

        <para>When a solution for n, PV, PMT or FV is required, the nominal
        interest rate (i) must first be converted to the effective
        interest rate per payment period (ieff). This rate,
        ieff, is then used to compute the selected variable. When a solution
        for i is required, the computation produces the effective interest
        rate (ieff). Thus, we need functions which convert from i to ieff, and
        from ieff to i.</para>

        <literallayout>
To convert from i to ieff, the following expressions are used:
Discrete Interest:     <emphasis>ieff = (1 + i/CF)^(CF/PF) - 1</emphasis>
Continuous Interest: <emphasis>ieff = e^(i/PF) - 1 = exp(i/PF) - 1</emphasis>

To convert from ieff to i, the following expressions are used:
Discrete Interst:      <emphasis>i = CF*[(1+ieff)^(PF/CF) - 1]</emphasis>
Continuous Interest: <emphasis>i = ln[(1+ieff)^PF]</emphasis>
</literallayout>

        <note>
          <para>NOTE: in the equations below for the financial transaction,
          all interest rates are the effective interest rate, ieff. For the
          sake of brevity, the symbol will be shortened to just 'i'.</para>
        </note>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="loans_calcsdetails_basic2">
        <title>The basic financial equation</title>

        <para>One equation fundamentally links all the 5 variables. This is
        known as the fundamental financial equation:</para>

        <literallayout>
<emphasis>PV*(1 + i)^n + PMT*(1 + iX)*[(1+i)^n - 1]/i + FV = 0</emphasis>

  Where: X = 0 for end of period payments, and
         X = 1 for beginning of period payments
</literallayout>

        <para>From this equation, functions which solve for the individual
        variables can be derived. For a detailed explanation of the derivation
        of this equation, see the comments in the file src/calculation/fin.c
        from the GnuCash source code. The A, B, and C variables are defined
        first, to make the later equations simpler to read.</para>

        <literallayout>
<emphasis>A = (1 + i)^n - 1</emphasis>
<emphasis>B = (1 + iX)/i</emphasis>
<emphasis>C = PMT*B</emphasis>

<emphasis>n = ln[(C - FV)/(C + PV)]/ln((1 + i)</emphasis>
<emphasis>PV = -[FV + A*C]/(A + 1)</emphasis>
<emphasis>PMT = -[FV + PV*(A + 1)]/[A*B]</emphasis>
<emphasis>FV = -[PV + A*(PV + C)] </emphasis>

The solution for interest is broken into two cases.  
The simple case for when  PMT == 0 gives the solution:
<emphasis>i = [FV/PV]^(1/n) - 1</emphasis>

</literallayout>

        <para>The case where PMT != 0 is fairly complex and will not be
        presented here. Rather than involving an exactly solvable function,
        determining the interest rate when PMT !=0 involves an iterative
        process. Please see the src/calculation/fin.c source file for a
        detailed explanation.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="loans_calcsdetails_ex2">
        <title>Example: Monthly Payments</title>

        <para>Let's recalculate <xref linkend="loans_calcsexample1_2"/>, 
        this time using the
        mathematical formulas rather than the Financial Calculator. What is
        your monthly payment on a $100000 30 year loan at a fixed rate of 4%
        compounded monthly?</para>

        <para>First, let's define the variables: n = (30*12) = 360, PV =
        100000, PMT = unknown, FV = 0, i = 4%=4/100=0.04, CF = PF = 12, X = 0
        (end of payment periods).</para>

        <para>The second step is to convert the nominal interest rate (i) to
        the effective interest rate (ieff). Since the interest rate is
        compounded monthly, it is discrete, and we use: ieff = (1 +
        i/CF)^(CF/PF) - 1, which gives ieff = (1 + 0.04/12)^(12/12) - 1, thus
        ieff = 1/300 = 0.0033333.</para>

        <para>Now we can calculate A and B. A = (1 + i)^n - 1 = (1 +
        1/300)^360 - 1 = 2.313498. B = (1 + iX)/i = (1 + (1/300)*0)/(1/300) =
        300.</para>

        <para>With A and B, we can calculate PMT. PMT = -[FV + PV*(A +
        1)]/[A*B] = -[0 + 100000*(2.313498 + 1)] / [2.313498 * 300] =
        -331349.8 / 694.0494 = -477.415296 = -477.42.</para>

        <para>Answer: You must make monthly payments of 477.42.</para>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_mortgage1">
    <title>House Mortgage (How-To)</title>

    <para>A house mortgage can be setup using the account structure present in
    <xref linkend="loans_accounts1" />.</para>

    <para>As an example, assume you have $60k in you bank account, and you buy
    a $150k house. The mortgage is charging 6% APR, and has administrative
    fees (closing costs, etc) of 3%. You decide to put $50k down, and thus
    will need to borrow $103k, which will give you $100 after the closing
    costs are paid (3% of $100k).</para>

    <para>Your accounts before borrowing the money:</para>

    <screenshot id="loans_mortgage">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_mortgage1.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>Accounts Before Receiving Loan</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption><para>Accounts Before Receiving Loan</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The purchase of the house is recorded with a split transaction in
    the Asset:House account, with $50k coming from the bank (IE: your down
    payment), and $100k coming from the Mortgage. You can place the $3k
    closing costs in the same split, and we increase the house loan to $103k
    to include the closing costs as well.</para>

    <para><table>
        <title>Buying a House Split Transaction</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Account</entry>

              <entry>Increase</entry>

              <entry>Decrease</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Assets:Fixed Assets:House</entry>

              <entry>$150,000</entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Assets:Current Assets:Bank</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>$50,000</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Liabilities:Loans:Mortgage Loan</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>$103,000</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Expenses:Mortgage Adm Fees</entry>

              <entry>$3000</entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>

    <para>The split will look like this in the Assets:Fixed Assets:House
    Account:</para>

    <screenshot id="loans_mortgage2.png">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_mortgage2.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>Mortgage Split Transaction</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption><para>Mortgage Split Transaction</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>Which will give a Chart of Accounts like this:</para>

    <screenshot id="loans_mortgage3">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_mortgage3.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>Mortgage Accounts</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption><para>Mortgage Account</para></caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_personalLoanToSomeOne">
    <title>A Personal Loan to a friend (How-To)</title>

    <para>It is not always you are borrowing money from the bank, sometimes
    you borrow money from your family, or perhaps even lend money to a friend.
    This How-To chapter will describe one way to handle lending money to a
    friend.</para>

    <para>We are basing this How-To on the following generic account
    structure.</para>

    <literallayout>
-Asset
   -Bank 
        -Bank Account
   -Money owed to you
        -Person
-Income
   -Interest Income
        -Person
  </literallayout>

    <para>This example will show how to track a personal loan of 2,000 USD
    (default currency) to your friend Peter</para>

    <sect2 id="loans_personalLoanToSomeOne_loan">
      <title>Loan Specifications</title>

      <para>Peter wants to borrow $2,000 dollars from you and plans to pay you
      back montly for the next 18 months. Since he is your friend, (but not
      that close) you both agree on a yearly interest rate of 5%</para>

      <para>In summary we have the below details. Peter's loan details:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Pinciple Amount - $2,000</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Term - 18 months with 12 payments per year</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Annual Percentage Rate: 5%</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Monthly Payment : ??</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>So how do you caculate the Montly Payment?</para>

      <para>You have a number of different options, like paper and pen, 
      Linux Calculator, Open Office's Calc module, but the easiest is to use
      GnuCash Financial Calculater. This gives you that the Monthly Payment
      should be 115.56$.</para>

      <para>But you need to know how much of this is Interest and how much is
      Principal to be able to do a proper bookkeeping. For this you need a 
      more powerful tool, something like the Calc module in Open Office, and
      in particular the PMT function.</para>

      <screenshot id="loans_OpenOfficePrivateLoanDetails">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_PrivateLoanCalculation.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Calculation of Private Loan details</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption><para>Detailed view over the private loan to
          Peter</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="loans_personalLoanToSomeOne_accounts">
      <title>Accounts for the loan</title>

      <para>Let's start with the following acccounts (all accounts have the
      same currency, in this case USD)</para>

      <literallayout>
Assets:Bank:USD
Assets:Money owed to you:Peter
Income:Interest Income:Peter
Equity:Opening Balances:USD
  </literallayout>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="loans_personalLoanToSomeOne_InitialSetup">
      <title>Lending the money</title>

      <para>When you have lended money to your friend, you have in fact moved
      money from an Asset account (like Bank, Checking or similar) to your
      Asset account "Money owed to you". To record this you enter the
      following transaction into the Assets:Money owed to you:Friend
      account.</para>

      <para><table>
          <title>Personal loan to a Friend</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Account</entry>

                <entry>Increase</entry>

                <entry>Decrease</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Assets:Money owed to you:Friend</entry>

                <entry>$2,000</entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Assets:Bank:USD</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>$2,000</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>

      <screenshot id="loans_PrivateLoanInitial">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_PrivateLoanInitial.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Lended money</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption><para>Chart of Accounts after lending
          money</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="loans_personalLoanToSomeOne_FirstPayment">
      <title>Receiving first payment</title>

      <para>When the first payment ($115.56) is received, you will need to
      determine how much is for the principal loan, and how much is for the
      loan interest.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Outstanding loan amount this period = $2,000</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Payment per month = $115.56</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Payment breakdown</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>5%/12 * $2,000 = $8.33 Interest</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>$115.56 - $8.33 = $107.23 Principle</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This can be translated to the following GnuCash entry</para>

      <screenshot id="loans_PrivateLoanFirstPayment">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_PrivateLoanFirstPayment.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>First payment</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption><para>Detailed view over first payment</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The balance on Peters loan is now $2,000 - $107.23 =
      $1,892.77</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="loans_personalLoanToSomeOne_SecondPayment">
      <title>Receiving second payment</title>

      <para>When the second payment ($115.56) is received, you will again need
      to determine how much is for the principal loan, and how much is for the
      loan interest.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Outstanding loan amount this period = $1,892.77</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Payment per month = $115.56</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Payment breakdown</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>5%/12 * $1,892.77 = $7.89 Interest</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>$115.56 - $7.89 = $107.67 Principle</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This can be translated to the following GnuCash entry</para>

      <screenshot id="loans_PrivateLoanSecondPayment">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_PrivateLoanSecondPayment.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Second payment</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption><para>Detailed view over the second
          payment</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The balance on Peters loan is now $1,892.77 - $107.67 =
      $1,785.10</para>

      <para>The Chart of accounts looks now like this</para>

      <screenshot id="loans_PrivateLoanSecondPaymentAccounts">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/loans_PrivateLoanSecondPaymentAccounts.png"
                       format="PNG" srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Chart of Accounts after second payment</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption><para>Chart of Accounts after second
          payment</para></caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>As you can see, the interest varies for every month, as well as
      the principal amount. So for every payment you receive you need to
      calculate the proper amounts for your various split entries.</para>

      <para>The interest amount will be less and less for every payment (since
      it is calculated on a smaller loan amount all the time), until the last
      payment where it is more or less 0. Please review the Figure of Detailed
      view over private loan to Peter for more details</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_CarLoan">
    <title>Automobile Loan (How-To)</title>

    <para>The Automobile Loan, or in common terms, Car Loan, is treated more
    or less exactly as the House loan. The only difference is different
    accounts, and different interest rates.</para>

    <para><literallayout>Basic Car Loan Account Structure

-Asset
    -Current Assets
        -Savings Account
    -Fixed Assets
        -Car
-Liability
   -Loans
       -Car Loan
-Expenses
   -Interest
       -Car Loan Interest
   -Car Loan Adm Fees</literallayout></para>

    <para>For more information, please check <xref
    linkend="loans_mortgage1" /></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_Reconciling">
    <title>Reconciling with the Loan Statements (How-To)</title>

    <para>Reconciling a loan statement is no different from reconciling a bank
    or credit card statement.</para>

    <para>During the period you should have recorded all the various loan
    related transactions, and every one of them are touching the
    <guilabel>Libility:Loans:&lt;Loan&gt;</guilabel> account. For instance,
    paying of a bit of the loan, decreases your <emphasis>Bank
    Account,</emphasis> and increases the <emphasis>Loan account</emphasis>,
    <emphasis>Loan Interest</emphasis> as well as perhaps <emphasis>Loan
    administration fee</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>With the loan statement in your hands, open the Loan account, start
    the reconcile druid, and tick of all the various transaction you have
    recorded. When you have finished, the reconciling difference should be 0,
    and if it is not, then you will have to go through the account and compare
    it with the loan statement to find the difference. When you have reached a
    0 in difference, then your loan account is reconciled and you can finish
    the Reconcile druid.</para>

    <para>For more information on how to Reconcile, please check <xref
    linkend="txns-reconcile1" /></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Selling a house or a car (How-To)</title>

    <para>When you will record the selling of your house in GnuCash you have 
    some different options. Here we will go through two of them, one in which 
    you only recorded the purchase amount, and now the selling amount. The other
    where you have followed the ups and downs on the property market and registered
    various Unrealized gains over the time.</para>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Simple Transaction</title>

      <para>In this way you only record the proper sale amount.</para>

      <para>Let's work through two samples of selling a house, one with a
      profit, and one with a loss. If you want to sell a car instead, just
      substitute the house accounts with a car account.</para>

      <para><literallayout>
-Assets
  -Fixed Assets
    -House
  -Current Assets
    -Saving
-Income
  -Capital Gains Long
    -House
    </literallayout></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You bought a house for $300,000 once upon a time, and now managed
          to sell it for $600,000. How do you record this?</para>

          <para>To record this you need to increase our bank account with the
          $600k, and decrease some other accounts with $600k. The house
          account only contains $300k which is what you bought it for, so you
          move this amount to your bank account. That means you are lacking
          #300k. This amount you fetch from the Income:Captial Gains Long:House
          account. The split transaction you enter into your
          <emphasis>bank</emphasis> account (<guilabel>Assets:Fixed
          Assets:Saving</guilabel>) should look like this.</para>

          <para><table>
              <title>Selling an asset (house) with a profit</title>

              <tgroup cols="3">
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Account</entry>

                    <entry>Increase</entry>

                    <entry>Decrease</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Current Assets:Saving</entry>

                    <entry>$600,000</entry>

                    <entry></entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Fixed Assets:House</entry>

                    <entry></entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Income:Capital Gains Long:House</entry>

                    <entry></entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You bought a house for $300,000 once upon a time, but due to a
          newly created airport, could only sell it for $230,000. How do you
          record this?</para>

          <para>To record this you need to increase your bank account with the
          $230k, and decrease some other accounts with $230k. The house
          account contains $300k which is more than what you sold it for. So
          let's move $230k of it to your bank account. After this you have $70k
          remaining in your house account which needs to be removed. You move it
          to our Income:Capital Gains Long:House account, which will indicate
          a loss. The split transaction you enter into your
          <emphasis>house</emphasis> account (<guilabel>Assets:Fixed
          Assets:House</guilabel>) should look like this.</para>

          <para><table>
              <title>Selling an asset (house) with a loss</title>

              <tgroup cols="3">
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Account</entry>

                    <entry>Increase</entry>

                    <entry>Decrease</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Fixed Assets:House</entry>

                    <entry></entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Current Assets:Saving</entry>

                    <entry>$230,000</entry>

                    <entry></entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Income:Capital Gains Long:House</entry>

                    <entry>$70,000</entry>

                    <entry></entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>A More Complex Transaction</title>

      <para>In this example we will touch a little on some more complicated 
      accounting principles. For more details on this subject please check
      <xref linkend="chapter_capgain"></xref></para>

      <para>Here we will only touch on the case when you have accurately estimated 
      the current value of your house. For the other cases (over-, and
      under-estimated), please check <xref linkend="chapter_capgain"></xref>.</para>

      <para><literallayout>
-Assets
    -Fixed Assets
        -House
            -Cost
            -Unrealized Gain
    -Current Assets
        -Saving
-Income
    -Realized Gain
        -House
    -Unrealized Gain
        -House
    </literallayout></para>

          <para>You bought a house for $300,000 once upon a time, and over
          the years kept a close look on the market and updated your
          records with the estimated current value of your house. At the time
          you want to sell it, you have determined that the current market
          value is $600,000. </para>
          
          <para>The difference between $600,000 (estimated market value), and 
          $300,000 (purchase value) is the current Unrealized Gain value. Therefore
          you have a total of $300,000 in your 
          <guilabel>Assets:Fixed Assets:House:Unrealized Gain</guilabel> account</para>
          
          <para>How do you record this sell transaction?</para>

          <para>To record this you need to increase your bank account with the
          $600k, and decrease some other accounts with $600k.
          You must first change from unrealized gain to realized gain 
          for your Income accounts.
          Lastly you need to transfer the full amounts from the "Assets:Fixed Assets:House"
          sub-accounts.</para>
          
          <para>The transaction you enter into your 
          <guilabel>Income:Realized Gain:House</guilabel> 
          account should look like this.</para>

          <para><table>
              <title>Selling an asset (house) with a profit</title>

              <tgroup cols="3">
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Account</entry>

                    <entry>Increase</entry>

                    <entry>Decrease</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Income:Realized Gain:House</entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>

                    <entry></entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Income:Unrealized Gain:House</entry>

                    <entry></entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>
                  </row>

                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></para>
            
          <para>The transaction you enter into your 
          <guilabel>Assets:Current Assets:Saving</guilabel> account 
          should look like this.</para>

          <para><table>
              <title>Selling an asset (house) with a profit 2</title>

              <tgroup cols="3">
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Account</entry>

                    <entry>Increase</entry>

                    <entry>Decrease</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Current Assets:Saving</entry>

                    <entry>$600,000</entry>

                    <entry></entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Fixed Assets:House:Cost</entry>

                    <entry></entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>
                  </row>
                  
                  <row>
                    <entry>Assets:Fixed Assets:House:Unrealized Gain</entry>

                    <entry></entry>

                    <entry>$300,000</entry>
                  </row>

                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></para>
            <para>After having recorded these transactions you see that your House 
            Asset have a value of 0, your Savings account have increased with $600,000, 
            and lastly, the Income:Realized Gain have increased to $300,000.</para>

    </sect2>

    
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="loans_missing1">
    <title>Missing Loan Documentation</title>

    <literallayout>
 -Entering a Payment Schedule
     -Monthly Payments (How-To)
     ---See the Mortgage druid
     ----ARM 10/1 means 10 year fixed interest rate, then changes every year
     ----ARM 10/3 means 10 year fixed interest rate, then changes every third year
     -Final Payment (How-To)
     ---Same as a normal payment, but you get the figures from the bank
     ---How to fix 10 amortization and then a final bulk payment setup?

 -Putting It All Together
 </literallayout>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
