<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.0
  Last modified: July 9th 2006
  Maintainers:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Author:
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
  	Updated	Bengt Thuree <bengt@thuree.com>
  Originally written by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="chapter_oview">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <sect1 id="oview-intro1">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>GnuCash is the personal finance software package made for you. It is
    versatile enough to keep track of all your financial information, from the
    simple to the very complex. It is one of the few financial software
    packages that supports global currencies, and it is the only open-source
    program of its kind. Best of all, GnuCash is easy to learn and use!</para>

    <para>So, what can GnuCash do for you? It can keep track of your personal
    finances in as much detail as you prefer. If you are just starting out,
    use GnuCash to keep track of your checkbook. You may then decide to track
    cash as well as credit card purchases to better determine where your money
    is being spent. When you start investing, you can use GnuCash to help
    monitor your portfolio. Buying a vehicle or a home? GnuCash will help you
    plan the investment and track loan payments. If your financial records
    span the globe, GnuCash provides all the multiple-currency support you
    need.</para>

    <screenshot id="oview-intro">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/oview_intro.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Bengt Thuree" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>GnuCash Chart of Accounts - Teaser</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>This image shows a Chart of Accounts with multiple currencies and investments.</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>While GnuCash is well suited for personal finances, it is also
    powerful enough for business use. There are many business features, from
    integrated accounts receivable and payable systems, to tax table
    construction. You will find these and the many other business features
    surprisingly powerful and easy to use.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview-features1">
    <title>Features</title>

    <sect2 id="oview-featureseasy2">
      <title>Easy to Use</title>

      <para>Within a matter of minutes you will be able to enter your personal
      finance information and generate color graphs that represent your
      financial status. If you can use the register in the back of your
      checkbook - you can use GnuCash! Type directly into the register, tab
      between fields, and use quick-fill to automatically complete
      transactions. The interface is customizable from within the application
      itself.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Easy to Use Menus</emphasis>: GnuCash menus conform
          with the GNOME Human Interface Guidelines. This means that they are
          simple and similar in appearance to many other GNOME
          applications.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Documentation</emphasis>: GnuCash has built in Help
          and extensive User Guide documentation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Import Methods</emphasis>: GnuCash supports many
          ways to input transactions besides manual entry. If you can access
          your bank accounts on-line, this is especially useful, as most banks
          and credit card companies support one of the following import
          methods. You will spend less time entering data and more time
          analyzing results.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>Quicken Import File (QIF)</emphasis>: Import
              Quicken QIF style files, a popular file format with many
              commercial personal finance software packages.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>Open Financial Exchange (OFX)</emphasis>:
              GnuCash is the first free software application to support the
              Open Financial Exchange protocol. Many financial institutions
              are moving towards this format.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>Home Banking Computer Interface
              (HBCI)</emphasis>: GnuCash is the first free software
              application to support the German Home Banking Computer
              Interface protocol. This protocol includes statement download,
              initiates bank transfers, and makes direct debits
              possible.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Reports</emphasis>: GnuCash comes with over 30
          prebuilt reports, including Account Summary, Income, Expenses,
          Transaction Report, Balance Sheet, Profit&amp;Loss, Portfolio
          Valuation, and many others. Reports support graphical views of the
          data, including pie charts, bar charts, and scatter plots. The
          reports can be exported to HTML files, and are easily
          customized.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scheduled Transactions</emphasis>: GnuCash now has
          the ability to automatically create and enter transactions, or
          remind you when these transactions are due, giving you the choice of
          entering, postponing or removing the automated transaction.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Mortgage and Loan Repayment Druid</emphasis>: Used
          to set up a variable payment loan scheduled transaction.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Easy Account Reconciliation</emphasis>: Integrated
          reconciliation makes reconciling your GnuCash accounts with
          statements simple and effective.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Multi-platform Compatibility</emphasis>: GnuCash is
          supported on a variety of platforms and operating systems. The list
          of fully supported operating systems (and platforms) for GnuCash
          v2.0.x is: GNU/Linux (x86, Sparc, PPC), FreeBSD (x86), OpenBSD
          (x86), Solaris (Sparc), and MacOS X (PPC). Previous versions of
          GnuCash have been known to work with, SGI IRIX (MIPS), IBM AIX 4.1.5
          (RS/6000), Unixware 7 (Intel), and SCO OpenServer 5.0.4 (Intel), but
          their current status is unknown.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="oview-featuresinvest2">
      <title>Tracks Your Investments</title>

      <para>GnuCash has a number of investment features. From simple
      certificates of deposit, to publicly traded stocks, GnuCash will track
      all your investments.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Stock/Mutual Fund Portfolios</emphasis>: Track
          stocks individually (one per account) or in a portfolio of accounts
          (a group of accounts that can be displayed together).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>On-line Stock and Mutual Fund Quotes</emphasis>:
          With GnuCash, you no longer need look up your stock values one at a
          time. The process can be automated, to always present you with the
          latest value of your stocks.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="oview-featuresintl2">
      <title>International Support</title>

      <para>GnuCash is truly an application that works with and understands
      users from all around the world. There are many built-in features to
      facilitate interaction with the international world we live in
      today.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Native Languages</emphasis>: GnuCash has been fully
          translated into 12 languages: Chinese, Czech, Dutch, English,
          French, German, Italian, Portuguese, Russian, Slovak, Spanish and
          Swedish. More than 13 other languages are partially
          supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Multiple Currencies and Currency Trading</emphasis>:
          Multiple currencies are supported and can be bought and sold
          (traded). Currency movements between accounts are fully balanced
          when double-entry is enabled.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>International Date Handling</emphasis>: GnuCash
          understands that different countries display the date differently.
          You are able to work with the date format you are accustomed
          to.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>On-line exchange rates</emphasis>:
          With GnuCash, you no longer need look up your exchange rates one at a
          time. The process can be automated, to always present you with the
          account values converted to your preferred currency using the latest 
          exchange rates.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="oview-featuresbus2">
      <title>Business Support</title>

      <para>GnuCash has many features to support the needs of the business
      accounting community.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Accounts Receivable/Payable</emphasis>: GnuCash has
          an integrated Accounts Receivable and Accounts Payable system. You
          can track Customers, Vendors, Invoicing and Bill Payment, and use
          different Tax and Billing Terms in a small business.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Depreciation</emphasis>: GnuCash can track
          depreciation of capital assets.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Reports</emphasis>: GnuCash offers a wide variety of
          ready-to-use business reports.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="oview-featuresaccounting2">
      <title>Accounting Features</title>

      <para>For those knowledgeable in accounting, here is a list of GnuCash's
      accounting features.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Double Entry</emphasis>: Every transaction must
          debit one account and credit others by an equal amount. This ensures
          the "books balance" - that the difference between income and expense
          exactly equals the sum of all bank, cash, stock and other
          assets.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Split Transactions</emphasis>: A single transaction
          can be split into several pieces to record taxes, fees, and other
          compound entries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Chart of Accounts</emphasis>: A master account can
          have a hierarchy of detail accounts underneath it. This allows
          similar account types such as Cash, Bank, or Stock to be grouped
          into a master account such as <quote>Assets</quote>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>General Ledger</emphasis>: One register window can
          display multiple accounts at the same time. This eases the trouble
          of tracking down typing/entry errors. It also provides a convenient
          way of viewing a portfolio of many stocks, by showing all
          transactions in that portfolio.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Income/Expense Account Types
          (Categories)</emphasis>: These categorize your cash flow and, when
          used properly with the double-entry feature, will provide an
          accurate Profit&amp;Loss statement.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="oview-featuresnew2">
      <title>What's New in v2.0</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Gnome 2.0 (Gtk2)</emphasis></para>

            <para>GnuCash is now using the latest tool-kits from gtk, and
            follows the normal Gnome2 HIG standards.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>UTF-8 support</emphasis></para>

            <para>GnuCash now stores and reads each country's special
            character sets by using UTF-8.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Budget</emphasis></para>

            <para>GnuCash now comes with a budget feature that can help you
            keep your expenses under control.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Import of MT940 files</emphasis></para>

            <para>Data files with transactions in MT940 format (as can be
            downloaded from some banks) can now be imported into
            GnuCash.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Bug fixes</emphasis></para>

            <para>GnuCash is now more stable and secure than ever before due
            to the long testing phase before we reached 2.0, as well as using
            more stable and mature libraries (gtk2 for instance). Numerous
            corrections has been made in every part of GnuCash, and too many
            for us to highlight any special area.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview-about1">
    <title>About this Book</title>

    <para>This manual's goal is to save you time. It will get you started
    using GnuCash as quickly as possible.</para>

    <para>Each chapter follows a simple format. A chapter begins with a
    <quote>Concepts</quote> discussion which introduces general themes and
    terminology, addressed and used within that chapter. <quote>How-To</quote>
    sections, which address specific procedures follow. Finally, a
    <quote>Putting It All Together</quote> section ends the chapter by giving
    detailed, concrete examples.</para>

    <para>Beginning users will find the <quote>Concepts</quote> sections very
    helpful. They provide a reference for good ways to track your finances,
    and serve as a general introduction to financial background and
    terminology. Experienced users can flip to the <quote>How-To</quote>
    sections to quickly scan procedures. These sections provide to-the-point
    steps for accomplishing specific tasks. The <quote>Putting It All
    Together</quote> sections present real-world examples in the form of a
    tutorial. Beginning with creation of a file in <xref linkend="chapter_basics"></xref>, 
    each successive chapter builds on the previous chapter's tutorial.</para>

    <para>This manual is organized into 3 main parts: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Getting Started</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Managing Your Personal Finances</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Managing Your Business Finances</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para><emphasis>Getting Started</emphasis> provides you with the most
    basic information needed to begin using GnuCash. Use this part as a
    quick-start guide. Its chapters will get you up and running: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
           <para><xref linkend="chapter_oview"></xref></para>
       </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_basics"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_accts"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_txns"></xref></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para><emphasis>Managing Your Personal Finances</emphasis> addresses
    common applications and features of GnuCash in greater detail. You will
    see more specific cases, based on frequently asked questions about
    applying GnuCash to everyday situations. Here are the applications and
    features covered in this part: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_cbook"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_cc"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_loans"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_invest"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_capgain"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_currency"></xref></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para><emphasis>Managing Your Business Finances</emphasis> discusses the
    use of GnuCash in business accounting: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_dep"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_bus_ar"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_bus_ap"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="chapter_bus_pay"></xref></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>This manual also has an appendix, which contains extra information
    you might want to know:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="appendixa"></xref> - Guide for former <trademark
        class="registered">Quicken</trademark>, MS Money or other QIF
        users</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
          <para><xref linkend="appendixb"></xref></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="appendixc"></xref></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="appendixd"></xref></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="fdl"></xref></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Last, but not least, a glossary and index help you quickly locate
    topics.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview-reasons1">
    <title>Top Ten Reasons to Use GnuCash</title>

    <para>We've already discussed some of the general advantages of using
    GnuCash. Here are some specific features offered by GnuCash that may not
    exist in other programs.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Simple user interface</para>

        <para>GnuCash is as easy to use as a checkbook register. It's simpler
        than a paper register, because auto-completion and other entry
        shortcuts not only do work for you, but reduce data entry
        errors.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Easy import</para>

        <para>GnuCash allows you to import data from on-line bank statements
        and software packages using QIF (<trademark
        class="registered">Quicken</trademark> Interchange Format), OFX and
        HBCI files. An easy-to-use <quote>druid</quote> walks you through
        reviewing resulting changes and actually importing them into
        GnuCash.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Statement reconciliation</para>

        <para>Reconcile monthly statements quickly by entering the statement
        ending balance and checking off transactions. GnuCash helps you catch
        any discrepancies between your data and statements you receive.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Investment tracking</para>

        <para>GnuCash offers a host of ways to track your investment
        portfolio. Special investment accounts simplify data entry, and
        on-line tools allow you to update prices of your holdings as the
        markets change. Reports complete the picture, allowing you to analyze
        your investment decisions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Multiple currency support</para>

        <para>GnuCash allows you to track multiple currencies. If you have
        bank accounts, investments or other financial data in different
        currencies, use GnuCash to monitor them.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Customized reports and graphs</para>

        <para>Reports and graphs give you valuable information for filing
        taxes, budgeting, or simply figuring out where your money goes.
        GnuCash offers a variety of easy-to-use reports and graphs to help
        analyze your financial position. It gives you the freedom to customize
        your own reports to suit your unique needs.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Double entry</para>

        <para>To provide complete records, GnuCash uses the double entry
        method of bookkeeping. Double entry simply means that money doesn't
        just appear or disappear - an equal amount must come from one location
        and go to another location. By tracking the transaction in both
        locations, GnuCash will give you detailed reports from the perspective
        of either account.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sources of help</para>

        <para>A Tip of the Day dialog gives helpful tips to new users about
        GnuCash features. Within the program, a searchable Help menu guides
        you to information or connects to the GnuCash web page for further
        assistance. GnuCash also has strong, helpful developer and user
        communities who provide help through mailing lists as well as through 
        the IRC channel.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Shortcuts</para>

        <para>GnuCash offers many shortcuts to help you enter data. Type the
        first few characters of a common entry and GnuCash will automatically
        fill in the rest! You can also use copy, paste and duplicate functions
        to save typing time. Keyboard shortcuts let you quickly choose a menu
        option or to enter numerical data. Many numeric entry fields can act
        as a calculator: enter "92.18+33.26" and watch GnuCash input the
        corresponding sum for you!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Open source</para>

        <para>GnuCash doesn't hide its methods. If you wonder how GnuCash
        computed a number, you can find it out. In addition, you can set
        preferences that tell GnuCash how much information to display to you.
        There is no <quote>secret code</quote> used in GnuCash - it continues
        to be an open-source program.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>These are only a few of the advantages you'll discover when you
    start using GnuCash to track your financial information. Now get ready to
    enjoy the benefits of GnuCash for yourself!</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview-install1">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>Installation of GnuCash can be simple, as most modern linux
    distributions come with GnuCash precompiled and ready to go. In fact, most
    likely, GnuCash is already installed. If you do not have GnuCash
    installed, the simplest method for installing it is to insert the
    installation CD that came with your distribution and follow the
    instructions.</para>

    <para>The <ulink url="http://www.gnucash.org/"><citetitle>GnuCash home
    page</citetitle></ulink> contains detailed instructions on how to install
    GnuCash in the event your current distribution does not include it or you
    want to install a different version. You can also read the README file in
    the source code.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
