<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.0
  Last modified: 2014-09-26 (fell)
  Maintainers:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Author:
        David Cousens <davidcousens@bigpond.com>
        rewritten with extractions from
        from ch_accnts.xml and ch_txns.xml
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
  	Updated	Bengt Thuree <bengt@thuree.com>
  Originally written by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="chapter_reconciliation">
  <title>Account Reconciliation</title>
  <para><emphasis>Reconciliation</emphasis> is a process which ensures that the information you have entered into an account in 
    <application>&app;</application> agrees with an external record held by and supplied by another entity. Most often this will 
    be a bank or lending institution but it may also be a vendor who supplies you with a statement of your account position with them. 
    In principle any account for which an external statement is available or can be requested can be reconciled, however in practice
    it will generally be:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitmem> asset accounts, particularly bank accounts, and liability accounts;</listitem>,
     <listitem>credit card and loan accounts</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     that you will reconcile regularly. This chapter will describe the principles behind reconciliation, the process as
    implemented in <application>&app;</application>. Specific examples of reconciliation of bank (check), credit card and loan accounts 
    are available in sections of the relevant chapters.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="Reconciliation_Concepts">
    <title>Basic Concepts</title>
    <para>A <emphasis>statement</emphasis> is usually supplied periodically by most institutions which hold our money for us or lend money to us. A
    statement covers a specified period in time is usually defined by a number of parameters:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Opening Date</emphasis> - The first date in the period for which transactions are recorded in the statement.</para></listitem>
      <listtem><para><emphasis>Closing Date</emphasis> - The last date in the period for which transactions are recorded in the statement.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Opening Balance</emphasis> - The balance of the account at the Opening Date before any of the transactions recorded in the 
      statement period have been applied.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Closing Balance</emphasis> - The balance of the account at the closing date after all transactions recorded in the statement 
      period have been applied.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Transaction List</emphasis> - A sequential list of transactions as recorded by the entity/institution between the opening
      and closing dates.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Transactions will be recorded in the statement at a date-time which is relevant to the institution (clearance of the transaction between
     banks for example). In some cases that date-time may not be in the same time-zone that you are. You may have recorded the transaction at a different 
     date-time which is relevant to your perspective on the transaction.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="Reconciliation_Process">
    <title>Reconcil;iation Process</title>
    <para>The process of reconciliation is one of matching the Opening Balance and Closing Balance and transaction details in your 
    <application>&app;</application> record for the account to those details in the external statement supplied by your bank or other institution. It is 
    implicit in this process that you have already carried out the reconciliation process on your <application>&app;</application> account records to previous 
    statements for all transactions before the Opening Date of the statement you are currently about to reconcile.
    </para>
    <para>The <application>&app;</application> reconciliation process is initiated while the register for the account you wish to reconcile either 
    by: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>Clicking on the <guilabel>Action</guilabel>-><guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> menu item while the account register you wish to edit is displayed; or</listitem>
    <listitemn>Clicking on the <guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> button in the toolbar while the account register you wish to edit is displayed; or</listitem>
    <listitem>Right click on the account you wish to reconcile in the <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab of the main window and select <guilabel>Reconcile</guilabel> from the popup menu.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This will open the Reconcile Information window <!-- insert link to window description in the help file  and or screenshot-->.</para> 
    <sect2 id="Rec_Information">
      <title>In the Reconciliation Information Window</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Set the <guilabel>Statement Date</guilabel> in the window to the Closing Date displayed on the statement you are reconciling to.</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>Check that the Starting Balance in the window is equal to the Opening Balance on your statement. If it is not see 
        <!-- link to fiing previous reconciliations -->.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Enter the Closing Balance from the statement into the <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> text box.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Check the <guilabel>Include subaccounts</guilabel> checkbox if the account you are reconciling has subaccounts you wish to reconcile.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>If you are reconciling a Credit Card account your statement may include an interest payment for the period which will not appear in the transactions
        listed in the statement for the period. Use the <guibutton>Enter Interest Payment</guibutton> button to start a dialog for creating a transaction to record 
        the interest charged.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para> Click on the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to open the Reconciliation Window <!-- link to window description in help --> to continue reconciling
        the account or the <guilabel>Cancel</guilabel> to exit the reconciliation process.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Rec_Window">
      <title>In the Reconciliation Window</title>
      <para>The features of the <guilabel>Reconciliation Window</guilabel> are described in detail in <!-- link to help description of the reconciliation 
        Window -->.</para>
      <para> The pane on the left lists transactions which add funds to the account. It will be labelled <guilabel>Funds In</guilabel> if you have not
         selected formal accounting labels in the preferences. (If you did it will be labelled <guilabel>Debits</guilabel> if you are reconciling an Asset 
         type account or <guilabel>Credits</guilabel> if you are reconciling a Liability type account).</para>
      <para>The pane on the right list transactions which tanke funds out of the account. It will be labelled<guilabel>Funds Out</guilabel> if you are not
         using formal accounting labels. (If you are it will be labelled <guilabel>Credits</guilabel> for an Asset type account or <guilabel>Debits</guilabel>
         for a Liability type account.)</para>
      <para>Each listed transaction in both panes has a checkbox to the right of it. <application>&app;</application> will initially select transactions 
      within the period in an attempt to achieve a <guilabel>Reconciled Balance</guilabel> equal to the <emphasis>Closing Balance</emphasis> entered into 
      the previous window from your statement and displayed as the <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> in the small pane at the bottom right of the
       <guilabel>Reconciliation Window</guilabel>.</para>
       <note><para>Transactions do not necessarily appear in the same order in your <application>&app;</application> accounts as they occur in a statement for 
       that account. Dates may differ and transactions which occur on the same day may not be in the order you entered them.</para></note>
     <para>If the displayed <guilabel>Reconciled Balance</guilabel> and the <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> agree and the <guilabel>Difference</guilabel>
      value is 0 and you are happy that the checked transactions match those in your statement, you may click on the <guilabel>Reconcile->Finish</guilabel> menu item or click 
      the <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> button in the toolbar. This will set the transaction reconciliation status for the checked transaction splits to the account you are 
      reconciling to <emphasis>y</emphasis>. The displayed <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> will then be the <guilabel>Starting Balance</guilabel> 
      the next time you perform a reconciliation on this account.</para>
    <para>Some of you will prefer to check the checkboxes as you match transaction to the corresponding transaction in your statement. If this is the case 
      before you start you can uncheck all check boxes in either the right or left pane by using <emphasis>Ctrl-A</emphasis> to select all transactions in 
      the pane and then using the <guibutton>Unreconcile Selection</guibutton> button. You can then check each transaction line in the statement and check the box
      against the matching transaction in the left or right pane as appropriate. Again when you have matched all transactions in your statement to those in your
      account, then procedd as described in the previous paragraph. you can also use the <guibutton>Reconcile Selection</guibutton> buttonto check all the checkboxes
       in either pane after selecting all transactions in the pane with <emphasis>Ctrl-A</emphasis>.
     </para>
     <para> Again when the <guilabel>Reconciled Balance</guilabel> and <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> agree and the <guilabel>Difference</guilabel>
      is 0, you may click on the <guilabel>Reconcile->Finish</guilabel> menu item or click the Finish button in the toolbar to complete the reconciliation.
     </para>
    <sect2 id="Rec_error">
      <title>Unable to Complete Reconciliation</title>
      <para><application>&app;</application> has one very useful feature. The Reconciliation Window is not modal, i.e. it does not have to be closed before 
      you can carry out other operations in <application>&app;</application>. This means that you can leave the Reconciliation Window open and switch back to 
      the register tab to edit or create or delete transactions. The Reconciliation Window is also updated when any such changes are made and saved in the register.
      This facilitates fixing reconciliation errors on the fly without having to exit the Reconciliation Window.
      </para>
      <para>Clicking on the headers of the Funds In and Funds Out panes can allow you to sort by Date, Description or Amount (Reconcile Status is not 
      currently sortable) to assist in identifying the source of a reconcilaition problem.</para>
      <para>Sometimes you will not be able to get the <guilabel>Reconciled Balance</guilabel> and the <guilabel>Ending Balance</guilabel> to agree and 
        <guilabel>Difference</guilabel> will not be zero. In other cases the <guilabel>Starting Balance</guilabel> will be inerror.</para>
      <para>Common causes of this can be:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para> Transactions not recorded or duplicated.</para>
          <para> If the <guilabel>Difference</guilabel> total is negative then transactions which take funds out of 
          the account may not have been entered by you or transactions putting funds into the account may have been duplicated. If the 
          <guilabel>Difference</guilabel> total is positive then transactions which put funds into the account may not have been entered and/or transactions
          taking funds out of the account may be duplicated.
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>Incorrect Date entered for a transaction.</para><para>If the date entered incorrectly is before the start of the period being
           reconciled this will normally cause the Starting Balance not to agree with the Starting Balance of the statement. The transaction will normally 
           appear unchecked in one of the panes before any of the transactions of the current period where sorted in ascending date order. Similarly if the 
           incorrectly entered date is after the end of the current reconciliation period it will appear after any transactions from the current period 
           when sorted in ascending date order.
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>Transaction entered into the wrong account.</para><para>This can be one of the most difficult errors to locate. Accounts which appear
           adjacent to the account you are reconciling in the account selection drop down lists are obvious candidates. Also selecting a Credit Card 
           instead of a Bank Account or vice versa is another possibility. Payments into a Credit Card may be accidentally recorded as an Expense. If you know 
           something about the transaction (Amount, string in the description, memo etc.), the Find Transaction dialog <!-- link to help--> may be useful to
           locate transactions in a wrong account.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>Incorrect amount entered into a transaction</para><para>Usually obvious if other details of the transaction are the same. You need to
          be careful that you have indentified the correct transaction. </para> 
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Rec_tips">
      <title>Reconciliation Tips</title>        
        <tip><para>Exercise caution when altering or deleting transactions while reconciling. If you accidentally delete a transaction you need, you can open
        a backup file in another <application>&app;</application> instance, Use Transaction->Copy and Transaction->Paste to restore the transaction to 
        your main file. Be careful to close the backup file in its instance before closing the main file to ensure <application>&app;</application> 
        opens the correct file next time it is started.</para> </tip>
        <tip><para>Rather than delete transactions, change the split so it goes to the Imbalance Account rather than the account you are reconciling. If you have
         removed it in error, it is easy to restore. If it should have been to another account, you can redirect it there when reconciling that account. If
         you complete all reconciliations fo all accounts for the period and you no longer need it, then you can safely delete it from the Imbalance account.</para>
        </tip>
        <tip><para>If you use Actions->Reset All Warnings you will get a warning before deleting.</para>
        </tip>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
