 <!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 1.7.6
  Last modified: June 13, 2003
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Originally written by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->

 <chapter id="chapter1">
  <title>Overview of GnuCash</title>

  <sect1 id="oview_intro1">
   <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
GnuCash is the personal finance software package made for you. It is versatile enough to keep track of all your financial information, from the simple to the very complex. It is one of the few financial software packages that supports global currencies, and it is the only Linux open-source program of its kind. And best of all, it is easy to use!
    </para>
    <para>
So what can GnuCash do for you? It can keep track of your finances in as much detail as you prefer. If you are just starting out, use GnuCash to keep track of your checkbook. You may then decide to track cash purchases, as well as credit card purchases, so you can better determine where your money is being spent. When you start investing, you can use GnuCash's investing features to help you monitor your portfolio. Buying a vehicle or a home? GnuCash can help you with planning the investment, as well as tracking loan payments. And if your financial records span the globe, GnuCash can provide all the multiple-currency support you need.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview_features1">
   <title>Features</title>

  <sect2 id="oview_featuresall2">
   <title>GnuCash Features List</title>

   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>An easy-to-use interface.</emphasis> If you can use the
    register in the back of your checkbook, you 
    can use GnuCash.  Type directly into the register,
    tab between fields, and use quick-fill to
    automatically complete the transaction.
    The interface is customizable from within the 
    application itself (no editing config files :) )</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Scheduled Transactions</emphasis>: GnuCash now has the ability to 
    automatically create and enter transactions, remind when
    a transaction is due, give a choice of entering a transaction
    or postponing it and remove an automated transaction after a
    certain period.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Mortgage and Loan Repayment Druid</emphasis>: Used to setup a variable
    payment loan scheduled transaction.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Small Business Accounting Features</emphasis>: GnuCash now can be used
    for Customer and Vendor tracking, Invoicing and Bill Payment,
    and using different Tax and Billing	Terms in a small business.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>OFX Import</emphasis>: GnuCash is the first free software application 
    to support the Open Financial Exchange protocol that many 
    banks and financial services are moving to use. The 
    development of OFX and HBCI support has also resulted in
    an improved transaction matching system that more accurately
    picks duplicate transactions.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>HBCI Support</emphasis>: GnuCash is the first free software application
    to support the German Home Banking Computer Interface protocol
    which includes statement download, initiate bank transfers 
    and direct debits.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Quicken File Import</emphasis>: Import Quicken QIF style files.
    QIF files are automatically merged to eliminate 
    duplicate transactions.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Reconcile window</emphasis>  with running reconciled 
    and cleared balances makes reconciliation easy.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Stock/Mutual Fund Portfolios</emphasis>:  Track stocks
    individually (one per account) or in portfolio
    of accounts (a group of accounts that can be 
    displayed together).  </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Get Stock and Mutual Fund quotes</emphasis> from various web sites, 
    update portfolio automatically (more funds being added 
    regularly).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Reports</emphasis>: Display Balance Sheet, Profit&amp;Loss, Portfolio 
    Valuation, Transaction Reports, or account balance tracking,
    or export them as HTML.  You can write your own custom
    report if you know a little Scheme.  Reports can now be performed
    over an accounting period!</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Multiple Currencies and Currency Trading</emphasis>: Multiple 
    currencies are supported and can be bought and
    sold (traded).  Currency movements between accounts
    are fully balanced when double-entry is enabled.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>New Multi-Currency Transaction Handling</emphasis>: GnuCash no longer
    requires separate currency exchange accounts to handle 
    multiple currency transfers.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Chart of Accounts</emphasis>: A master account can have a hierarchy
    of detail accounts underneath it.  This allows similar
    account types (e.g. Cash, Bank, Stock) to be grouped 
    into one master account (e.g. Assets).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Split Transactions</emphasis>: A single transaction can be split
    into several pieces to record taxes, fees, and
    other compound entries.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Double Entry</emphasis>: When enabled, every transaction must 
    debit one account and credit another by an equal amount.
    This ensures that the "books balance": that the 
    difference between income and outflow exactly equals
    the sum of all assets, be they bank, cash, stock or other.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Income/Expense Account Types (Categories)</emphasis>:  
    These serve not only to categorize your cash flow, 
    but when used properly with the double-entry feature,
    these can provide an accurate Profit&amp;Loss statement.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>General Ledger</emphasis>: Multiple accounts can be displayed 
    in one register window at the same time.  This can
    ease the trouble of tracking down typing/entry errors.
    It also provides a convenient way of viewing a
    portfolio of many stocks, by showing all transactions
    in that portfolio.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Written in C</emphasis> with embedded scheme support via Guile.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>File access is locked in a network-safe fashion</emphasis>, preventing
    accidental damage if several users attempt to access the 
    same file, even if the file is NFS-mounted.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Provides a byte-stream format</emphasis>, which allows accounts and
    account groups to be transmitted to other processes
    via pipes or sockets.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>International date handling</emphasis>, many different translations.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>New User Manual and Help</emphasis>: A brand new user help has been 
    written which focuses on how to do tasks in conjunction 
    with a Tutorial and Concepts guide that gives the user 
    background information on using GnuCash.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Redesigned Menu's</emphasis>: The GnuCash menu's have been redesigned
    to conform more with the new GNOME Human Interface Guidelines.</para>
   </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="oview_featuresnew2">
   <title>What's New in v1.8</title>
    <para>
   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Scheduled Transactions</emphasis></para>
<para>GnuCash now has the ability to automatically create and enter transactions, remind when a transaction is due, give a choice of entering a transaction or postponing it and remove an automated transaction after a certain period.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Mortgage and Loan Repayment Druid</emphasis></para>
<para>Used to setup a variable payment loan scheduled transaction.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Small Business Accounting Features</emphasis></para>
<para>GnuCash now can be used for Customer and Vendor tracking, Invoicing and Bill Payment, and using different Tax and Billing Terms in a small business.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>OFX Import</emphasis></para>
<para>GnuCash is the first free software application to support the Open Financial Exchange protocol that many banks and financial services are moving to use. The development of OFX and HBCI support has also resulted in an improved transaction matching system that more accurately picks duplicate transactions.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>HBCI Support</emphasis></para>
<para>GnuCash is the first free software application to support the German Home Banking Computer Interface protocol which includes statement download, initiate bank transfers and direct debits.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>New User Manual and Help</emphasis></para>
<para>A brand new user help has been written which focuses on how to do tasks in conjunction with a Tutorial and Concepts guide that gives the user background information on using GnuCash.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>New Multi-Currency Transaction Handling</emphasis></para>
<para>GnuCash no longer requires separate currency exchange accounts to handle multiple currency transfers.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
<para><emphasis>Redesigned Menu's</emphasis></para>
<para>The GnuCash menu's have been redesigned to conform more with the new GNOME Human Interface Guidelines.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview_about1">
   <title>About this Book</title>
    <para>
The goal of this manual is to save you time and to get you started in GnuCash as quickly as possible. Each chapter follows a simple format, beginning with a <quote>Concepts</quote> discussion to introduce the general themes that the chapter will address, followed by <quote>How-To</quote> sections which address specific procedures and finally, a <quote>Putting It All Together</quote> section at the end of the chapter will give specific examples.
    </para>
    <para>
Beginning users will find the <quote>Concepts</quote> sections helpful, since they provide a reference and ideas for the best ways to track your finances. Experienced users  can flip to the <quote>How-To</quote> sections to quickly scan procedures. These sections provide quick, to-the-point steps for accomplishing specific tasks. The <quote>Putting It All Together</quote> sections present real-world examples in the form of a tutorial, beginning with creation of a file  in Chapter 2. Each successive chapter will build on the previous chapter's tutorial.
    </para>
    <para>
This manual is organized into 3 main parts, <emphasis>Getting Started</emphasis> (chapters 1-4), <emphasis>Managing Your Personal Finances</emphasis> (chapters 5-8), and <emphasis>Managing Your Personal Finances</emphasis> (chapters 9-13).
    </para>
    <para>
The first part, <emphasis>Getting Started</emphasis>, contains 4 chapters that give you the basic information needed to begin to use GnuCash:
    </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 1: Overview of GnuCash
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 2: Basic Structure and Setup
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 3: Organizing Your Accounts
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 4: Entering Transactions
    </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
    <para>
Use this part as a quick-start guide; it will cover everything you need to get up and running in GnuCash.
    </para>
    <para>
The second part, <emphasis>Managing your Personal Finances</emphasis>, addresses common applications and features of GnuCash in greater detail. You will see more specific cases, based on frequently asked questions about applying GnuCash to everyday situations. Here are the applications and features covered in this part:
    </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 5: Checkbook
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 6: Credit Cards
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 7: Investments
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 8: Loans
    </para>
    </listitem>

   </itemizedlist>
     <para>
The last part, <emphasis>Managing Your Business Finances</emphasis>, discusses the use of GnuCash in business accounting.
    </para>
   <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 9: Depreciation and Capital Gains
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 10: Multiple Currencies
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 11: Business: Accounts Receivable
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 12: Business: Accounts Payable
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Chapter 13: Business: Payroll
    </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
     <para>
This manual also has an appendix, which contains extra information you might want to know:
    </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Appendix A: Migration Guide - 
       Guide for former <trademark class="registered">Quicken</trademark>, MS Money or other QIF users
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Appendix B: Frequently Asked Questions
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Appendix C: Contributed Account Trees
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Appendix D: GNU Free Documentation License
    </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
     <para>
Last but not least, a glossary and index help you quickly locate the topics you need.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview_reasons1">
   <title>Top Ten Reasons to Use GnuCash</title>
    <para>
We've already discussed some of the general advantages of using GnuCash. Here are some specific features offered by GnuCash that may not exist in other programs.
    </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Simple user interface
     </para>
     <para>
GnuCash is a Linux financial software package that is as easy to use as a checkbook register. It's even easier to use than a paper register, because features like auto-completion and other entry shortcuts do most of the entry work for you.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Easy import
     </para>
     <para>
GnuCash allows you to import your data from your online bank statement or from another software package using QIF (<trademark class="registered">Quicken</trademark> Interchange Format) files. An easy-to-use <quote>druid</quote> walks you through loading your files, reviewing them for changes, and importing them into GnuCash.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Statement reconciliation
     </para>
     <para>
Reconcile those monthly statements quickly by entering the statement ending balance and checking off transactions. GnuCash helps you catch any discrepancies between your data and the statements you receive.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Investment tracking
     </para>
     <para>
GnuCash offers a host of ways to track your investment portfolio. Special investment accounts simplify your data entry, and online update tools allow you to update the prices of your holdings as the markets change. Reports complete the picture, allowing you to analyze your investment decisions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Multiple currency support
     </para>
     <para>
GnuCash allows you to track multiple currencies. If you have bank accounts, investments or other financial data in different currencies, you can monitor these in GnuCash.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Customized reports and graphs
     </para>
     <para>
Reports and graphs can give you valuable information for filing taxes, budgeting, or simply figuring out where all the money goes. GnuCash offers a variety of easy-to-use reports and graphs to help you analyze your financial position. It also gives you the freedom to customize your own reports to suit your unique needs.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Double entry
     </para>
     <para>
To provide complete records, GnuCash uses the double entry method of bookkeeping. Double entry simply means that money doesn't just appear or disappear - an equal amount must come from one location and go to another location. By entering both locations, you provide information that GnuCash can then use to give you detailed reports of your data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Sources of help
     </para>
     <para>
A Tip of the Day dialog gives helpful tips to new users about GnuCash features. Within the program, a searchable Help menu guides you to the information you need or connects you to the GnuCash web page for further assistance. GnuCash also has strong developer and user communities, and it is easy to get help from these communities through mailing lists.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Shortcuts
     </para>
     <para>
GnuCash offers many shortcuts to help you enter your data. When you type the first few characters of a common entry, it will automatically fill in the rest of the entry. You can also use copy, paste and duplicate functions to save typing time.  Keyboard shortcuts let you quickly choose a menu option or to enter numerical data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
       Open source
     </para>
     <para>
GnuCash doesn't hide its methods from you. If you wonder how GnuCash computed a number, you can easily find it out. In addition, you can set preferences that tell GnuCash how much information to display to you. There is no <quote>secret code</quote> used in GnuCash - it continues to be an open-source program.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
     <para>
These are only a few of the advantages you'll discover when you start using GnuCash to track your financial information. Now get ready to enjoy the benefits of GnuCash for yourself!
     </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="oview_install1">
   <title>Installation</title>
    <para>
Installation of GnuCash can be simple, as most modern linux distributions come with gnucash precompiled and ready to go.  In fact, most likely, GnuCash is already installed.  If you do not have GnuCash installed, the simplest method for installing it is to insert the installation CD that came with your distribution and follow the instructions.
    </para>
    <para>
The <ulink url="http://www.gnucash.org/"><citetitle>GnuCash home page</citetitle></ulink> contains detailed instructions on how to install GnuCash in the event your current distribution does not include it, or if you want to install a different version.  You can also read the README file in the source code.
    </para>

  </sect1>
 </chapter>
