<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 1.6.5
  Last modified: November 24, 2001
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Written by Chris Lyttle
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
 <chapter id="chapter8">
 <title>Depreciation and Capital Gains</title>
 <para>
This chapter will present some of the techniques used to keep track of the changing values of assets, ie: depreciation, unrealized gains, capital gains.   </para>
 <sect1 id="depcapg_concepts1">
 <title>Basic Concepts</title>
 <para>
This chapter will present some of the techniques used to keep track of the changing values of assets, ie: depreciation, unrealized gains, capital gains.
  </para>
 <para>
Certain resellable assets can change value over time, such as stocks, bonds, houses, or cars.  Some assets (eg: a stock) could increase in value, some (eg: a car) could decrease in value.  It is important to be able to track some of these time-dependent asset valuations, this chapter will show you how.
  </para>
 <sect2 id="depcapg_concepts_what2">
 <title>Which Assets to Track</title>
  <para>
Probably everything you own will increase or decrease in value over time. So, the question is for which of these assets should you track this changing value?  The simple answer is that you only need to track this for items which could be sold for cash in the future or which relate to taxation.  
  </para>
  <para>
Consumable and disposable items (eg: food, gas for your car, or printer paper) are obviously not involved.  Thus, even though the new clothes you recently bought will certainly depreciate, you would not want to track this depreciation since you have no intention of reselling the clothes and there is no tax implications to the depreciation on clothing.  So, for this example, the purchase of new clothes should be recorded as a pure expense... you spent the money, and it is gone.
  </para>
  </sect2>
 <sect2 id="depcapg_concepts_dep2">
 <title>Introduction to Depreciation</title>
 <para>
Depreciation is the effect in which the value of an asset decreases with time.  The often used example of an asset to which this is often applied is an automobile.  An automobile holds retained value after the purchase date, but this value decreases with time.  If you hold assets for business purposes, their depreciation can be treated as a deduction for tax purposes.
 </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2 id="depcapg_concepts_app2">
 <title>Introduction to Capital Gains</title>
 <para>
Asset appreciation occurs when something you own increases in value over time.  When you own as asset which has increased in value, the difference between the original purchase price and the new value is known as <emphasis>unrealized gains</emphasis>.  When you sell the asset, the profit you earn is known as <emphasis>realized gains</emphasis> or <emphasis>capital gains</emphasis>.  An example of an asset from which you could have unrealized gains, and eventually capital gains, is stock in a publically traded company.
 </para>
 </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="asset_dep1">
 <title>Depreciation</title>
 <para>
Depreciation is usually recognized as an ongoing (accrued) expense, gradually reducing the value of an asset toward zero. 
 </para>
 <para>
Normally, depreciation is only calculated on assets used for professional or business purposes, because governments don't generally allow you to claim depreciation deductions on personal assets, and it's usually pointless to bother with the procedure if it's not deductible.  The only case where you may want to track depreciation for personal assets would be if you will sell the asset in the future and you want to track your potential personal worth.
 </para>
 <note>
 <para>
Warning: Be aware that different countries can have substantially different tax policies for depreciation; all that this document can really provide is some of the underlying ideas to help you apply your "favorite" tax/depreciation policies.  
 </para>
 </note>

  <sect2 id="asset_dep_valuation2">
 <title>Estimating Valuation</title>
  <para>
A central issue with depreciation is to determine how you will estimate the future value of the asset.  Compared to the often uncertain estimates one has to do where appreciation of assets is concerned, we are on somewhat firmer ground here.  Using sources listed below should make it fairly straight forward to estimate the future value of your depreciating assets.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Tax Codes:</emphasis> For businesses that want to use depreciation for tax purposes, governments tend to set up precise rules as to how you are required to calculate depreciation.  Consult your local tax codes, which should explictly state how to estimate depreciation.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Car Blue Book:</emphasis> For automobiles, it is easy to look up in references such as "Blue Books" estimates of what an automobile should be worth after some period of time in the future.  From this you will be able to develop a model of the depreciation.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="asset_dep_schemes2">
 <title>Depreciation Schemes</title>
  <para>
A <emphasis>depreciation scheme</emphasis> is a mathematical model of how an asset will lose value over time.  For every asset which undergoes depreciation, you will need to decide on a depreciation scheme.  Since depreciation of assets is very often driven by tax policies, the discussion of depreciation will focus in that direction, on some of the more common depreciation calculation schemes.    </para>
  <para>
Once you have an idea of the future value of your asset, you must decide on a depreciation scheme (remember, this may be dictated by your local tax codes).  This section will present 3 of the more popular depreciation schemes: <emphasis>linear</emphasis>, <emphasis>geometric</emphasis>, and <emphasis>sum of digits</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Linear depreciation</emphasis> diminishes the value of an asset by a fixed amount each period until the net value is zero. This is the simplest calculation, as you estimate a useful lifetime, and simply divide the cost equally across that lifetime.  
  </para>
  <para>
Example: You have bought a computer for $1500 and wish to depreciate it over a period of 5 years. Each year the amount of depreciation is $300, leading to the following calculations: 
  </para>
 <para>
 <table>
 <title>Linear Depreciation Scheme Example</title>
 <tgroup cols="3">
 <tbody>
 <row>
 <entry><emphasis>Year</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Depreciation</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Remaining Value</emphasis></entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>0</entry>
 <entry>-</entry>
 <entry>1500</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>1</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 <entry>1200</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>2</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 <entry>900</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>3</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 <entry>600</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>4</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>5</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 <entry>0</entry>
 </row>
 </tbody>
 </tgroup>
 </table>
 </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Geometric depreciation</emphasis> is depreciated by a fixed percentage of the asset value in the previous period.  This is a front-weighted depreciation scheme, more depreciation being applied early in the period.  In this scheme the value of an asset decreases exponentially leaving a value at the end that is larger than zero (i.e.: a resale value).
  </para>
  <para>
Example: We take the same example as above, with an annual depreciation of 30%. 
  </para>
 <para>
 <table>
 <title>Geometric Depreciation Scheme Example</title>
 <tgroup cols="3">
 <tbody>
 <row>
 <entry><emphasis>Year</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Depreciation</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Remaining Value</emphasis></entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>0</entry>
 <entry>-</entry>
 <entry>1500</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>1</entry>
 <entry>450</entry>
 <entry>1050</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>2</entry>
 <entry>315</entry>
 <entry>735</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>3</entry>
 <entry>220.50</entry>
 <entry>514.50</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>4</entry>
 <entry>154.35</entry>
 <entry>360.15</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>5</entry>
 <entry>108.05</entry>
 <entry>252.10</entry>
 </row>
 </tbody>
 </tgroup>
 </table>
 </para>
  <note>
  <para>
Beware: Tax authorities may require (or allow) a larger percentage in the first period. On the other hand, in Canada, this is reversed, as they permit only a half share of "Capital Cost Allowance" in the first year. The result of this approach is that asset value decreases more rapidly at the beginning than at the end which is probably more realistic for most assets than a linear scheme. This is certainly true for automobiles.
  </para>
  </note>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Sum of digits</emphasis> is a front-weighted depreciation scheme similar to the geometric depreciation, except that the value of the asset reaches zero at the end of the period.  This is a front-weighted depreciation scheme, more depreciation being applied early in the period.  This method is most often employed in Anglo/Saxon countries.  Here is an illustration:
  </para>
  <para>
Example: First you divide the asset value by the sum of the years of use, e.g. for our example from above with an asset worth $1500 that is used over a period of five years you get 1500/(1+2+3+4+5)=100. Depreciation and asset value are then calculated as follows: 
  </para>
 <para>
 <table>
 <title>Sum of Digits Depreciation Scheme Example</title>
 <tgroup cols="3">
 <tbody>
 <row>
 <entry><emphasis>Year</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Depreciation</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Remaining Value</emphasis></entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>0</entry>
 <entry>-</entry>
 <entry>1500</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>1</entry>
 <entry>100*5=500</entry>
 <entry>1000</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>2</entry>
 <entry>100*4=400</entry>
 <entry>600</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>3</entry>
 <entry>100*3=300</entry>
 <entry>300</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>4</entry>
 <entry>100*2=200</entry>
 <entry>100</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>5</entry>
 <entry>100*1=100</entry>
 <entry>0</entry>
 </row>
 </tbody>
 </tgroup>
 </table>
 </para>
  </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="asset_dep_accounts2">
 <title>Account Setup</title>
  <para>
As with most accounting practices, there are a number of different ways to setup depreciation accounts.  We will present here a general method which should be flexible enought to handle most situations.  The first account you will need is an <emphasis>Asset Cost</emphasis> account (GnuCash account type "asset"), which is simply a place where you record the original purchase of the asset.  Usually this purchase is accomplished by a transaction from your bank account.
  </para>
  <para>
In order to keep track of the depreciation of the asset, you will need two depreciation accounts.  The first is an <emphasis>Accumulated Depreciation</emphasis> account in which to collect the sum of all of the depreciation amounts, and will contain negative values.  In GnuCash, this is an account type <emphasis>asset</emphasis>.  The Accumulated Depreciation account is balanced by a <emphasis>Depreciation Expense</emphasis> account, in which all periodic depreciation expenses are recorded. In GnuCash, this is an account type <emphasis>expense</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
Below is a generic account heirarchy for tracking the depreciation of 2 assets, ITEM1 and ITEM2.  The "Asset Cost" accounts are balanced by the "Bank" account, the Accumulated Depreciation account is balanced by the Depreciation Expense account.
  </para>
  <literallayout>
-Assets
   -ITEM1 
      -Cost                (Asset Cost account)
      -Depreciation     (Accumulate Depreciation account)
   -ITEM2
      -Cost                (Asset Cost account)
      -Depreciation     (Accumulate Depreciation account)
   -Bank
-Expenses
   -Depreciation        (Depreciation Expense account)
  </literallayout>
  <para>
One of the features of the account heirarchy shown above is that you can readily see some important summary values about your depreciating asset.  The "Assets:ITEM1" account total shows you the current estimated value for item1, the "Assets:ITEM1:Cost" shows you what you originally paid for item1, "Assets:ITEM1:Depreciation" shows you your accrued depreciation for item1, and finally, "Expenses:Depreciation" demostrates the total accrued depreciation of all your assets.
  </para>
  <para>
It is certainly possible to use a different account heirarchy.  One popular account setup is to combine the <emphasis>Asset Cost</emphasis> and <emphasis>Accrued Depreciation</emphasis> asset accounts.  This has the advantage of having fewer accounts cluttering your account heirarchy, but with the disadvantage that to determine some of the summary details mentioned in the paragraph above you will have to open the account register windows.  As with most things, there are many ways to do it, find a way that works best for you.
  </para>
  <para>
The actual input of the depreciation amounts is done by hand every accounting period.  There is no way in GnuCash (as of yet) to perform the depreciation scheme calculations automatically, or to input the values automatically into the appropriate accounts.  However, since an accounting period is typically one year, this really is not much work to do by hand.
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="asset_dep_example2">
 <title>Example</title>
  <para>
Let's go ahead and step through an example.  Imagine you are a photographer and you use a car and an expensive camera for your personal business.  You will want to track the depreciation on these items, because you can probably deduct the depreciation from your business taxes.
  </para>
  <para>
The first step is to build the account heirarchy (as shown in the previous section, replace ITEM1 and ITEM2 with "car" and "camera").  Now, record the purchase of your assets by transferring the money from your bank account to the appropriate <emphasis>Asset Cost</emphasis> accounts for each item (eg: the "Assets:Car:Cost" account for the car).  In this example, you start with $30k in the bank, the car cost $20k and the camera cost $10k and were both purchased on January 1, 2000.
  </para>

	<screenshot id="dep_example1">
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/dep_example1.png" 
	      srccredit="Jon Lapham" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
	        <phrase>Asset Depreciation Example1</phrase>
	    </textobject>
	    <caption>
	       <para>The asset depreciation example main window, before depreciation
	       </para>
	    </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

  <para>
Looking at the tax codes, we realize that we must report depreciation on these items using the "sum of digits" scheme, over a 5 year period.  So, the yearly depreciation amounts for the car come to $6667, $5333, $4000, $2667, $1333 for years 1 to 5 respectively, rounded to the nearest dollar.  The yearly depreciation amounts for the camera are $3333, $2667, $2000, $1333, $667.  Consult the previous section on Depreciation Schemes for the formula for calculating these values.
  </para>
  <para>
For each accounting period (ie: fiscal year) you record the depreciation as an expense in the appropriate <emphasis>Accrued Depreciation</emphasis> account (eg: the "Asset:Car:Depreciation" account for the car). The two windows below show your car's accrued depreciation account and the main window after the third year (ie: three periods) of depreciation using this "sum of digits" scheme.
  </para>

	<screenshot id="asset_dep">
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/asset_dep.png" 
	      srccredit="Jon Lapham" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
	        <phrase>Asset Depreciation Register Window</phrase>
	    </textobject>
	    <caption>
	       <para>The asset depreciation register window
	       </para>
	    </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

	<screenshot id="asset_dep_main">
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/asset_dep_main.png" 
	      srccredit="Jon Lapham" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
	        <phrase>Asset Depreciation Main Window</phrase>
	    </textobject>
	    <caption>
	       <para>The asset depreciation main window
	       </para>
	    </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

  <note>
  <para>
A Word of Caution:  Since depreciation and tax issues are closely related, you may not always be free in choosing your preferred method. Fixing wrong calculations will cost a whole lot more time and trouble than getting the calculations right the first time, so if you plan to depreciate assets, it is wise to make sure of the schemes you will be permitted or required to use. 
  </para>
  </note>

  </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="capgains1">
 <title>Capital Gains</title>
 <para>
As mentioned in the introduction to this chapter, capital gains are the profits received from the same of an asset.  This section will describe how to record capital gains in GnuCash.
 </para>
 <para>
The accounting methods for handling asset appreciation differs somewhat from depreciation because typically you are only concerned with the moment you sell the asset and realize the capital gains.  This is opposed to the continuous nature of tracking depreciation.  Capital gains are an important subject in the world of taxation, because governments tend to be quite interested in taxing capital gains in one manner or another. 
  </para>
  <note>
  <para>
As always, there are exceptions. If you hold a bond that pays all of its interest at maturity, tax authorities often require that you recognize interest each year, and refuse this to be treated as a capital gain.  Consult the appropriate tax codes to determine the preferred treatment for each type of asset you have which may be affected by capital gains taxes.
 </para>
  </note>
  <sect2 id="capgains_valuation2">
 <title>Estimating Valuation</title>
  <para>
Estimating the increasing value of assets is generally not simple, because often it is difficult to know its exact value until the moment it is sold.  
  </para>
  <para>
Securities traded daily on open markets such as stock exchanges are possibly the easiest type of asset to predict the value of, and selling the asset at market prices may be as simple as calling a broker and issuing a Market Order.  On the other hand, estimating the value of a house is more difficult.  Homes are sold less often than stocks, and the sales tend to involve expending considerable effort and negotiations, which means that estimates are likely to be less precise. Similarly, selling a used automobile involves a negotiation process that makes pricing a bit less predictable.
  </para>
  <para>
Values of collectible objects such as jewelry, works of art, baseball cards, and "Beanie Babies" are even harder to estimate. The markets for such objects are much less open than the securities markets and less open than the housing market. Worse still are one-of-a-kind assets. Factories often contain presses and dies customized to build a very specific product that cost tens or hundreds of thousands of dollars; this equipment may be worthless outside of that very specific context. In such cases, several conflicting values might be attached to the asset, none of them unambiguously correct.
  </para>
  <para>
The general rule of thumb in accounting for estimating unrealized gains (or loses) is that you should only revalue assets such as stocks which are readily sellable and for which there are very good estimates of the value.  For all other assets, it is better to simply wait until you sell them, at which time you can exactly determine the capital gains.  Of course, there is no hard rule on this, and in fact different accountants may prefer to do this differently.
  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="capgains_accounts2">
 <title>Account Setup</title>
  <para>
As with most accounting practices, there are a number of different ways to setup capital gains accounts.  We will present here a general method which should be flexible enought to handle most situations.  The first account you will need is an <emphasis>Asset Cost</emphasis> account (GnuCash account type "asset"), which is simply a place where you record the original purchase of the asset.  Usually this purchase is accomplished by a transaction from your bank account.
  </para>
  <para>
In order to keep track of the appreciation of the asset, you will need three accounts.  The first is an <emphasis>Unrealized Gains</emphasis> asset account in which to collect the sum of all of the appreciation amounts.  The Unrealized Gains asset account is balanced by a <emphasis>Unrealized Gains</emphasis> income account, in which all periodic appreciation income is recorded.  Finally, another income account is necessary, called a <emphasis>Realized Gains</emphasis> in which you record the actual capital gains upon selling the asset.
  </para>
  <para>
Below is a generic account heirarchy for tracking the appreciation of 2 assets, ITEM1 and ITEM2.  The "Assets:ITEM1:Cost" accounts are balanced by the "Assets:Bank" account, the "Assets:ITEM?:Unrealized Gains"  accounts are balanced by the "Income:Unrealized Gains" account.  
  </para>
  <literallayout>
-Assets
    -ITEM1 
        -Cost
        -Unrealized Gain
    -ITEM2
        -Cost
        -Unrealized Gain
    -Bank
-Income
    -Unrealized Gains
    -Realized Gains
  </literallayout>

  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="capgains_example2">
 <title>Example: Setup</title>

  <para>
Let's suppose you buy an asset expected to increase in value, say a Degas painting, and want to track this. (The insurance company will care about this, even if nobody else does.)  
  </para>

  <para>
Start with an account heirarchy similar to than shown in the previous section, but replace "ITEM1" with "Degas" and you can remove the "ITEM2" accounts.  We will assume that the Degas painting had an initial value of one hundred thousand dollars.  Begin by giving your self $100000 in the bank and then transferring that from your bank account to your "Asset:Degas" account (the asset purchase transaction).  You should now have a main account window which appears like this:
  </para>
	<screenshot id="asset_dep">
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/asset_app_main.png" 
	      srccredit="Jon Lapham" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
	        <phrase>Asset Appreciation Main Window</phrase>
	    </textobject>
	    <caption>
	       <para>The asset appreciation example main window
	       </para>
	    </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="capgains_example_unrealized2">
 <title>Example: Unrealized Gains</title>

  <para>
A month later, you have reason to suspect that the value of your painting has increased by $10000 (an unrealized gain). In order to record this you transfer $10000 from your Accrued Gains income account to your asset Unrealized Gains account. Your main window will resemble this:
  </para>
	<screenshot id="asset_app_main">
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/asset_app2_main.png" 
	      srccredit="Jon Lapham" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
	    <textobject>
	        <phrase>Asset Appreciation Main Window</phrase>
	    </textobject>
	    <caption>
	       <para>This image shows the asset appreciation main window
	       </para>
	    </caption>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="capgains_selling2">
 <title>Example: Selling (Capital Gains)</title>
  <para>
Let's suppose another month later prices for Degas paintings have gone up some more, in this case about $20000, you estimate. You duly record the $20000 as an unrealized income like above, then decide to sell the painting.
  </para>
  <para>
Three possibilities arise.  You may have <emphasis>accurately estimated</emphasis> the unrealized gain, <emphasis>underestimated</emphasis> the unrealized gain, or <emphasis>overestimated</emphasis> the unrealized gain.    </para>
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Accurate estimation</emphasis> of unrealized gain.
  </para>
  <para>
Your optimistic estimate of the painting's value was correct. First you must record that the profits made are now realized gains, not unrealized gains.  Do this by transferring the income from the "Income:Unrealized Gains" to the "Income:Realized Gains" account.  
  </para>
  <para>
Secondly, you must credit your bank account with the selling price of the painting.  This money comes directly from your "Asset:Degas" subaccounts.  Transfer the full "Asset:Degas:Cost" value into "Asset:Bank", and the full "Asset:Degas:Unrealized Gain" into "Asset:Bank".
  </para>
  <para>
These transactions should now appear as follows:
  </para>
  <para>
 <table>
 <title>Turning an Accrued Gain into a Realized Gain</title>
 <tgroup cols="4">
 <tbody>
 <row>
 <entry><emphasis>Account</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Transfer to</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Transaction Amount</emphasis></entry>
 <entry><emphasis>Account Total</emphasis></entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>Income:Unrealized Gains</entry>
 <entry>Income:Realized Gains</entry>
 <entry>$30000</entry>
 <entry>$0</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>Asset:Degas:Cost</entry>
 <entry>Asset:Bank</entry>
 <entry>$100000</entry>
 <entry>$0</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
 <entry>Asset:Degas:Unrealized Gains</entry>
 <entry>Asset:Bank</entry>
 <entry>$30000</entry>
 <entry>$0</entry>
 </row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
  </table>
  </para>
  <para>
This leaves the "Asset:Bank" account with a total of $130000 and "Income:Realized Gains" with a total of $30000.
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Under estimation</emphasis> of unrealized gain.
  </para>
  <para>
You were over-optimistic about the value of the painting. Instead of the $130000 you thought the painting was worth are only offered $120000. But you still decide to sell, because you value $120000 more than you value the painting. The numbers change a little bit, but not too dramatically. 
  </para>
  <para>
Under construction
  </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
  <para>
<emphasis>Over estimation</emphasis> of unrealized gain.
  </para>
  <para>
You manage to sell your painting for more than you thought in your wildest dreams. The extra value is, again, recorded as a gain, i.e. an income. 
  </para>
  <para>
Under Construction
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="capgains_caution2">
 <title>Caution about Valuation</title>
  <para>
As we see in this example, for non-financial assets, it may be difficult to correctly estimate the ``true'' value of an asset. It is quite easy to count yourself rich based on questionable estimates that do not reflect "money in the bank."
  </para>
  <para>
When dealing with appreciation of assets,
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>
Be careful with your estimation of values. Do not indulge in wishful thinking.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>
Never, ever, count on money you do not have in your bank or as cash. Until you have actually sold your asset and got the money, any numbers on paper (or magnetic patterns on your hard disk) are merely that. If you could realistically convince a banker to lend you money, using the assets as collateral, that is a pretty reasonable evidence that the assets have value, as lenders are professionally suspicious of dubious overestimations of value. Be aware: all too many companies that appear "profitable" on paper go out of business as a result of running out of cash, precisely because "valuable assets" were not the same thing as cash. 
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="capgains_taxation2">
 <title>Taxation of Capital Gains</title>
  <para>
Taxation policies vary considerably between countries, so it is virtually impossible to say anything that will be universally useful. However, it is common for income generated by capital gains to not be subject to taxation until the date that the asset is actually sold, and sometimes not even then. North American home owners usually find that when they sell personal residences, capital gains that occur are exempt from taxation. It appears that other countries treat sale of homes differently, taxing people on such gains. German authorities, for example, tax those gains only if you owned the property for less than ten years.
  </para>
  <para>
Chris Browne has a story from his professional tax preparation days where a family sold a farm, and expected a considerable tax bill that turned out to be virtually nil due to having owned the property before 1971 (wherein lies a critical "Valuation Day" date in Canada) and due to it being a dairy farm, with some really peculiar resulting deductions. The point of this story is that while the presentation here is fairly simple, taxation often gets terribly complicated...
  </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 </chapter>
