<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.6.15
  Last modified: December 6, 2016
  Author:
  		David T. <sunfish62@yahoo.com>
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<glossary id="gnc-gloss">
  <title><application>&app;</application> Glossary</title>
  <para>This is a glossary of common terms used in <application>&app;</application>.
  Some entries here are taken from Wikipedia (<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org"/>).</para>

<!-- ... -->

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_account">
  <glossterm>Account</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>An account keeps track of what you own, owe, spend or receive.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_accountingperiod">
  <glossterm>Accounting Period</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>An accounting period is the period with reference to which accounting 
    books of an entity are prepared. Common accounting
    periods include month, quarter, and year.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_aqbanking">
  <glossterm>AqBanking</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A library which implements the German Home Banking Computer Interface 
    (HBCI) and Electronic Banking Internet Communication Standard (EBICS), OFX 
    Direct Connect and Paypal. It is the successor of openHBCI.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_asset">
  <glossterm>Asset</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>An asset is something you own. Anything tangible or intangible that 
    can be owned or controlled to produce value and that is held to have 
    positive economic value is considered an asset.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_balancesheet">
  <glossterm>Balance Sheet</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A Balance Sheet is a summary of the financial balances of an individual 
    or organization. It summarizes a company's assets, liabilities and ownership 
    equity at a specific point in time.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_book">
  <glossterm>Book</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A book is a record of all transactions for an individual or organization. In
    <application>&app;</application>, each file contains a book.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_capgainloss">
  <glossterm>Capital Gain/Loss</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The difference between the purchase and selling prices of an investment
     at the time the investment is sold. Also known as 
     <emphasis>Realized Gain/Loss</emphasis>. Before an investment 
     is sold, the difference in value is referred to as 
     <emphasis>Unrealized Gain/Loss</emphasis>.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_realgainloss">Realized Gain/Loss</glossseealso>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_unrealgainloss">Unrealized Gain/Loss</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_capstock">
  <glossterm>Capital stock</glossterm>
  <glosssee otherterm="gnc-gl_stock">Stock</glosssee>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_chartofaccounts">
  <glossterm>Chart of Accounts</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A listing of all the accounts available in the data file. The chart 
    of accounts consists of balance sheet accounts (assets, liabilities, 
    stockholders' equity) and income statement accounts (revenues, expenses, 
    gains, losses).</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_commission">
  <glossterm>Commission</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The fee paid to a broker to buy or sell securities.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_commodity">
  <glossterm>Commodity</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A commodity is something of value that is easily tradeable or sellable; 
    for example, currencies, stocks, bonds, grain, copper, and oil are all commodities.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_commonstock">
  <glossterm>Common stock</glossterm>
  <glosssee otherterm="gnc-gl_stock">Stock</glosssee>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_compounding">
  <glossterm>Compounding</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The concept that the reinvested interest can later earn interest of 
    its own (interest on interest). This is often referred to as <emphasis>compound
    interest</emphasis>.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
 
<glossentry id="gnc-gl_costbasis">
  <glossterm>Cost Basis</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Cost basis is the original cost of property, adjusted for various factors. 
    Its primary use is for tax purposes. Factors that affect the cost basis include: 
    stock splits, dividends, depreciation and return of capital distributions. 
    Cost basis is used to determine the <emphasis>capital gain</emphasis>.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_csv">
  <glossterm>CSV</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Stands for Comma Separated Values. CSV files are used to store data 
    in plain text. Each line of the file is a record and each record can be 
    comprised of multiple fields separated by commas. CSV is one import format
    that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_dividends">
  <glossterm>Dividends</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Dividends are cash payments a company makes to shareholders. The 
    amount of this payment is usually determined as some amount of the profits 
    of the company. Not all common stocks give dividends.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_equities">
  <glossterm>Equities</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Equities are investments in which the investor becomes part (or whole) 
    owner in something.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_fints">
  <glossterm>Financial Transaction Services (FinTS)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A banking protocol used by German banks. Developed by the German Central 
    Banking Committee ZKA (Zentraler Kredit-Ausschuss). The standard is used 
    only by German banks. Prior 2002, it was called Home Banking Computer
    Interface (HBCI). FinTS is one import format that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para> 
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_hbci">Home Computer Banking Interface (HBCI)</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
 
<glossentry id="gnc-gl_gsettings">
  <glossterm>GSettings</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Since version 2.5 the tool that stores user configuration data. It 
    uses the native data store of the operating system:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Linux</emphasis></term>
        <listitem><para>DConf since Gnome 3.0 dropped GConf</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Mac OS X</emphasis></term>
        <listitem><para>Defaults. Use the command-line defaults(1) to modify 
        prefs when GnuCash isn't running.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Windows</emphasis></term>
        <listitem><para>Registry.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
 
<glossentry id="gnc-gl_hbci">
  <glossterm>Home Computer Banking Interface (HBCI)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A bank-independent online banking protocol used by German banks. Home 
    Banking Computer Interface (HBCI) was developed by the German Central 
    Banking Committee ZKA (Zentraler Kredit-Ausschuss). Since 2002, it has 
    been called Financial Transaction Services (FinTS). HBCI is one import 
    format that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_fints">Financial Transaction Services (FinTS)</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_interest">
  <glossterm>Interest</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>What a borrower pays a lender for the use of their money. Normally, 
    this is expressed in terms of a percentage of the principal per year. For 
    example, a savings account with 1% interest will pay you $1 for every $100 
    you keep deposited per year.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_liability">
  <glossterm>Liability</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A liability is a debt or obligation that an individual or organization
    owes.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_libofx">
  <glossterm>LibOFX</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>An open source library for <emphasis>OFX</emphasis>. It was created by one 
    of the <application>&app;</application> developers, originally to be the 
    OFX interface for <application>&app;</application>.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_ofx">OFX</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_liquidity">
  <glossterm>Liquidity</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A measure of how easily convertible an investment is to cash. Money 
    in a savings account is very liquid, while money invested in a house has 
    low liquidity because it takes time to sell a house.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_lot">
  <glossterm>Lot</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A lot is a means of grouping a commodity so that you later identify that 
    the item bought in one transaction is the same as one sold in a different 
    transaction. Lots are often implemented with stocks, where capital gain can
    depend on which item is being sold at a given time.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_mt940">
  <glossterm>MT940</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A financial information standard defined by SWIFT and used by several 
    European banks. It is also used internally in HBCI. Unfortunately, you can't 
    download the MT940 standard, but some banks publish it on their web sites. 
    MT940 is one import format that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry> 

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_ofx">
  <glossterm>OFX</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The Open Financial eXchange format. This is a financial information 
    exchange standard used by many institutions. OFX is one import format
    that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_pricedb">
  <glossterm>Price Database</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The price database contains a store of price quotes for stocks, mutual
    funds, and currencies.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_principal">
  <glossterm>Principal</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The original amount of money invested or borrowed.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_qfx">
  <glossterm>QFX</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The Quicken Financial eXchange format is a proprietary financial 
    information exchange standard promoted by Quicken and used by many institutions. 
    QFX is one import format that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_qif">
  <glossterm>QIF</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The Quicken Interchange Format (QIF) is an open specification for 
    reading and writing financial data to files. This is an older format that 
    is still used by many institutions. QIF is one import format
    that <application>&app;</application> supports.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_realgainloss">
  <glossterm>Realized Gain/Loss</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The difference between the purchase and selling prices of an investment
    at the time the investment is sold. Also known as 
    <emphasis>Capital Gain/Loss</emphasis>. Before an investment 
    is sold, the difference in value is referred to as 
    <emphasis>Unrealized Gain/Loss</emphasis>.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_capgainloss">Capital Gain/Loss</glossseealso>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_unrealgainloss">Unrealized Gain/Loss</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_return">
  <glossterm>Return</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The total income plus capital gains or losses of an investment.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_yield">Yield</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_risk">
  <glossterm>Risk</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The probability that the return on investment is different from what 
    was expected. Investments are often grouped on a scale from low risk (e.g., 
    savings accounts or government bonds) to high risk (e.g., common stocks 
    or junk bonds). As a general rule of thumb, the higher the risk, the 
    higher the possible return.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_schedtxn">
  <glossterm>Scheduled Transaction</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Scheduled transactions provide a framework for remembering information 
    about transactions that are set to occur in the future, either once or 
    periodically.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_yield">Yield</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_scheme">
  <glossterm>Scheme</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Scheme is a functional programming language based on a dialect of LISP.
    Reports in <application>&app;</application> use the Scheme programming language;
    thus, users wishing to customize reports must write Scheme.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

 <glossentry id="gnc-gl_shareholder">
  <glossterm>Shareholder</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A shareholder is a person who holds common stock in a company.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_split">
  <glossterm>Split</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A split, or Ledger Entry, is the fundamental accounting unit. 
    Each split consists of an amount, the value of that amount expressed in a 
    (possibly) different currency, a Memo, a pointer to the parent Transaction, 
    a pointer to the debited Account, a reconciled flag and timestamp, an action 
    field, and a key-value frame which can store arbitrary data.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_stock">
  <glossterm>Stock</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A security that represents a certain fractional ownership of a company. 
    This is what you buy when you <quote>buy stock</quote> in a company on the 
    open market. This is also sometimes known as <emphasis>capital stock</emphasis>, 
    or <emphasis>common stock</emphasis>.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_stocksplit">
  <glossterm>Stock split</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Occurs when a company offers to issue some additional multiple of shares 
    for each existing stock. For example, a <quote>2 for 1</quote> stock split 
    means that if you own 100 shares of a stock, you will receive an additional 
    100 shares at no cost to you. The unit price of the shares will usually be 
    adjusted  so there is no net change in the value, so in this example the 
    price per share will be halved. Note that such transactions affect the cost
    basis per share owned.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_transaction">
  <glossterm>Transaction</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A transaction consists of a date, a description, an ID number, a list 
    of one or more splits, and a key-value frame. Transactions embody the notion 
    of "double entry" accounting.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_unrealgainloss">
  <glossterm>Unrealized Gain/Loss</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Unrealized gain or loss is the difference in value between a purchase
    price and the current value of a given asset. These gains remain unrealized
    until the asset is sold, at which point they become <emphasis>Realized gains 
    or losses</emphasis>.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_capgainloss">Capital Gain/Loss</glossseealso>
    <glossseealso otherterm="gnc-gl_realgainloss">Realized Gain/Loss</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_valuation">
  <glossterm>Valuation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The process of determining the market value or the price the 
    investment would sell at in a <quote>reasonable time frame</quote>.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_xml">
  <glossterm>XML</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The eXtensible Markup Language is an international markup standard.
    <application>&app;</application> stores its data by default in an XML data 
    structure.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry id="gnc-gl_yield">
  <glossterm>Yield</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>A measure of the amount of money you earn from an investment 
    (i.e., how much income you receive from the investment). Typically, this 
    is reported as a percentage of the principal amount. Yield does not include 
    capital gains or losses (see Return). For example, a stock that sells for $100 
    and gives $2 in dividends per year has a yield of 2%.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<!-- ... -->

</glossary>
