<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.x
  Last modified: December 7th 2009
       modified: March 28th 2007
       modified: August 12th 2006
	   modified: February 28th 2005

  Maintainers:
               Alex Aycinena <alex.aycinena@gmail.com>
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
               Neil Williams <linux@codehelp.co.uk>

  Author:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->

<chapter id="setup-accounts">
      <title>Setting Up, Editing &amp; Working with Accounts</title>

      <para>This section describes the process of setting up, editing and working with GnuCash Accounts.
        In GnuCash an Account is used as the basic tool to organize the recording of where money comes
        from and goes to. GnuCash also extends the concept of real world accounts such as a bank
        account or loan account to grouping income and expense accounts. This allows you to
        quickly see where you spent your money and what your major income and expenses are.
        GnuCash sets Account Types (as described in the next section) to help in organizing
        and grouping accounts. Account Types can be used to create a Chart of Accounts.
      </para>

      <sect1 id="acct-types">
        <title>Types of GnuCash Accounts</title>

        <para>GnuCash supports a number of different account types. It is recommended to
         choose an appropriate account type based on the list of account types described
         below.</para>

        <table frame="topbot" id="TypeAccounts">
         <title>Types of GnuCash Accounts.</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Account Type</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Accounts Payable</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Accounts Payable are used by businesses to record amounts that
                 must be paid. Example: The business has bought something, but the business
                 has not paid the bill until later.</para>
                  <note><para>Previous versions of this help defined A/P and A/R the other way
                   round.</para></note>
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Accounts Receivable</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Accounts Receivable records amounts for which money
                 has not yet been received. Example: A business has sold something and
                 issued a bill, but the client has not payed until later.</para>
                  <note><para>Previous versions of this help defined A/P and A/R the other way
                   round.</para></note>
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Asset</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Asset accounts are used for tracking things that are of
		 value and can be used or sold to pay debts. (Normally a placeholder account)
                 </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Bank</para></entry>
                <entry><para>The Bank account type denotes savings or checking accounts
                 held at a bank or other financial institution. Some of these accounts may
                 bear interest. This is also the appropriate account type for check (debit)
                 cards, which directly withdraw payments from a checking account. </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Cash</para></entry>
                <entry><para>The Cash account type is used to denote the cash that you store
                 in your wallet, shoe box, piggyback, or mattress.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Credit Card</para></entry>
                <entry><para>The Credit Card account type is used to denote credit card
                 accounts, both for cards that allow floating lines of credit (e.g. VISA,
                 MasterCard, or Discover) and with cards that do not permit continuing
                 balances (e.g. American Express) </para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Currency</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Currency Accounts were used for trading currencies, but have
                 been replaced by the Currency Transfer pane on the Transfer Funds Window
                 (<xref linkend="trans-win-enter"></xref>).</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Equity</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Equity accounts are used to store the opening balances when you
                 first start using GnuCash or start a new accounting period.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Expense</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Any expense such as food, clothing, taxes, etc. This type is
                 called a category in Quicken.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Income</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Any income received from sources such as salary, interest,
                 dividends, etc. This type is called a category in Quicken.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Liability</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Liability accounts are used for tracking debts or financial
                 obligations. (Normally a placeholder account)</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Mutual Fund</para></entry>
                <entry><para>A professionally managed portfolio of stocks and bonds or other
                 investments divided up into shares.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Stock</para></entry>
                <entry><para>A share of ownership in a corporation, which entitles its owner
                 to all the risks and rewards that go with it.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">New Account Hierarchy Setup</emphasis> druid described in the first section
         of this help is a convenient way of setting up a set of accounts to use as a framework of
         account types.</para>

        <para>When new accounts are created the available choices of account types are grayed
         out according to what type the parent account is. The following list contains the possible choices.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Accounts Payable: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Accounts Receivable: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Asset: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Bank: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Cash: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Credit Card: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Currency: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Equity: Only Equity accounts can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Expense: Only Expense or Income accounts can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Income: Only Expense or Income accounts can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Liability: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Mutual Fund: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Stock: All accounts except Equity, Expense and Income can be child accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="chart-create">
        <title>Creating a Chart of Accounts</title>

        <para>The Chart of Accounts is like a table of contents for your finances. The best
         way to conceptualize a chart of accounts is as a tree. The main branches represent
         entire categories or groups, while the leaves of the tree denote individual bank
         accounts or expense categories. When a summary report is requested, typically only
         the main branches are shown in the report, rather than the individual accounts. For
         example, a chart of accounts might look like the following:

	&chartacctseg;

	</para>

        <para>Note that accounts not only have names; they may have codes, to order the accounts.
         When a report is generated, the sort order is determined by the numbering. It's
         customary to have the leaf accounts end in non-zero digits, while parent nodes have
         increasing numbers of zeros. </para>

        <para>GnuCash does not prevent duplicate numbering, although we would encourage you
         to avoid this. Account codes are treated as numbers in base-36, thus, if you run out
         of numbers, you can use the letters, a through z.</para>

        <para>A sample chart of accounts is shown below. Each account is of a given account
         type. This example is a combination of some typical business and personal accounts.

	&chartofaccts;

	</para>

      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="chart-edit">
        <title>Editing a Chart of Accounts</title>

        <para>Editing the Chart of Accounts is done within the Parent Account pane of the Edit
         Account dialog. It is possible to move an account to any part of the Chart of Account.
         It is recommended to keep accounts generally under the related types of accounts as
         described in the Types of GnuCash Accounts section. This helps to preserve the Chart
         of Accounts structure.</para>

        <para>To move the selected account to a different parent account just select the
         account in the Parent Account pane. If New top level account is selected then the
         account will be move to the top level.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="acct-create">
        <title>Creating a New Account</title>

        <para>The <guilabel>New Account</guilabel> properties dialog consists of two tabs, the <guilabel>General
         Information</guilabel> tab and the <guilabel>Opening Balance</guilabel> tab. This dialog can be accessed by
         going to <guimenu>File -&gt; New Account...</guimenu> or by clicking the <guilabel>New</guilabel> toolbar
         icon in the Account Tree Window.
        </para>

        <para>Creating a New Account involves planning in advance several details that are
         used in the New Account dialog. </para>

         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>What type of account is needed .</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Where it fits in the structure of the Chart of Accounts.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If there is an Opening Balance.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If there is a Commodity(security/currency) needed for the account.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If on-line updating of the commodity price is needed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>These details are described below.</para>

        <sect2 id="gen-info">
          <title>General Information Tab</title>

          <para>The General Information tab is used to access the basic information about the
           account. It provides a way of connecting the account to stock information if it is
           one of the currency, mutual fund or stock account types. It can also be flagged as
           a Placeholder account. It displays if it is flagged as a Tax Related account (which
           is set through the Edit -&gt; Income Tax Options dialog).</para>

          <para>There are six panes in the Identification section of this tab.</para>

          <para>The top pane contains the Account Information.</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Account Name:</guilabel> Enter a name for the account such as First Bank
               Checking.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Account Code:</guilabel> Enter an optional number code as described in the To Create
               a Chart of Accounts section.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Description:</guilabel> This is an optional description for the account.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Security/Currency:</guilabel> </para>

                 <note><para>The Type field in the <guilabel>Select Security</guilabel> is determined by the selection
                 of <guilabel>Account Type</guilabel> panel in the <guilabel>New Account</guilabel> screen.</para></note>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>For accounts other than Stock or Mutual Fund this should be the
               default currency, USD (US Dollar) or your local currency symbol. If this account is for a foreign
               currency then use the <guilabel>Select...</guilabel> button to choose a different currency from the
               currencies pull-down list.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para>For Accounts containing a Stock and Mutual Fund; first select "stock" or "mutual fund" in
               the <guilabel>Account Type</guilabel> panel, then the <guilabel>Parent Account</guilabel>, then use
               the <guilabel>Select...</guilabel> button, to choose the Type (usually the exchange the security
                is traded on) and security from the Select Security window.</para>

              <para>If the required security/fund is not on the list, and you have the correct Type you will need
               to create the security/fund.  To create a commodity for mutual fund and stock accounts select the
               <guilabel>New...</guilabel> button in the Select Security screen, to bring up the
               <guilabel>New Security:</guilabel> screen. The options are described in detail in the Security Editor
               <xref linkend="tool-security-edit"></xref> section.
               Fill in a name, symbol and type and <guilabel>Close</guilabel> to create the security.
               After the security is created select the <guilabel>Type:</guilabel> (usually the exchange the security
               is traded on) and the name in the <guilabel>Currency/security:</guilabel> drop down list and
               <guilabel>Close</guilabel> the screen.</para>

            </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>

          <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Smallest Fraction:</guilabel> Choose the smallest fraction that will be tracked.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Notes:</guilabel> Free form text box. This is used for any additional notes about
               the account.</para>
          </listitem>
         </orderedlist>

           <para> Below the panes are check-boxes: one to show if the account is <guilabel>Tax
           Related</guilabel> (which is set through the Edit -&gt; Income Tax Options dialog), and
           two to mark the account as a <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel>, and/or a
           <guilabel>Hidden</guilabel> account.
           </para>

           <para>The <guilabel>Tax Related</guilabel> check-box means that this account has been
           flagged to be included in the Tax Schedule Report. This flag is only displayed on the Edit
           Account dialog and is set in the Income Tax Information dialog (Edit->Income Tax
           Options). See the Tax Schedule Report and TXF Export section in Reports Chapter (<xref linkend="report-general"></xref>).</para>

           <para>The check-box <guilabel>Placeholder</guilabel> marks this account as solely a placeholder in the
           hierarchy, it is used to enable a hierarchy or chart of accounts to be setup. A Placeholder means this
           account is not used for transaction data. Transactions may not be posted to this account, only to
           sub-accounts of this account.</para>

           <para>The check box <guilabel>Hidden</guilabel> marks this account (and any sub-accounts) to be hidden in
           the account tree and not appear in the pop-up account list in the register.  To reset this option, you will
           first need to open the <guimenu>View -&gt; Filter By...</guimenu> dialog for the account tree and check the
           <guilabel>show hidden accounts</guilabel> option.  Doing so will allow you to select the account and reopen
           this dialog.</para>

          <para>The next pane contains a list of <guilabel>Account Types</guilabel>. Select a type from the
           descriptions in the Types of GnuCash Accounts section.</para>

          <para>The next pane contains an account tree to choose a <guilabel>Parent Account</guilabel>. To create a
           new account tree select New top level account. If the parent account is a certain
           type, then several of the choices in Account Type become grayed out. For example if the
           Parent Account is Assets then Equity, Expense and Income become grayed.  This is to help
           maintain a proper account structure for the Chart of Accounts.</para>

       </sect2>

       <sect2 id="Online-price-setup"><title>Steps to enable On-line price updating</title>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Create the Account for the mutual fund or stock with it listed in the
               Security/Currency field, as described above.</para>

                <tip><para>When creating these accounts it is a good time to create income accounts to track dividends,
                 capital gains (long and short) and expense account(s) for tracking commissions and losses (if you
                 track losses as expenses).</para></tip>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Create the mutual fund or stock with either the Security Editor for existing stock/funds or the
               New Security/Currency dialog for a new stock/fund.</para>
              <para>Select <guilabel>Get On-line Quotes:</guilabel>, <guilabel>Type of Quote Source</guilabel> and
              <guilabel>Timezone.</guilabel></para>

              <para>Online currency quotes require that the check-box for Online quotes and the timezone be
               selected in the Security screen and the Security Editor check-box for "get quote" box is checked for
               those currencies that are to be downloaded.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Get On-line Quotes:</guilabel> This check-box is to enable this security/fund to
               have quotes downloaded from an on-line source.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Type of Quote Source</guilabel> use the radio buttons to select the type of source
               for the Online quotes.  <guilabel>Multiple:</guilabel> quote sources like "Europe" should be used if
               fail-over to multiple sites are desirable.  <guilabel>Single:</guilabel> selections will only return
               information from the specified source.</para>

               <para>After selecting the type of source for price quotes, select a quote source from the pull-down menu.
               Currently among the supported quote sources are; Yahoo, Yahoo Europe, Fidelity
               Investments, T. Rowe Price, the Vanguard Group, the Australian Stock Exchange
               (ASX) and TIAA-CREF.</para>

               <note><para>Note that Yahoo will provide price quotes for many mutual
               funds including Fidelity, T.Rowe Price and Vanguard, and that the quoted prices
               at Yahoo should be identical to those that may be found at the source sites.</para></note>

               <para> If you choose Yahoo Europe or Europe, you should append the market code for the security,
               such as PA for Paris, BE for Berlin, etc. Example: 12150.PA (a Peugeot security
               in the Paris market).  <xref linkend="Code4EurMrks"></xref> below lists codes for various European 
               markets.</para>

              <para>Pseudo-symbols for TIAA-CREF funds are listed in table <xref linkend="PsSymbs-TIAA-CREF"></xref>.
              </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Timezone for these quotes:</guilabel> Select the timezone for the source of the
               on-line quotes you are receiving. For example, Yahoo normally quotes Eastern
               timezone, so choose America/New York if you use that quote source.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

            <listitem>
             <para>To determine if the Perl module Finance::Quote is already installed on
              your system, type <quote>perldoc Finance::Quote</quote> in a terminal window
              and check to see if there is any documentation available. If you see the
              documentation, then the module is installed, if you do not see the
              documentation, then it has not been installed.</para>

             <para>To install Finance::Quote;</para>
              <orderedlist>
               <listitem><para>Close any GnuCash applications you have running.</para></listitem>

               <listitem><para>Locate the folder where GnuCash is installed by searching for <quote>gnc-fq-update</quote>
                (without the quotes).</para></listitem>

               <listitem><para>Change to that directory, open a root shell and run the command <quote>gnc-fq-update</quote>
                (without the quotation marks). This will launch a Perl CPAN update session that will go out onto the
                Internet and install the Finance::Quote module on your system. The gnc-fq-update program is interactive,
                however, with most systems you should be able to answer <quote>no</quote> to the first question:
                <quote>Are you ready for manual configuration? [yes]</quote> and the update will continue automatically
                from that point.</para>
               </listitem>

             </orderedlist>
             <para>After installation is complete, you should run the <quote>gnc-fq-dump</quote> test program, in the
              same directory, distributed with GnuCash to test if Finance::Quote is installed and working properly.</para>

             <note>
              <para>If you feel uncomfortable about performing any of these steps, please either email the GnuCash-user
               mailing list (<email>gnucash-user@gnucash.org</email>) for help or come to the GnuCash IRC channel on
               irc.gnome.org. You can also leave out this step and manually update your stock prices.</para>
             </note>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Select a commodity to the Price Editor.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Select <guibutton>Get Quotes</guibutton> in the Price Editor.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Check the latest price for the selected security.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>If you wish to update price quotes from the command line, you can do so by
           the following command;</para>

          <para><userinput>gnucash --add-price-quotes &lt;gnucash-file-name&gt;</userinput>
          </para>

          <para>The command <userinput>gnucash --add-price-quotes &lt;gnucash-file-name&gt;</userinput>
          can be used to fetch the current prices of your stocks.  The file specified
          <quote>&lt;gnucash-file-name&gt;</quote> will depend on the name and location of your
          data file.  This can be determined by the name displayed in the top frame of the GnuCash window,
          before the <quote>-</quote>.  The file name can also be found <quote>File -&gt;</quote>
          <quote>pull down list</quote>, the first item, numbered 1, is the name of the currently
          open file.</para>

          <para>This can be automated by creating a crontab entry. For example, to update your file every Friday
          evening (18:00) after markets close (modify the time accordingly for your time zone), you could add
          the following to your personal crontab:</para>

          <para>0 18 * * 5 gnucash --add-price-quotes $HOME/gnucash-filename &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1</para>

          <para>Remember that Mutual Fund <quote>prices</quote> are really <quote>Net Asset Value</quote>
          and require several hours after the exchange closes before being available. If NAVs are downloaded before
          the current days NAVs are determined, yesterday's NAVs are retrieved.</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="open-balance">
          <title>Opening Balance</title>

          <para>The Opening Balance tab is visible only when creating a new account. It is
           used to record the beginning balance for an account. This allows it to be used for
           two different scenarios. If using GnuCash for the first time to record transactions,
           it can be used as a beginning balance. If the accounts in use are closed at the end
           of a period and new accounts are created, it is used to close and carry balances
           forward.</para>

          <para>There are three panes in this tab. The top pane contains the <guilabel>Balance
           Information</guilabel>.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Balance:</guilabel> Enter the balance to start the account with.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Date:</guilabel> Choose here the date the opening balance should be recorded.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The next pane is the <guilabel>Transfer Type</guilabel> pane.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Use Opening Balances Equity account:</guilabel> This transfers the opening balance
               for the account from a standard Equity account called Opening Balances.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Select Transfer Account:</guilabel> This enables the pane below so a different
               account can be used to transfer the opening balance.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The last pane is the <guilabel>Transfer Account</guilabel> pane. Select the account to use for
           opening balances from the list of accounts in this pane.</para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="acct-edit">
       <title>Editing an Account</title>
        <para></para>
        <para>The Edit Account dialog consists of just the General Information tab. This tab
         has the same information that was described in To Create a New Account <xref linkend="acct-create"></xref>.
         To access the Edit Account dialog go to <guimenu>Edit -&gt; Edit Account</guimenu> (menu shortcut Ctrl-E) or
         click the <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> toolbar icon in the Account Tree Window.</para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="chart-renumber">
        <title>Renumbering Subaccounts</title>
          <para>Use "Renumber Subaccounts" to rewrite the account codes for all children of the
           current account.  For example, you have the following account structure:</para>

        <table frame="topbot" id="table-renumber1">
          <title>Starting account numbers.</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Code</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Name</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>10</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Colors</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-1</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Red</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-2</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Orange</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-3</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Yellow.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-4</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Blue</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-5</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Violet</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

         <para>You now need to add the "Green" account, but you want it to sort between
          the Yellow and Blue accounts.  Instead of having to manually renumber all the
          accounts starting with Blue, you can use the "renumber subaccount" command on the
          Colors account.  In the pop-up dialog the prefix value should default to "10", the
          account code for the colors account.  If you set an interval value of 5 and click
          "Renumber" you will end up with the following account structure:</para>

        <table frame="topbot" id="table-renumber2">
          <title>Renumbered account numbers</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Code</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Name</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>10</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Colors</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-05</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Red</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-10</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Orange</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-15</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Yellow.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-20</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Blue</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-25</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Violet</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Now you have room in the account code numbering space to add the Green account
         with an account code to force the proper ordering.</para>

        <table frame="topbot" id="table-renumber3">
          <title>Final account numbers.</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Code</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Name</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>10</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Colors</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-05</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Red</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-10</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Orange</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-15</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Yellow.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-18</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Green</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-20</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Blue</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>10-25</para></entry>
                <entry><para>Violet</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="acct-delete">
        <title>Deleting an Account</title>
        <para></para>
        <para>Deleting an Account means removing all transaction information and information about this
         account from the file. This cannot be undone. You will be prompted to verify that you wish to
         remove the account. If the account still contains transaction information you will be warned that this
         account contains transactions.</para>

        <para>A side effect of removing an account that contains transactions is that you will
         end up with unbalanced accounts. This will be indicated in the account by a gray
         check-box next to the debit and credit amounts. You can repair automatically these
         unbalanced accounts by using the <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Check &amp; Repair</guimenu> menu. This will
         automatically assign the unbalanced amounts to a new account named <emphasis role="bold">Imbalance.
         </emphasis></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1 id="acct-reconcile">
        <title>Reconciling an Account to a Statement</title>
        <para>Reconciliation of Accounts in GnuCash with statements from a bank or other
         institution is a way of double checking the accuracy of your (and your banks) transactions and the balance
         of your accounts. It also is useful to track uncleared checks and other outstanding transactions. </para>

        <para>The Summary Bar at the bottom of the Account Register Window indicates the amounts
         of Present (Balance), Future (Balance), Cleared (Transactions), Reconciled (Transactions) and
         Projected Minimum. On-line account information can be used to
         mark which transactions the bank has processed by changing the R (reconciliation status)
         column in the register from n (new) to c (cleared). The bank statement is then used
         with the Reconcile Window to reconcile the account which changes the R field to y
         (reconciled).</para>

        <para>The Reconciling Windows are accessed in the Account Tree Window or the Account Register Window by
         going to  <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Reconcile...</guimenu> (menu shortcut Alt-A, R).</para>


      <sect2 id="tool-reconcile">
<!--        <title>Reconciling Windows</title>

        <para>The Reconciling Windows are used to reconcile bank statements to
        GnuCash accounts. They provide access to various GnuCash functions to
        make it easy to enter and update account information during the
        reconciliation.</para>

        <sect3 id="rec-info">-->
          <title>Reconciling Information Window</title>

          <para>The Reconcile Information dialog is used to indicate the closing statement date
           and the starting (fixed from last reconciliation) and ending balance from the statement. The <guilabel>Include
           Sub-accounts</guilabel> check-box is used if two or more accounts are used to track a single
           bank account. The <guilabel>Enter Interest Payment</guilabel> button is used to add a transfer to the
           accounts for an interest payment. If selected a dialog will be displayed to add the interest
           payment to the account.</para>

          <para>There are three panes in the Interest Payment dialog. At the bottom is a
           button called <guibutton>No Auto Interest Payments for this Account</guibutton> which will cancel the
           dialog. The top pane contains the Payment Information.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Amount:</guilabel> Enter the amount of the interest payment.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Date:</guilabel> Select the date for the interest payment.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Num:</guilabel> Enter a number for the transaction (optional).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Description:</guilabel> Enter an informational description for the transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><guilabel>Memo:</guilabel> Enter a note about the transaction (optional).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The next window contains a list of accounts for the <quote>Payment From</quote> account. If the
           payment is for a credit or loan account then usually this would be from an Expense
           account. If the payment is for a checking or savings account then usually this would
           be from an Income account. The Show Income/Expense check-box shows or hides the
           Income and Expense accounts.</para>

          <para>Select <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to enter the interest transaction and return to the initial
           reconciliation screen.</para>

          <para><!--The next pane contains the Reconcile Account. This shows the account that the
           interest payment will be transferred to or from.--></para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="rec-win">
          <title>Reconcile Window</title>

          <para><!--The parts of the Reconcile Window are described in the Tool Windows section of
           GnuCash Windows. This window is used to open the account and to add transaction
           information to the account in order to reconcile the account to the bank statement.
          --></para>

          <para>The set of unreconciled transactions in the Funds In and Funds Out panes can
           be changed by using the menus and toolbar to access the account and transaction
           information. If you wish to postpone the reconciliation until later use the
           <guimenu>Reconcile -&gt; Postpone</guimenu> menu item (menu shortcut Ctrl-P) or pressing the
           <guibutton>Postpone</guibutton> icon.   If you wish to cancel the reconciliation use the
           <guimenu>Reconcile -&gt; Cancel</guimenu> menu item or press the
           <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> icon.</para>

          <para>Select each unreconciled transaction matching a transaction on the statement so a
           green tick appears in the R column. The Balance pane changes to reflect each
           selected transaction until the Ending Balance equals the Reconciled Balance and the
           Difference is zero. Once this is done select the <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> button or
           <guimenu>Reconcile -&gt; Finish</guimenu> (menu shortcut Ctrl-F) to finish the reconcile process.</para>
<!--        </sect2>

        <table frame="topbot" id="Tools-ReconcileWin">
          <title>Components of the Reconcile Window.</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Component</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Menu bar</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Contains the Menus used in the Reconcile
                  Window.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Tool (Icons and/or Text) Bar</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Contains buttons used to access common Reconcile Account
                  Window tasks.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Funds In</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Contains a list of funds deposited in the
                  account.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Funds Out</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Contains a list of funds withdrawn from the
                  account.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Balance Pane</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Contains a list of balances to use in
                  reconciling.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="rec-menus">
          <title>Menus</title>

          <para>The following tables describe menus in the Reconcile
          Window.</para>

          <table frame="topbot" id="tool-reconcile-menu">
            <title>Reconcile Menu - Access to Reconcile Information and
          finishing or postponing.</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Menu Item</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Reconcile Information</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Opens the Reconciling Information Window.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Finish</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Complete the reconciliation of this account.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Postpone</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Postpone the reconciliation of this account.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Cancel</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Cancel the reconciliation of this account.</para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>


          <table frame="topbot" id="tool-rec-account">
            <title>Account Menu - Access to account operations.</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Menu Item</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

             \ <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Open Account</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Opens a transaction register for the accounts</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Edit Account</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Modify name or characteristic of selected account. <xref linkend="acct-edit"></xref>
                   </para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Transfer...</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Opens a Transfer druid for entering a transfer transaction between any two accounts.</para>
                  </entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Check &amp; Repair</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Verify &amp; Repair this account if necessary.</para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>


          <table frame="topbot" id="tool-rec-trans">
            <title>Transaction Menu - Access to transaction editing
          operations.</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Menu Item</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>New</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Add a new transaction to the account.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Edit</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Edit the currently selected transaction.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Delete</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Remove the currently selected transaction.</para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>


          <table frame="topbot" id="tool-rec-help">
            <title>Help Menu - Access to help.</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Menu Item</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Help</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Open this Help text file.</para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>

        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="rec-toolbar">
          <title>Tool Bar Buttons</title>

          <para>The Reconcile Window has a tool bar to access quickly some
          common functions used with reconciliation.</para>

          <table frame="topbot" id="tool-rec-toolbar">
            <title>Reconcile Window Tool Bar</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Tool Bar Button</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>New</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Add a new transaction to the account.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Edit</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Edit the currently selected transaction.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Delete</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Remove the currently selected transaction.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Open</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Open an Account transaction window.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Finish</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Complete the reconciliation of this account.</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry><para>Postpone</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Postpone the reconciliation of this account.</para></entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><para>Cancel</para></entry>

                  <entry><para>Cancel the reconciliation of this account.</para></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>

-->
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="rec-main">
          <title>Reconciling Window</title>

          <para>The "Funds In" pane shows all unreconciled deposits to the
          account.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Date: The date of the unreconciled transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Num: The number of the unreconciled transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Description: The Description of the unreconciled
              transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Amount: The Amount of the unreconciled transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>R: Shows a green tick if the transaction will be
              reconciled when done.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The "Funds Out" pane shows all unreconciled expenses from the
          account.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Date: The date of the unreconciled transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Num: The number of the unreconciled transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Description: The Description of the unreconciled
              transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Amount: The Amount of the unreconciled transaction.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>R: Shows a green tick if the transaction will be
              reconciled when done.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The Balance pane shows the balances used in
          reconciliation.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Starting Balance: The balance at the end of the last
              reconciliation.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Ending Balance: The balance entered from the
              statement.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Reconciled Balance: The balance of selected
              transactions.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Difference: The difference between the Reconciled and
              Ending Balances.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
<!--      </sect3>-->
     </sect2>

    </sect1>

</chapter>

