<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.x
   Last modified: April 15th 2007
        modified: August 12th 2006
	modified: February 28th 2005

  Maintainers:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
               Neil Williams <linux@codehelp.co.uk>

  Author:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->

<!--
  Common Transaction Operations Items Here !!!
-->

<chapter id="ch_Common_Trans_Ops">
  <title>Common Transaction Operations</title>

      <para>A transaction represents the movement of money from one account to another account. Whenever you spend or
       receive money, or transfer money between accounts, that is a transaction. In GnuCash transactions always involve
       at least two accounts.</para>

      <para>GnuCash uses accounts as a way of grouping or organizing the recording of transactions.
       This section describes the methods GnuCash has to help enter transactions
       quickly into the register. </para>
      <para></para>

        <para>GnuCash has several methods available for entering transactions.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
            <para>Entering directly into the register window is the most common way of entering transactions.</para>
           </listitem>

           <listitem>
            <para>Using the Transfer Funds Window.</para>
           </listitem>

           <listitem>
            <para>Importing transactions either from a QIF/OFX file or via "OFX on-line banking".</para>
           </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>

<note>
<para>Where should the "Importing of data from downloaded files" and "On-line" banking be covered?.
</para></note>

    <sect1 id="reg-views">
        <title>Changing the Register View</title>

        <para>GnuCash has several options to change the way the register looks so transactions can be seen more
         clearly.  The default style is the Basic Ledger. This presents a single line view of transactions to allow
         the most concise view with all the relevant details.</para>

        <para>The default view or style can be changed by going to <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu, three radio buttons
         will select the desired option. When the window closes the style will revert to the Basic Ledger style. To
         make this change permanent change the style in the <guilabel>Edit &gt; Preferences &gt; Register Defaults
         </guilabel> in the Register display.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Basic Ledger:</guimenu> The default one line per transaction style. Splits are
             shown as a summary.  The <guimenu>Splits</guimenu> icon and <guimenu>Actions &gt; Split
             Transaction</guimenu> are enabled.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Auto-Split Ledger:</guimenu> This style will automatically expand the splits in any
             transaction selected.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Transaction Journal:</guimenu> This style expands all transactions so the complete
             transaction can be seen.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><guimenu>Double Line:</guimenu> This check-box changes any of the above styles so that an additional
             line for notes about the transaction is added.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The two other options to change the view of the register are; to restrict displayed items with the 
         <guimenu>View &gt; Filter By ...</guimenu>,
          and changing the sort order <guimenu>View &gt; Sort Order</guimenu>.   <xref linkend="Trans-view-menu"></xref>.
        </para>

    </sect1>

  <sect1 id="trans-win-enter">
    <title>Transfer Funds Window</title>

          <para>The method described here uses the Transfer Funds Window to enter a single transaction. This is
           mainly used as a quick way to enter a single transaction without opening the account registers. When
           entering multiple transactions it is recommended to use the register directly.  The Transfer Funds window
           is accessed from <guimenu>Action &gt; Transfer</guimenu>, or by pressing the <guibutton>Transfer</guibutton>
           icon from the account register tab.</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enter in the "Transfer Information" pane the Amount, Date and Description. The Num and Memo fields
               are optional.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the "Transfer From" account. If this account is an income or expense account select the
               check-box at the bottom of the "Transfer From" pane.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Choose the "Transfer To" account. If this account is an income or expense account select the
               check-box at the bottom of the Transfer From pane.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If one of the accounts above is a different currency from the other account the Currency Transfer
               pane will be enabled to add either an "Exchange Rate" or a "To Amount".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Select <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to commit the transaction or <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>
               to dismiss the dialog without entering the transaction.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="trans-enter">
    <title>Enter Transaction via register</title>

     <para>When the Account Register Window for an account is opened the list of transactions for that
      account is shown. This window has the name of the account on its tab. The menus contain several
      functions that alter the display of transactions. The toolbar also contains several functions that are
      often used when entering or manipulating transactions. These are described in the
      <xref linkend="account-register"></xref> section of this document.</para>

    <sect2 id="trans-reg-enter">
     <title>Entering Directly in the Register Window</title>

      <para>The register window will look slightly different depending on the style options you have chosen.
       The following describes entering simple transactions in the basic ledger style. The cursor is placed
       in the date field by default when the register window is opened.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>Selecting the small icon on the right of the date field drops down a date selection calender.
            Use the arrows to select the correct month and year for the transaction then select the date.
            Selecting the icon once more will close the date selection calender. It is also possible to
            type in the date or part of the date and let GnuCash fill the rest.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move to or select the "Num" field. Here you can enter a check or
            transaction number.  Pressing <keycap>+</keycap> (plus) will automatically advance the number by one from
            the last transaction to have a number.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move or select the "Description" field. This field is used to enter
            either a payee or other description for the transaction. It will automatically attempt to fill the payee
            name as you type.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>At this stage one of two things will happen if tab is pressed. If GnuCash matches an existing
            transaction the cursor will jump to one of the amount fields, automatically filling in the transfer
            account.  Selecting any field with the mouse instead of tabbing will not automatically fill the
            transferring account field.  If there is no matching (existing) transaction, GnuCash will move the
            cursor to the "Transfer" field with only one line of the transaction supplied.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>When typing into the account field GnuCash will also attempt to automatically match the account
            name with an existing account.  It does this alphabetically, so typing 'Ex' will match the Expenses
            section of the account list. When the section is matched, it is possible to move to a child account by
            pressing <keycap>:</keycap> (colon). If after typing 'Ex' you press <keycap>:</keycap> then the cursor will
            move to the first child account in the list.  Typing combinations of letters and <keycap>:</keycap> will
            allow movement down the tree of accounts quickly. The triangle icon on the right of the Transfer box can
            be used as an alternate way of selecting accounts.  Up &amp; down arrow keys will also move up/down the
            displayed list of accounts.
           </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>The next field (R) is used for reconciliation. This is described in the <guimenu>Reconcile an
            Account to a Statement</guimenu> section.  <xref linkend="acct-reconcile"></xref></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>Press tab to move to the first of the amount fields. The names of the next two columns are different
            according to what type of account is opened. For example, Bank accounts show Deposit and Withdrawal here,
            Credit Card accounts show Payment and Charge, and Stock accounts show Shares, Price, Buy and Sell.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>Enter an amount for the transaction in the correct fields. When the transaction is "balanced"
            pressing the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key, selecting the <guibutton>Enter</guibutton> icon or going to
            <guimenu>Transaction -&gt; Enter Transaction</guimenu> will finish the transaction. Selecting the
            <guibutton>Cancel </guibutton> icon or going to <guimenu>Transaction -&gt; Cancel Transaction</guimenu>
            will erase the transaction.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>Transactions with just one transfer account will show the name of that account in the Transfer
            field in completed transactions. (The "Transfer field" is the fourth (4) from the left in the register
            display.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
           <para>To move to the blank transaction at the bottom of the register, press the 
            <guibutton>Blank</guibutton> toolbar icon or go to <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Blank Transaction</guimenu>.
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
        </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="trans-multi-enter">
   <title>Multiple Split Transactions</title>

    <para>The register window will look slightly different depending on the style options you have chosen.
     The following describes entering transactions with multiple splits in the basic ledger style. GnuCash describes
     as a "Split" when money is transferred to or from more than two accounts in a transaction.
     The cursor is placed in the date field by default when the register window is opened.</para>

    <para>The multiple account lines will not be displayed in the Basic Ledger unless the <guimenu>Split</guimenu>
     icon or the <guimenu>Action &gt; Split Transaction</guimenu> option have been selected.
    </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>Selecting the triangle icon on the right of the date field drops down a date selection dialog.
          Use the arrows to select the correct month and year for the transaction then select the date. Selecting
          the icon once more will close the date selection calendar. It is also possible to type in the
          date or part of the date and let GnuCash fill the rest.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move to or select the "Num" field. Here you can enter a check or
          transaction number.  Pressing <keycap>+</keycap> (plus) will automatically advance the number by one from
          the last transaction to have a number.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move to or select the "Description" field. This field is used to enter
          either a payee or other description for the transaction. It will automatically attempt to fill the payee name
          as you type.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>At this stage one of two things will happen if tab is pressed. If GnuCash matches an existing
          transaction the cursor will jump to one of the amount fields, automatically filling in the transfer
          account.  Selecting any field with the mouse instead of tabbing will not automatically fill the
          transferring account field.  If there is no matching (existing) transaction, GnuCash will move the
          cursor to the "Transfer" field with only one line of the transaction supplied.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>When typing in the Transfer field GnuCash will also attempt to automatically match the account.
          It does this alphabetically, so typing 'Ex' will match the Expenses section of the account list.
          When the section is matched, it is possible to move to a child account by pressing <keycap>:</keycap> (colon).
          If after typing 'Ex' you press <keycap>:</keycap> then the cursor will move to the first child account in the
          list.  Typing combinations of letters and <keycap>:</keycap> will allow movement down the tree of accounts
          quickly. The icon on the right of the Transfer box can be used as an alternate way of selecting accounts.
         </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>The next field is used for reconciliation. This is described in the To Reconcile an Account
          to a Statement section.  <xref linkend="acct-reconcile"></xref></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move to the first of the amount fields. The names of the next two columns
          are different according to what type of account is opened. For example, Bank accounts show 
          Deposit and Withdrawal here, Credit Card accounts show Payment and Charge, and Stock accounts
          show Shares, Price, Buy and Sell.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Enter the total amount for the transaction in the correct field. Before pressing <keycap>Tab</keycap>
          or <keycap>Enter</keycap> read next step.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>To enter the additional splits, press the Split button on the toolbar or select 
          <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Split Transaction</guimenu>. Transactions with more than one split show
          '--Split Transaction--' and the <guibutton>Split</guibutton> button will need to be used
          to show the details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>The display will expand, the titles of the amount columns will be renamed and the Transfer
          column name will be blank. The first line contains the description and the amount of the transaction.
          The second line contains the currently opened account name in the Account field and the amount of
          the transaction. The third line contains the transfer account name in the Account field. If the
          amount is not balanced GnuCash will indicate this by placing gray check-boxes in the amount columns
          with the unbalanced amount in a blank last row.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>When one of the short lines is selected, the column titles will change. The very first and last
          (Date and Balance) columns will have blank titles. Num will change to Action, Description to Memo,
          the now blank Transfer column will change to Account. The last two amount columns will show the name
          described in step seven.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>The Action and Memo columns are optional to fill out at this stage. Action is used to describe
          what kind of account transfer is involved. Memo is an additional description of the transfer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Move to the missing amount field on the third line and fill in the amount. Pressing the
          <keycap>Enter</keycap> key, selecting the <guibutton>Enter</guibutton> icon or going to <guimenu>Actions
          -&gt; Enter</guimenu> will now move the cursor to the next line.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>The Account column contains the list of transfer accounts. This column is the one that is used
          to add splits. The method described in step five can be used to select another account on a blank line.
          Add as many additional splits as needed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>When the transaction is balanced the gray check-boxes will disappear and the last blank line will
          not have an amount.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap> as described above past the blank line will jump to the next
          transaction. Selecting the next transaction will close the split or it can be manually closed by pressing
          the <guibutton>Split</guibutton> icon or selecting <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Split Transaction</guimenu>.</para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>

   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="trans-currency-enter">
        <title>Multiple Currency Transactions</title>

        <para>Currently transfers between different currencies are only supported by using the Transfer Funds
         Window described above (<xref linkend="trans-win-enter"></xref>. It is necessary to use this dialog
         to add an exchange rate. </para>

        <para>To setup an account as a different currency edit the account properties and change the Commodity
         field to the foreign currency. This account will now enable the Currency Transfer pane in the
         Transfer Funds Window.</para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="trans-edit">
        <title>Editing a Transaction</title>

        <para>Editing a transaction involves just selecting the part of the transaction that needs to be changed.
         Once the changes are complete pressing the <keycap>Enter</keycap> key, selecting the
         <guibutton>Enter</guibutton> icon or going to <guimenu>Transaction -&gt; Enter Transaction</guimenu> will
         now move the cursor to the next line or transaction.
        </para>

        <para>To see a more detailed view of a transaction for editing in Basic Ledger, press the
         <guibutton>Split</guibutton> button on the toolbar or select <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Split Transaction
         </guimenu>.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="trans-delete">
        <title>Deleting a Transaction</title>

        <para>If a transaction needs to be removed from the register, select the transaction and press either
         the <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> icon on the toolbar or go to <guimenu>Transaction -&gt; Delete
         Transaction</guimenu>.

         A window will appear to confirm the delete, unless the preference has been changed.  The window presents
         two options; "Remember and don't ask again", and "Remember and don't ask again this session". The response
         will be set according to the selected checkbox.  The preference can also be reset via <guimenu>Actions -&gt;
         Reset Warnings </guimenu>.  <xref linkend="reset-warning"></xref>.</para>

         <para>Parts of a transaction can also be removed by pressing the <guibutton>Split</guibutton> button on
         the toolbar or selecting <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Split Transaction</guimenu>. The part of the
         transaction that needs to be deleted can be then selected for deletion.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="trans-split-remove">
        <title>Removing Transaction Splits</title>

        <para>Removing Transaction Splits involves erasing all splits except the one for the account that is opened.
         This is a useful way of reusing a previous transaction that has multiple splits that need to be changed.
         (Note this can be done without opening the split, but doing so makes the effect more visible)</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If in Basic Ledger, press the <guibutton>Split</guibutton> button on the toolbar or Select
             <guimenu>Action -&gt; Split Transaction</guimenu> to open the transaction.  If in other modes
             select transaction.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select <guimenu>Transaction -&gt; Remove Transaction Splits</guimenu>.</para>
            <para>A window will appear to confirm the delete, unless the preference has been changed.  The window
             presents two options; "Remember and don't ask again", and "Remember and don't ask again this session".
             The response will be set according to the selected checkbox.  The preference can also be reset via
             <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Reset Warnings </guimenu>.  <xref linkend="reset-warning"></xref>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All Accounts and their related details will be removed except for the
             currently opened account. </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The amount is not balanced and GnuCash will indicate this by placing gray
             check-boxes in the amount columns with the unbalanced amount in the blank last
             row.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Edit the transaction to fill in the new details.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

 <sect1 id="trans-copy">
        <title>Copying a Transaction</title>

        <para>Copying Transactions is available from the <guimenu>Transaction</guimenu> menu.  The
         <guimenu>Transaction</guimenu> menu has <guimenu>Cut Transaction</guimenu>, <guimenu>Copy
         Transaction</guimenu> and <guimenu>Paste Transaction</guimenu> which allows a whole transaction to be
         cut or copied and pasted to a new transaction line.
         This way of copying a transaction will use the date showing in the new transaction blank line.
        </para>

        <para>The <guimenu>Transaction -&gt; Duplicate Transaction...</guimenu> or the toolbar
         <guimenu>Duplicate</guimenu> which, unlike the Copy method, allows for choosing a different date.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the transaction to duplicate.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Go to <guilabel>Transaction -&gt; Duplicate Transaction...</guilabel></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A dialog called <emphasis role="bold">Duplicate Transaction</emphasis> will prompt for a new 
             Date and Num for the transaction.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to add the transaction to the register.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="acct-jump">
    <title>Jump to another Account Register</title>

     <para>When using the Account Register Window it is frequently useful to be able to
      view another account and also the transfer account at the same time. GnuCash allows you to
      do this quickly by using 'Jump'. This is available <guimenu>Jump</guimenu> icon on the toolbar and in
      the <guimenu>Actions &gt; Jump</guimenu> menu in the Account Register Window. </para>

     <para>Select the transaction in the Account Register Window and either click the jump icon or select
      <guimenu>Action &gt; Jump</guimenu> to open the Account Register Window target. If the transaction is split
      between more than one transfer account then you will need to show all the split transfer accounts first and
      select the transfer account to jump to.</para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="trans-sched">
    <title>Scheduling Transactions</title>

     <para>Scheduled Transactions provide the ability to have reminders scheduled or transactions scheduled to be
      entered at a specified date. This is combined with the <emphasis role="bold">Since Last Run
      </emphasis> druid (<xref linkend="trans-sched-slr"></xref>) to review and enter the transactions. The
      <guilabel>Mortgage &amp; Loan Repayment</guilabel> druid (<xref linkend="trans-sched-loans"></xref>) is used
      to setup a scheduled transaction to repay a compounding interest loan. The Scheduled Transaction Editor
      (<xref linkend="sched-editor"></xref>) is used to create and edit transactions that are to be added to the
      register in an automated way.</para>

     <para>The easiest way to setup a scheduled transaction is to use an existing transaction in an account register
      as a template. Select the transaction you wish to use as a template and then either select the
      <guilabel>Schedule</guilabel> icon on the toolbar or go to <guilabel>Actions -&gt; Schedule...</guilabel>.
      This will bring up the <emphasis role="bold">Make Scheduled Transaction</emphasis> dialog.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Name:</guilabel> Enter a name to use for the scheduled transaction. This will be
         used in the Description file of the transaction.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Frequency:</guilabel> Choose the time period you want between scheduled entries. The
         dates that the transactions will be entered will show in the mini calendar pane to the right.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Start Date:</guilabel> Choose a date for the scheduled transaction to start.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Never End:</guilabel> This scheduled transaction has no finish date.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>End Date:</guilabel> Choose a date for the scheduled transaction to end.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Number of Occurrences:</guilabel> Enter the number of times you wish the scheduled
         transaction to be added to the register.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

       <para>The <guilabel>Advanced...</guilabel> button brings up the Scheduled Transaction Editor's dialog to
        Edit the Scheduled Transaction. This is described in the section Scheduled Transaction Editor.
        <xref linkend="sched-editor"></xref></para>

       <sect2 id="sched-trans-win">
        <title>Scheduled Transactions Window</title>

         <para>The Scheduled Transaction Window is used to access the list of scheduled transactions and create,
          edit or remove them. It also provides a calendar which displays upcoming scheduled transactions. Clicking
          on the calendar view and hovering over any date will pop up a small dialog that shows the transactions
          scheduled for that day. The yellow highlight in the calendar indicates which days have scheduled
          transactions. To dismiss the hover dialog click once more.</para>

         <para>The top pane of the Scheduled Transaction Window contains the list of scheduled transactions that are
          currently setup. This window lists the Name of the transaction, if the transaction is enabled for scheduling,
          the Frequency (month and day) that the transaction is to be entered, the last time the transaction was entered
          and the next time the transaction will be entered.</para>

         <para>The right side of this pane contains a down arrow button that when "clicked" will pull-down a window to
          allow selection of the characteristics displayed in the list.  Unchecking the appropriate box will remove the
          characteristic from the display.</para>

         <para>The tool bar of this window contains three buttons to create, delete and edit scheduled transactions.
          New and Edit opens the Edit Scheduled Transaction dialog. Delete removes the selected scheduled transaction.
          The same options are available thru <guimenu>Schedule -&gt; New/Edit/Delete</guimenu>, from the Scheduled
          Transaction Tab. </para>

         <para>Below the list of scheduled transactions is the Upcoming calendar. This calendar displays up to the next
          year and highlights the dates that the scheduled transactions are scheduled to occur so it is easy to see when
          the transactions are scheduled.  Clicking on a date in the calendar brings up a list of scheduled transactions
          for that date. Moving the mouse over other dates changes to the list of transactions on those dates. Clicking
          once more on the calendar removes the transaction list.</para>

         <para>The Scheduled Transaction Window is activated from the Account tab or the Transaction Register via
          <guimenu>Actions -&gt; Scheduled Transactions -&gt; Scheduled Transaction Editor</guimenu>,</para>

        </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sched-editor">
     <title>Edit Scheduled Transaction Window</title>

       <para>The Edit Scheduled Transaction Window is divided into a Name area, Options area, Occurrences area,
        Recurrence Frequency area, mini calendar and Template Transaction pane.</para>

       <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis> a name to use for the scheduled transaction. This will be
        used in the Description of the transaction.</para>

       <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis> area contains check-boxes to set if the transaction is
        automatically created and how many days in advance the transaction is created and/or a reminder posted.
       </para>

       <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Occurrences</emphasis> area contains selections to set for dates limits on
        transactions to be entered or the number of transactions to be entered.</para>

       <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Recurrence Frequency</emphasis> area contains selections to set how
        often the transaction is scheduled to be added and on what dates this occurs.</para>

       <para>The mini calendar provides a visual indication of what transactions are already scheduled.</para>

       <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Template Transaction</emphasis> pane allows you to setup the transaction
        as you would like it to be entered into the register.</para>

       <para>These options are described in more detail in <xref linkend="trans-sched"></xref></para>

        <itemizedlist>
         <listitem><para>From the Scheduled Transaction tab selecting a transaction from the list and pressing
          the Edit or pressing New icons will bring up the Edit Scheduled Transaction Editor.</para>
         </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="print-check">
    <title>Printing Checks</title>

     <para>Checks are printed in GnuCash from the account register. GnuCash provides the
      ability to print to standard Quicken Checks (US Letter) or to make a custom check
      format. Check position and Date formats are also customizable.</para>

     <para>To access the check printing feature in GnuCash, select the transaction to print
      a check for and go to File -&gt; Print Check. This will open the Print Check
      properties dialog.</para>

     <para>The Print Check dialog has two tabs. The first tab, Options, is used to setup
      the most common options to print a check. The second tab, Custom format, is used to
      setup the position of various fields on the check. It is useful to print a test check
      to a plain piece of paper first and use that to make any adjustments needed.</para>

     <para>The default selection in Options is for Quicken/Quickbooks (tm) US-Letter checks.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>Check format: Test with Quicken first then use custom if the position is incorrect.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Check position: This sets if the Top, Middle or Bottom check is printed.  Custom is used if the
         position of the checks on the page is incorrect.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Date format: The default here is set in the Preferences International section. Choose a date format.
         This can also be adjusted by the Use of the Months: and Years: lines. Custom allows the date format to be
         set in the Format: box (%m means month, %d means day, %Y means year) A Sample of the format chosen is
         displayed below.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The Custom check format contains two columns to enter in the X and Y co-ordinates of the field position
       on the check. Positions in the Custom Check Format entry area are specified with x = 0 at the left edge of
       the check with x increasing to the right, and y = 0 at the top edge of the check with y increasing as you
       travel down.  (If you are using a version of GTK prior to 2.10, then y = 0 is
       at the bottom of the page and y increases as you travel up.)</para>

       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>Payee: </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Date: </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Amount (words): </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Amount (numbers): </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Memo: </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Check position: </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Date format: </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
         <para>Units: Set the unit to use for the above positions.</para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>

       <para>Once OK is pressed on the Print Check dialog the Print GnuCash Document dialog is presented. Press OK
        to print the check.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="trans-online">
     <title>Online Actions ...</title>

<note><para>This section is "under construction - any input will be welcome !!".</para></note>

      <sect2> <title>Get Balance</title><para></para></sect2>
      <sect2> <title>Get Transactions ...</title><para></para></sect2>
      <sect2> <title>Issue Transaction</title><para></para></sect2>
      <sect2> <title>Direct Debit</title><para></para></sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1  id="general-ledger">
     <title>General Ledger</title>
      <para>The General Ledger is an advanced register used to enter transactions without needing to open
       individual accounts. The General Ledger shows the transaction entries for all accounts on one register.</para>

      <para>Entering transactions in the General Ledger is more complicated than entering them in the individual
       account registers. The advantage is the General Ledger provides a more comprehensive view of the
       transactions you have entered in all your accounts.</para>

      <para>The General Ledger defaults to showing only the previous month of transactions. This is changeable
       by using the Date Range on the View menu.</para>
    </sect1>

</chapter>

