<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.x
   Last modified: December 7th 2009
        modified: May 13th 2007
        modified: November 28th 2006
        modified: August 12th 2006
	modified: February 28th 2005

  Maintainers:
               Alex Aycinena <alex.aycinena@gmail.com>
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
               Neil Williams <linux@codehelp.co.uk>

  Author:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->

<chapter id="Reports">
  <title>Reports And Charts</title>

     <note><para>This section is a <quote>work in process</quote>. Some of the material has not been reviewed for V2.0.
      While it may not be strictly accurate, it is at least a "guide".</para></note>

  <sect1 id="report-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

   <para>Reports and Charts give <application>&app;</application> the ability to present an overview of financial
    data in various ways. This can range from a simple summary of account totals to an
    advanced portfolio view. This section will present an explanation of the main <application>&app;</application>
    reports and how to adjust them.</para>

   <para>To run a report or chart, click on the <menuchoice><guimenu>Reports
     </guimenu></menuchoice> menu, then either select
     a report (it will open with standard options), or click on <guibutton>
     Saved Report Configuration</guibutton> to select a report you have
     previously configured and saved.
   </para>

   <para>Once the report has opened, click on the <guibutton>Options
     </guibutton> toolbar button to
     configure the report as needed, for example to set the report date or
     select accounts.
   </para>

   <tip><para>If you intend to save a report configuration, you
     should choose a named report date option such as <emphasis>Today
     </emphasis>rather than enter a specific date so it is not necessary to
     enter a specific date again in future reports.</para>
   </tip>

   <tip><para>If you often run a report with a date as at the start or end of an
       accounting period, set the accounting period start and end dates in
       <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
       <guimenuitem>Accounting Period</guimenuitem></menuchoice> then select
       appropriate report date options.
       See <xref linkend="prefs-accounting-period" />.
     </para>
   </tip>

   <tip>
     <para>If you cannot find a specific report to suit your requirements, you
       may be able to use the <guilabel>Find Transaction</guilabel> assistant
       (<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Find</guimenuitem>
       </menuchoice>) to select a set of transactions, and then report them
       using <menuchoice><guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guimenuitem>Account Report
       </guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Further formatting or analysis may be done
       by copying and pasting the report into a spreadsheet.
     </para>
   </tip>

   <para>After you have configured a report, you can save the configuration for
     future use by clicking either the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration
     </guibutton> or <guibutton>Save Report Configuration As...</guibutton>
     button.
   </para>

   <sect2 id="report-saving">
     <title>Saving a Report Configuration</title>

     <para>To save a report configuration for future use, while the required
       report tab is selected, go to the report options, select the
       <emphasis>General</emphasis> tab and change the <emphasis>Report Name
       </emphasis> to a meaningful unique name. Do not confuse this with the
       <emphasis>Report Title</emphasis> which prints at the top of a report.
     </para>

     <para>Click the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration</guibutton> or
       <guibutton>Save Report Configuration As...</guibutton> button. This will
       store your customized report options in a file in your home directory.
       E.g. Linux: <emphasis>~/.gnucash/saved-reports-[versioninfo]</emphasis>
     </para>

     <para>The first time you save a report with a name that has not already
       been saved, you can use either the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration
       </guibutton> or the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration As...
       </guibutton> button. You can modify the report name before saving it.
     </para>

     <para>After a report configuration for a specific name has been saved, the
       <guibutton>Save Report Configuration</guibutton> button will immediately
       update the saved report configuration without giving the opportunity to
       save the configuration with a new name. Use the <guibutton>Save Report
       Configuration As...</guibutton> button to save the current report
       configuration with a new name.
     </para>

     <para>After your customized report has been saved, it is available for use
       by the <menuchoice><guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guimenuitem>Saved Report
       Configurations</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu and it will also be listed
       when starting <menuchoice><guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guisubmenu>Sample
       &amp; Custom</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Custom Multicolumn Report
       </guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
     </para>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-working">
     <title>Working with Saved Report Configurations</title>

     <para>Selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guimenuitem>Saved
       Report Configurations</guimenuitem></menuchoice> will open a dialog
       window with a list of the <emphasis>Saved Report Configurations
       </emphasis> you have previously created. In this
       context <emphasis>Saved Report Configurations</emphasis> means the set of
       customized settings for standard reports.
     </para>

     <para>The <emphasis>Saved Report Configurations</emphasis> window lists
       each of your previously saved report configurations, and 3 small buttons
       at the end of each. These buttons perform the following actions
     </para>

     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem><para>Load (and run) report configuration. Double clicking a
         report configuration also performs this action.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem><para>Edit report configuration name. This enables a report
         configuration to be renamed.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem><para>Delete report configuration.</para>
       </listitem>

     </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

  </sect1>

   <sect1 id="report-config">
      <title>Configuring Reports and Charts</title>

        <para><application>&app;</application> reports have many configuration
          options. First, run the original report itself. Then,
        access the report options with the <guibutton>Options</guibutton>
        button on the toolbar.</para>

           <note> <para>Check changed Graphic Engine Options</para></note>

   <sect2 id="report-opt-btns">
     <title>Report Options Buttons</title>

     <para>After modifying report options, either</para>

     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>Click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button to apply the changes,
           regenerate the report and
           close the options window.</para>

         <para>or</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
         <para>Click the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button to apply the
           changes, regenerate the report and leave the options window open for
           possible further changes. In this case, both the <guibutton>Apply
           </guibutton> and <guibutton>OK</guibutton> buttons will be disabled,
           indicating changes have been applied, until further changes are made.
         </para>

         <para>or</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
         <para>Click the <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button to close the
           options window without applying any unapplied changes.</para>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-common">
     <title>Common Report Options</title>

        <para>Many reports share similar options. Some common ones include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Report Name: Set the title of the report. This is also used to print the
             report for later viewing.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Date Options: Reports typically specify either a single date, or a date
             range, for the report. Dates can be specified in two ways, either directly
             (using the date selector), or by selecting a relative date from the menu.
             Relative dates allow you to specify dates like <guilabel>Beginning of this year</guilabel> or
             <guilabel>Today</guilabel>.</para>

            <tip><para>If you often run a report with a date as at the start or end
             of an accounting period, set the accounting period start and end
             dates in <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guisubmenu>
             Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Accounting Period
             </guimenuitem></menuchoice> then select appropriate report date
             options. See <xref linkend="prefs-accounting-period" />.</para>
		   </tip>

          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Step Size: This option is used on bar charts to determine the interval which
             each bar represents. Typical values are daily, weekly, monthly, and yearly.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Accounts: Select the appropriate accounts for the report. Note that in some
             reports only certain types of accounts can be selected. For example, an expense
             piechart only allows expense accounts to be selected. </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show Long Account Names: This option allows displaying either short account
             names (for example, Power) or long account names (for example, Utilities:Power).
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Include Subaccounts?: Summary reports typically have an include all
             subaccounts option, which if selected ensures that all subaccounts are included
             if the parent account is.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Depth: This option allows the selection of how many levels the report
             displays subaccounts. If the subaccounts go deeper than selected, an overall value
             for all the subaccounts is calculated and included in a total. To make sure every
             account selected is individually displayed, select <guibutton>All</guibutton>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Style Sheet: Select a Style Sheet. Style sheets control how reports are
             displayed. At the moment, there are four style sheets: <guilabel>Default</guilabel>, <guilabel>Easy</guilabel>,
             <guilabel>Footer</guilabel> and <guilabel>Technicolor</guilabel>.
             You can customize each of these from the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Style
             Sheets...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item.
             This is described in the <xref linkend="change-style"></xref><!--Changing Style Sheets--> section.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Plot Dimensions: There are width and height options for most charts, which
             specify the displayed dimensions (in pixels).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Report Currency: Select the report currency. Generally, values will be
             converted to this currency for display.</para>

            <para>The default Report Currency is defined in <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
              </menuchoice> Reports tab. See <xref linkend="prefs-reports" />.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Price Source: Select how stock and currency prices are calculated in this
             report. Choose between a weighted average of prices over all transactions, prices
             at current values, or prices at the time of the report date.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Totals: Charts display totals in the chart legend if this option is selected.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Maximum Slices: Controls the maximum number of slices displayed in a
             piechart - other accounts will be placed in a slice marked Other. </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Maximum Bars: Controls the maximum number of bars displayed in a barchart.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Display Columns: Choose columns to show from the register.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="report-classes">
   <title>Reports Listed By Class</title>

   <para><application>&app;</application> has classified the main types of
     reports into major classes. These
      are all available under the Reports menu.</para>

     <sect2 id="report-general">
      <title>General Reports</title>

      <para>The General Reports include the Account Summary Report, the Future
        Scheduled Transactions Summary, the Tax Schedule Report and <acronym>
        TXF</acronym> Export, and the Transaction Report and also the reports in the Sample &amp; Custom menu.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Account Summary</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Future Scheduled Transactions Summary</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="report-taxreport">
        <title>Tax Schedule Report and <acronym>TXF</acronym> Export</title>
        <para>The tax schedule report lists all taxable income and deductible expense amounts used in the preparation of US Income Tax returns. The purpose of the report is to provide a complete audit trail for these amounts. The report is intended to be used by a tax payer to manually prepare his or her own tax return, or alternatively, to be provided to a tax preparer for that purpose. The report can also be used to generate an export of all tax related income and expenses to a <acronym>TXF</acronym> (Tax eXchange Format) file (this is in addition to exporting to the <acronym>HTML</acronym> format that all reports allow). The <acronym>TXF</acronym> file can be imported into tax filing programs such as TaxCut or TurboTax. The report should be run, inspected carefully for errors or omissions, and then corrections made to transactions, report settings, currency conversion rates or the account structure as needed. This process should be repeated as often as needed until all the amounts on the report are correct before a final version is used and saved along with the tax returns.</para>

          <para> For accounts specified in the report options (none = all) that are also flagged as <guilabel>Tax-related</guilabel>, all transactions for the time period selected (also in the report options) are included. The report sorts transactions by date within account providing subtotals by account within tax code within Form or Schedule line number. Support is also provided for multiple copies of and for sub-line items for selected Forms/Schedules. Optionally uses special date processing to include federal estimated tax payments after year end.</para>

          <para>All totals are in USD since this is the currency required for filing US Income Tax returns. Non-USD transaction amounts are converted to USD using the transaction conversion rate to USD, if available. If not, a conversion rate from the price database is used (either the date nearest the transaction date or nearest the report date as specified in the report options; if none is available, transaction amounts are converted to zero and the report provides a comment accordingly). A complete audit trail of conversions is provided.</para>

          <note><para>For this to work, the user has to segregate taxable and non taxable
           income to different accounts, as well as deductible and non deductible expenses.
           The Income Tax Information dialog is used for this. To access the Income Tax
           Information dialog go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Tax Report Options</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The user
           also must set the <acronym>TXF</acronym> category of each tax related account. The Income Tax
           Information dialog is described in the <xref linkend="set-tax-options"></xref> section.</para></note>

      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Transaction Report</title>

        <para>This report lists transactions in selected accounts during a specified financial period. Two fields may be optionally
          used for sorting and totalling.
        </para>

        <sect4 id="report-txrpt-opts">
          <title>Report Options</title>

           <figure>
             <title><emphasis>Transaction Report &mdash; Report Options</emphasis></title>
             <screenshot id="Help_TxRptOpt_Screen">
               <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject role="html">
                   <imagedata fileref="figures/Help_TxRptOpt_Screen.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Geert Janssens" width="510px"></imagedata>
                 </imageobject>

                 <imageobject role="fo">
                   <imagedata fileref="figures/Help_TxRptOpt_Screen.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Geert Janssens" ></imagedata>
                 </imageobject>

                 <textobject><phrase>Transaction Report &mdash; Report Options screen</phrase>
                 </textobject>
                   <caption><para>This is an image of the <emphasis>Transaction Report &mdash; Report Options &mdash; Display tab.</emphasis></para>
                 </caption>
               </mediaobject>
             </screenshot>
           </figure>

           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para><emphasis>Accounts tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> &mdash; Select one or more accounts to be reported.</para>
                   <para>There are 4 buttons to aid account selection</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Select All</entry><entry>Select all accounts</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Clear All</entry> <entry>Clear the selection and unselect all accounts</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Select Children</entry><entry>Select all descendants of selected account</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Select Default</entry><entry>Select the default account selection</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Hidden Accounts</guilabel> &mdash; Show accounts that have been marked hidden.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Filter By</guilabel> &mdash; Optionally select accounts to be either included or
                   excluded depending on Filter type</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Hidden Accounts</guilabel> &mdash; Show accounts that have been
                   marked hidden in the Filter By list of accounts</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Filter Type</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not do any filtering</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Include Transactions to/from Filter Accounts</entry>
                           <entry>Include Transactions to/from Filter Accounts only</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Exclude Transactions to/from Filter Accounts</entry>
                           <entry>Exclude Transactions to/from all Filter Accounts</entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Void Transactions</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Non-void only</entry><entry>Show only non-voided transactions</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Void only</entry><entry>Show only voided transactions</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Both</entry><entry>Show both and include voided transactions in totals</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button</guilabel> &mdash; Reset all values to their defaults</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Display tab</emphasis></para>

               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Date</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reconciled Date</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Num</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Description</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Memo</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Notes</guilabel> &mdash; Display the notes if the memo is unavailable</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Account Name</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Use Full Account Name</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Account Code</guilabel></para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Other Account Name</guilabel> &mdash; For multi-split transactions, this parameter should be unticked. See below for more details.</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Use Full Other Account Name</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Other Account Code</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Shares</guilabel> &mdash; Display number of shares</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Price</guilabel> &mdash; Display share prices</para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Amount</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not display Amount</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Single</entry><entry>Single column display</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Double</entry><entry>Two column display</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Running Balance</guilabel></para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Totals</guilabel></para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sign Reverses</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not display signs reversed</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Credit Accounts</entry><entry>Reverse amount display for Liability, Payable, Equity, Credit Card and Income accounts</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Income and Expense</entry><entry>Reverse amount display for Income and Expense accounts</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button	Reset all values to their defaults</guilabel></para></listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>General tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report name</guilabel> &mdash; Enter a descriptive name for this report</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Stylesheet</guilabel> &mdash; Select Default, Easy, Footer or Technicolor</para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Start Date</guilabel> &mdash; Enter or select a specific Start Date</para>
                   <para>or 	select one of the following named start date options which will be used to	determine the start date each time the report is run
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Today</entry><entry>The current date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of this month</entry><entry>First day of the current month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of previous month</entry><entry>First day of the previous month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of current quarter</entry><entry>First day of the current quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of previous quarter</entry><entry>First day of the previous quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of this year</entry><entry>First day of the current calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of previous year</entry><entry>First day of the previous calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of accounting period</entry><entry>First day of the accounting period as defined in the global preferences</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>End Date</guilabel> &mdash; 	Enter or select a specific End Date,</para>
                   <para>or	select one of the following named end date options which will be used to determine the end date each time the report is run
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Today</entry><entry>The current date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of this month</entry><entry>Last day of the current month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of previous month</entry><entry>Last day of the previous month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of current quarter</entry><entry>Last day of the current quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of previous quarter</entry><entry>Last day of the previous quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of this year</entry><entry>Last day of the current calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of previous year</entry><entry>Last day of the previous calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of accounting period</entry><entry>Last day of the accounting period as defined in the global preferences</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Style</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Single</entry><entry>Display 1 line</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Multi-Line</entry><entry>Display N lines</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                   <note><para>In stable version 2.8.0, the <emphasis>Style</emphasis> option will be renamed to <emphasis>Detail Level</emphasis>
                     and moved to the Display tab.</para>
                   </note>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Common Currency</guilabel> &mdash; Convert all transactions into a common currency</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report's currency</guilabel> &mdash; Select the currency to display values</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Table for Exporting</guilabel> &mdash; Formats the table for cut &amp; paste exporting with extra cells</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button</guilabel> &mdash; Reset all values to their defaults</para></listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Sorting tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Key</guilabel> &mdash; Primary Sort Key. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not sort</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Account Name</entry><entry>Sort and subtotal by account name</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Account Code</entry><entry>Sort and subtotal by account code</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Date</entry><entry>Sort by date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Exact Time</entry><entry>Sort by exact time</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Reconciled Date</entry><entry>Sort by the reconciled date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Register Order</entry><entry>Sort as within the register</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Other Account Name</entry><entry>Sort by account transferred from/to's name</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Other Account Code</entry><entry>Sort by account transferred from/to's code</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Amount</entry><entry>Sort by amount</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Description</entry><entry>Sort by description</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Number</entry><entry>Sort by check/transaction number</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Memo</entry><entry>Sort by memo</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Full Account Name</guilabel> &mdash; Show the full account name for subtotals and subtitles</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Account Code</guilabel> &mdash; Show the account code for subtotals and subtitles</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Subtotal</guilabel> &mdash; Subtotal according to the primary key</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Subtotal for Date Key</guilabel> &mdash; Do a date subtotal. Only configurable if primary key is date, exact time or register order.
                   One of None, weekly, monthly, quarterly or yearly</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Sort Order</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Ascending</entry><entry>Smallest to largest, earliest to latest</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Descending</entry><entry>Largest to smallest, latest to earliest</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Key</guilabel> &mdash; Secondary Sort Key. Same options as Primary Key</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Subtotal</guilabel> &mdash; Subtotal according to the secondary key</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Subtotal for Date Key</guilabel> &mdash; Do a date subtotal. Only configurable if primary key is date, exact time or register order.
                   One of None, weekly, monthly, quarterly or yearly</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Sort Order</guilabel> &mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Ascending</entry><entry>Smallest to largest, earliest to latest</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Descending</entry><entry>Largest to smallest, latest to earliest</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button</guilabel> &mdash; Reset all values to their defaults</para></listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="report-txrpt-splits">
          <title>Displaying Split Account Details</title>
          <para>This is controled by the <emphasis>Style</emphasis> option on the General tab.</para>
          <note>
           <para>In stable version 2.8.0 this option will be renamed to <emphasis>Detail Level</emphasis> on the Display tab.</para>
          </note>
          <para>In <emphasis>Single</emphasis> line mode, there's only one line per transaction. So you can have
            the account name on one side of the equation and
          </para>

          <para>a. the other account name if there's only one other split in the transaction</para>

          <para>or</para>

          <para>b. "Split" if there are multiple other splits in the transaction. You can't
            display multiple "other" account names in one line. There's just no room for it.
          </para>

          <para>In the case of <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis> mode, this report uses a completely different concept.
            For each transaction, every split (both the split in this account and the
            split(s) in the other account(s) !) is printed on a separate line. And every
            split really means every split:  both the split which belongs in the account
            being reported and the split(s) in the other account(s) that balance the
            transaction. So even the most basic transaction, with only two splits (this
            account and other account) will print two lines in multiline mode.
          </para>

          <para>For a simple transaction like this</para>
          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis>Description</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Account</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Debit</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Credit</emphasis></entry>
                </row>
                <row><entry>Cheques Received</entry></row>
                <row><entry>"multiple payers"</entry><entry>IncomeAccount</entry><entry></entry><entry>£30.00</entry></row>
                <row><entry></entry><entry>BankAccount</entry><entry>£30.00</entry><entry></entry></row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>

          <para>then on a Transaction Report for the bank account the details appear pretty much as above.</para>

          <para>For clarity of the accounts, you might enter transactions with multiple splits referring to the same
            account. For example, the above transaction might well be entered like this
          </para>

          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis>Description</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Account</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Debit</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Credit</emphasis></entry>
                </row>
                <row><entry>Cheques Received</entry></row>
                <row><entry>"FirstPayer"</entry><entry>IncomeAccount</entry><entry></entry><entry>£10.00</entry></row>
                <row><entry>"SecondPayer"</entry><entry>IncomeAccount</entry><entry></entry><entry>£20.00</entry></row>
                <row><entry></entry><entry>BankAccount</entry><entry>£30.00</entry><entry></entry></row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>

          <para>When this transaction is printed on the bank account's Transaction Report in <emphasis>Single</emphasis> line mode, then
            under <emphasis>other account</emphasis> it simply prints the word <emphasis>split</emphasis> instead of the account name.
          </para>

          <para>To display the additional split detail, you need to set <emphasis>Single/Multi-Line</emphasis> to
            <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis> and then tick <emphasis>Display</emphasis> -> <emphasis>Account Name</emphasis>.
            Do NOT tick <emphasis>Display</emphasis> -> <emphasis>Other Account Name</emphasis>.
          </para>

          <para>You can choose whether or not to turn off the full account name using <emphasis>Display</emphasis> ->
            <emphasis>Use Full Account Name.</emphasis></para>

          <para><emphasis>Use Full Other Account Name</emphasis> has no effect in <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis> mode.</para>

        </sect4>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-assets">
    <title>Assets &amp; Liabilities</title>

     <para>The Assets &amp; Liabilities reports includes the Balance Sheet
       report, Investment reports and the Net Worth report.</para>

      <itemizedlist>

       <listitem>
        <para>Advanced Portfolio:</para>

        <para>Columns</para>
          <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Account</guilabel> &mdash; Stock Account</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Symbol</guilabel> &mdash; Ticker Symbol/Abbreviation as defined in the Security Editor. A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Listing</guilabel> &mdash; Type as defined in the Security Editor. A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Shares</guilabel> &mdash; Number of shares           (quantity). A report option sets how many decimal places to show.
	    A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Price</guilabel> &mdash; Unit market price as at report date. A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Basis</guilabel> &mdash; Cost of all shares acquired by any means, including brokerage fees if the option to include them is checked. Report option <emphasis>Basis calculation method</emphasis> can be set to Average, LIFO or FIFO.</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Value</guilabel> &mdash; Number of shares * Unit market price as at report date</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Money In</guilabel> &mdash; Sum of the cost of stock purchased, excluding stock acquired as part of a Dividend Reinvestment Plan. I.e. External money used to purchase shares.</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Money Out</guilabel> &mdash; Money from selling shares or a spin off transaction.</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Realized Gain</guilabel> &mdash; Money received for selling shares minus basis for shares sold, minus brokerage fees for the sale if the option to include them in basis is checked.</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Unrealized Gain</guilabel> &mdash; Value less Basis for unsold shares</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Total Gain</guilabel> &mdash; Realized Gain + Unrealized Gain</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Rate of Gain</guilabel> &mdash; Total Gain / Money In * 100 (from <application>&app;</application> 2.6.1 onwards)</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Income</guilabel> &mdash; Total of all income transactions associated with a stock account.</para>
              <note>
                <para>To include income from dividends which are not reinvested (if there is no split to the stock account in the income transaction, the report has no way of associating the income with a particular stock) :
                </para>
		<para>Ensure there is a dummy transaction split to the stock         account with quantity 0, price 1 and value 0 in the dividend transaction. Enter the dummy stock split with no values in the dividend account and it will create the transaction with price 1 even though you cannot see the Price column in that register.
		</para>
                <para>In GnuCash 2.6.6, this report was modified to simplify the recording of dividend and interest payments. With this
                change it may not be necessary to include the dummy stock split in the transaction. The report will find income (and expense) transactions that are in the parent account of the stock account being reported on. This is done by looking in the parent account for transactions that have exactly two splits (not counting trading account splits) where the other split is to an income or expense account with the same name as the stock's account.
                </para>
                <para>For example given an account structure like
                </para>
                <literallayout>
                Assets (type ASSET)
                  Broker (type ASSET)
                    Widget Stock (type STOCK)
                Income (type INCOME)
                  Dividends (type INCOME)
                    Widget Stock (type INCOME)
                </literallayout>
                <para>A transaction that debits the "Assets:Broker" account and credits the "Income:Dividends:Widget Stock" account will count as income even though it doesn't have a split with account "Assets:Broker:Widget Stock".
                </para>
                <para>This only works if the parent account ("Assets:Broker" in this case) is a Bank or Asset account and the Income/Expense account has the same name as the stock account. It won't double count transactions that have a dummy split since they won't have exactly two split transactions.
                </para>
                <para>It will not work if the income or expense account split is to a subaccount of the account with the same name as the stock account i.e. "Income:Dividends:Widget Stock:Franked"
                </para>
	      </note>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Brokerage Fees</guilabel> &mdash; Brokerage Fees</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Total Return</guilabel> &mdash; Total Gain + Income</para>
	    </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Rate of Return</guilabel> &mdash; Total Return / Money In * 100</para>
	    </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>

        <para>Common report options are described in <xref linkend="report-config"/></para>

        <para>Report Specific Options</para>

        <itemizedlist>	<!-- list of Tabs -->

          <listitem><para>Accounts Tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Include accounts with no shares</guilabel> &mdash; Unchecked (default) or checked.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>	<!-- end of Accounts Tab -->

          <listitem><para>Display Tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show ticker symbols</guilabel> &mdash; Checked default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Symbol column will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show listings</guilabel> &mdash; Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Listing column (source of shares price quotes) will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show number of shares</guilabel> &mdash; Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Shares column will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Share decimal places</guilabel> &mdash; The number of decimal places to show in the number of shares. Default is 2.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show prices</guilabel> &mdash; Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Price column will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>	<!-- end of Display Tab -->

          <listitem><para>General Tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Price Source</guilabel> &mdash; Nearest in time (default) or Most Recent.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Basis calculation method</guilabel> &mdash; Average (default), FIFO or LIFO.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Set preference for price list data</guilabel> &mdash; Checked (default): Use price list data. If there is no relevant price list data, transaction prices will be used and there will be a warning. Unchecked: Get prices from stock transactions.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>How to report brokerage fees</guilabel> &mdash; Include in basis (default), Include in gain or Ignore.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Asset Barchart:</para>

        <para>The Asset Barchart report displays bars that present the value of all assets in a
        <application>&app;</application> file over time.  By default, the report shows all accounts
        in <emphasis>Accounts Receivable</emphasis>, <emphasis>Current Assets</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>Fixed Assets</emphasis>, <emphasis>Investments</emphasis> and Special Accounts
        (if they exist) and it displays monthly bars for the current financial period.
        This report provides a graphic view of the assets in the file over time.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>Like all the generic reports, the user can assign a title and save the report with
          it's selected options for re-use later.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>The display is in the form of either a stacked barchart or simple barchart with an
        option to display a table of the values.</para>

        <para>This report calculates and displays a default of 8 bars or up to 24 separate asset
        accounts value at the end of the day on several dates through a specified time period.
        The report automatically selects the most significant accounts to display with all other
        selected accounts summed as <emphasis>Other</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>The report exploits the outline structure of the chart of accounts to allow the user
        to select top level accounts and sub-accounts down to a user-selectable depth.  Selected
        sub-accounts below the selected depth are automatically <emphasis>summed up</emphasis> into
        the next level when it is also selected.  The default number of sub-account levels is 2,
        giving a summary view.  Increasing the number of sub-levels increases the detail available
        to display. It is possible to un-select a higher level account and leave sub-accounts
        selected to force greater detail to appear in the report.</para>

        <para>By default the report includes all <emphasis>asset</emphasis> accounts and sub-accounts,
        as well as <emphasis>Imbalance</emphasis> and <emphasis>Orphan</emphasis> Special accounts
        in whatever currencies or commodities may be present. The report's base currency is the
        default currency of the <application>&app;</application> file but if the file has data
        for multiple currencies, then it can be changed to another currency.</para>

        <para>Since each account may be individually selected, the report can be designed to focus
        on a small subset of data such as current assets or investments.</para>

        <para>The overall interval of the report defaults to start at the start of the current
        accounting period and to end at the end of the current accounting period. Numerous
        other starting choices and ending choices are available.</para>

        <para>The first bar shows the selected values at the end of the day on the first date chosen.
        There are a number of choices for step size from <emphasis>day</emphasis> to
        <emphasis>year</emphasis> with the default being <emphasis>month</emphasis>. Note that if any
        step date would fall on the 29th, 30th or 31st in a month that does not have such a date
        the next interval will be 31 days later. For that step only the date will <emphasis>slip</emphasis>
        up to 3 days into the following month. This is true for releases at least through 2.4.13.
        Bug 639049 is open in Bugzilla to modify this behavior.</para>

        <para>Currently, there is no option to start the report on the last day of any period.
        There is also no option to show <emphasis>beginning</emphasis> balances or <emphasis>end of
        previous step</emphasis> balances. This makes it difficult to correlate this report to
        business quarterly reports, for example.</para>

        <para>The Net Worth linechart report, Liability barchart report and Net Worth barchart
        report are similar except for the graphic type and default account groups selected.</para>

       <para>Other features are customizable in a manner similar to other standard reports.</para>

       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Asset Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Average Balance:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Balance Sheet: This report summarizes assets, liabilities, and equity.
         When properly maintained, assets should equal the sum of liabilities and equity.
         If that is not the case, there is some kind of internal imbalance in the
         accounts.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Balance Sheet using eguile-gnc:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>General Journal:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>General Ledger:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Investment Portfolio: This report summarizes the value of the stocks in
         the current portfolio.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Liability Barchart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Liability Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Net Worth Barchart: Net worth is the difference between the value of assets
         or liabilities.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Net Worth Linechart: Net worth plotted over time.  Net worth is the difference between the value of assets
         or liabilities.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Price Scatterplot:</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-biz">
    <title>Business Reports</title>

      <para>The Business Reports includes Customer and Vendor Reports and Printable
       Invoices as well as Aging reports.</para>

       <sect3>
        <title>Customer Report</title>
        <para> </para>
       </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Customer Summary</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Easy Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Employee Report</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Fancy Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Job Report</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Payable Aging</title>
         <para>This report provides a listing of vendors and their aged
           outstanding balances. Vendors may be included if they have posted
           business transactions (e.g. invoices) for the selected accounts payable
           account. It shows their current balance, and how much they have
           due from invoices over time periods 0-30 days, 31-60 days,
           61-90 days, and over 90 days. The report also contains links to each
           vendor and to their current vendor report.
         </para>
         <para>Optionally, vendor address details may be also shown.</para>

         <tip><para>To export vendor address details, say in order to do a mail
           merge, select the optional vendor address details in the report options
           display tab, apply the options to regenerate the report, then copy and
           paste the report into a spreadsheet. Alternatively, the report can be
           exported to a .html file, then read into a spreadsheet.</para>
         </tip>

         <sect4 id="report-pay-aging-opts">
           <title>Report Options</title>

           <note><para>See <emphasis>Common Report Options</emphasis> in the
             <emphasis>Configuring Reports and Charts</emphasis> section of this
             help manual for more details of the common options.
             </para>
           </note>

           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para><emphasis>General tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel> Report name</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Enter a descriptive name for this report - see common report
                   options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Stylesheet</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Select a style sheet for this report - see common report
                   options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>To</guilabel> &mdash; Select a date
                   to report on or a named date. Transactions up to and
                   including the selected date will be used to calculate the
                   outstanding aged balances. See common report options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report's currency</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Select the currency to display the values in - see common
                   report options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Price Source</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Select the source of price information used for currency
                   conversion if needed. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Average Cost</entry><entry>The
                           volume-weighted average cost of purchases</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Weighted Average (default)</entry><entry>
                           The weighted average of all currency transactions
                           in the past</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Most recent</entry><entry>The most recent
                           recorded price</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Nearest in time</entry><entry>The price
                           recorded nearest in time to the report date</entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Multi-currency Totals</guilabel>
                    &mdash; If not selected, all totals are shown in the report
                   currency.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort By</guilabel> &mdash; Sort
                   companies by one of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Name (default)</entry><entry>Company name
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Total Owed</entry><entry>Total amount owed
                           to company</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Bracket Total Owed</entry><entry>Amount
                           owed in oldest bracket. If same, use next oldest
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort Order</guilabel> &mdash; One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Increasing (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Decreasing</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show zero balance items</guilabel>
                   &mdash; Show companies even if they have a zero outstanding
                   balance.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Due or Post Date</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Leading date. Which date to use to determine aging. One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Due Date (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Post Date</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Payable Account</guilabel> &mdash;
                   The accounts payable account used to select vendors to be
                   reported. Vendors are included if they have a posted
                   business transaction (usually an invoice) on or before the
                   report date and also meet the <emphasis>Show zero balance
                   items</emphasis> criteria.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Display tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address Name</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Display vendor address name. This, and other fields, may be
                   useful if copying this report to a spreadsheet for use in a
                   mail merge.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 1</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 1.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 2</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 2.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 3</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 3.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 4</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 4.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Phone</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address phone number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Fax</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address fax number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Email</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   email address.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Active</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   vendor active status.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>

        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Printable Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Receivable Aging</title>
         <para>This report provides a listing of customers and their aged
           outstanding balances. Customers may be included if they have posted
           business transactions (e.g. invoices) for the selected accounts receivable
           account. It shows their current balance, and how much they have
           outstanding from invoices over time periods 0-30 days, 31-60 days,
           61-90 days, and over 90 days. The report also contains links to each
           customer and to their current customer report.
         </para>
         <para>Optionally, customer address details may be also shown.</para>

         <tip><para>To export customer address details, say in order to do a mail
           merge, select the optional customer address details in the report options
           display tab, apply the options to regenerate the report, then copy and
           paste the report into a spreadsheet. Alternatively, the report can be
           exported to a .html file, then read into a spreadsheet.</para>
         </tip>

         <sect4 id="report-rec-aging-opts">
           <title>Report Options</title>

           <note><para>See <emphasis>Common Report Options</emphasis> in the
             <emphasis>Configuring Reports and Charts</emphasis> section of this
             help manual for more details of the common options.
             </para>
           </note>

           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para><emphasis>General tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel> Report name</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Enter a descriptive name for this report - see common report
                   options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Stylesheet</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Select a style sheet for this report - see common report
                   options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>To</guilabel> &mdash; Select a date
                   to report on or a named date. Transactions up to and
                   including the selected date will be used to calculate the
                   outstanding aged balances. See common report options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report's currency</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Select the currency to display the values in - see common
                   report options.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Price Source</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Select the source of price information used for currency
                   conversion if needed. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Average Cost</entry><entry>The
                           volume-weighted average cost of purchases</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Weighted Average (default)</entry><entry>
                           The weighted average of all currency transactions
                           in the past</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Most recent</entry><entry>The most recent
                           recorded price</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Nearest in time</entry><entry>The price
                           recorded nearest in time to the report date</entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Multi-currency Totals</guilabel>
                    &mdash; If not selected, all totals are shown in the report
                   currency.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort By</guilabel> &mdash; Sort
                   companies by one of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Name (default)</entry><entry>Company name
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Total Owed</entry><entry>Total amount owed
                           by company</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Bracket Total Owed</entry><entry>Amount
                           owed in oldest bracket. If same, use next oldest
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort Order</guilabel> &mdash; One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Increasing (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Decreasing</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show zero balance items</guilabel>
                   &mdash; Show companies even if they have a zero outstanding
                   balance.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Due or Post Date</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Leading date. Which date to use to determine aging. One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Due Date (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Post Date</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Receivables Account</guilabel> &mdash;
                   The accounts receivable account used to select customers to be
                   reported. Customers are included if they have a posted
                   business transaction (usually an invoice) on or before the
                   report date and also meet the <emphasis>Show zero balance
                   items</emphasis> criteria.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Display tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address Source</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Which customer address fields to display. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Billing (default)</entry><entry>Address fields from
                           billing address.</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Shipping</entry><entry>Address fields from
                           shipping address.</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address Name</guilabel> &mdash;
                   Display customer address name. This, and other fields, may be
                   useful if copying this report to a spreadsheet for use in a
                   mail merge.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 1</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 1.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 2</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 2.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 3</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 3.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 4</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address line 4.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Phone</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address phone number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Fax</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   address fax number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Email</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   email address.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Active</guilabel> &mdash; Display
                   vendor active status.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>

        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Tax Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Vendor Report</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

     </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-income">
    <title>Income &amp; Expense</title>

     <para>The Income &amp; Expense reports includes the Cash Flow and Income Statement reports.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>Cash Flow:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Equity Statement:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Expense Barchart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Expense Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Expense vs Day of Week:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income &amp; Expense Chart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income Barchart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income Statement: This report summarizes sources of income and expenditure.
         (This report was called Profit &amp; Loss in gnucash-1.8.)</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income vs Day of Week:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Profit &amp; Loss: This is the same report as the Income Statement but with a different title.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Trial Balance: This report summarizes sources of income and expenditure.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

    <sect2 id="report-sample">
      <title>Sample &amp; Custom</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Welcome Sample Report</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Custom Multicolumn Report</title>
        <para>This report is used to place multiple reports
           into a single report window to examine a set of financial information at a glance.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Sample Report with Examples</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-budget">
     <title>Budget</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Balance Sheet</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Barchart</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Flow</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Income Statement</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Profit &amp; Loss</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Report</title>
	<para>This report is used to compare budgeted and real amounts for selected accounts. It allows you to review how well you follow the budget.</para>
	<para>The report is generated as a table in which each row represents an account and each set of columns shows the <emphasis>budgeted amount</emphasis>, the <emphasis>real amount</emphasis>, and the <emphasis>difference</emphasis> between them for each report period.</para>
	<para>Each entry in the <emphasis>real amount</emphasis> column is the sum of all the splits in the row's account over the column's period. For example, if the report is set up for monthly periods, the column is for May, and the row is for Expences:Groceries, then the value will be the sum of all Expenses:Groceries splits for that May.</para>
	<para>The report supports selecting a range of periods instead all of them. Periods that are out of range can be included in report as the consolidated columns around the selected range. This allows you to focus on particular periods, for example the current one, and is especially useful for budgets with many periods. For example, if you have a 12 period budget you can make a 3 column report with the format "(all periods before columns set) (current period columns set) (all periods after columns set)" that is easily fits on the screen and allows you to match values with account names.</para>
	<para><emphasis>Budget report options</emphasis></para>
	<para>
	  <note><para>Here we describe only options that are specific for the Budget Report. You can find information about standard parameters in <xref linkend="report-config"/>.</para> </note>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Show budget</emphasis> - include the budgeted values for the period</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Show actual</emphasis> - include the real values for the period</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Show difference</emphasis> - include the difference between budgeted and real values for the period. Enabling this option does not force including budgeted and actual values in report</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Show Column with totals</emphasis> - Adds a final column set containing budgeted, real value, and difference columns summing those values across all periods of the report.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Rollup budget amounts to parent</emphasis> - not used in report, can be deleted or should be fixed</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Include accounts with zero total balances and budget values</emphasis> - enables display of accounts with no budget or splits in any period.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Budget</emphasis> - Select the budget to use for report generation</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Report for range of budget periods</emphasis> - Enables reporting on a subset of the budget by selecting a beginning and an ending period.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Range start</emphasis> - a combobox with a list of variants how to select start period:
	    <orderedlist>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>First</emphasis> - select first budget period</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Previous</emphasis> - select previous period.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Current</emphasis> - select current period.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Next</emphasis>  - select next period.</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Last</emphasis> - select last budget period</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para><emphasis>Manual</emphasis> - enables spinbox where you can select exact period</para></listitem>
	    </orderedlist></para>
	    <note><para>The <emphasis>current</emphasis>, <emphasis>previous</emphasis>, and <emphasis>next</emphasis> options select the period based on the date on which the report is run, with <emphasis>current</emphasis> being the period in which the date falls, <emphasis>previous</emphasis> being the one before that, and <emphasis>next</emphasis> the period after. If the current date falls outside the date range covered by the budget, the <emphasis>first</emphasis> or <emphasis>last</emphasis> period will be used as appropriate.</para></note>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Exact start period</emphasis> - options for select exact start period, enabled only if range start option is set to <emphasis>Manual</emphasis></para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Range end</emphasis> - a combobox with a list of variants how to select end period. Values are the same as in <emphasis>Range start</emphasis> options</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Exact end period</emphasis> - the same as <emphasis>Exact start period</emphasis> but for the end of range</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Include collapsed periods before selected</emphasis> - if on, then includes in report all budget periods, that are before selected period range, as a single consolidated column set</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para><emphasis>Include collapsed periods after selected</emphasis> - if on, then includes in report all budget periods, that are after selected period range, as a single consolidated column set.</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="report-print">
     <title>Printing or Exporting Reports and Charts</title>

       <note><para> Verify !!!  How customize printing with Gnome?</para></note>

     <para><application>&app;</application> is able to print reports and to export the reports to <acronym>HTML</acronym> (web) pages. The
       Print <application>&app;</application> Document dialog is accessed from the <guibutton>Print</guibutton> button on the <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> or
       go to <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the menu. To Export a report to a web page (<acronym>HTML</acronym>) select
       the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button on the <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> and type in a file name.</para>

     <para>Most reports, being presented in HTML, can also be copied and pasted into a spreadsheet.</para>

     <para>The Print <application>&app;</application> Document dialog is used to select which Printer to send the
       print job to or to print to a File. It also contains a Preview button to view the
       document before printing. Press Print to send the job to the selected printer or
       <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> to dismiss the Print dialog.</para>


       <para>Printing from an open register prints the Account Report, which is also called
         the Register Report. This lists transactions in the account with a total. Other
         reports print as viewed in the Report screen.</para>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="report-create">
     <title>Creating Reports and Charts</title>

     <note><para>This section may need updating !!!</para> </note>

     <para>It is possible to write reports if the current ones are not suitable. To do this
       you will need to know Scheme (a LISP-like programming language), and it is an
       excellent idea to have a copy of the <application>&app;</application> source code available. </para>

     <para>The reporting interface is documented in the source code file
       <filename>src/report/report-system/doc/report-html.txt</filename>.
       The file <filename>src/report/utility-reports/hello-world.scm</filename>
       in the <application>&app;</application> source distribution provides a
       good example of how reports are developed.</para>

     <sect2 id="report-api">
       <title>Accessing the <application>&app;</application> <acronym>API</acronym></title>

       <para>It is also necessary to access data from the engine to get
         information for your report. This is
         <emphasis>since version 2.1.x</emphasis> performed by a set of
         Scheme wrapper functions that are documented in the file
         <filename>src/engine/swig-engine.c</filename>.
         <emphasis>Up to version 2.0.5</emphasis> it was
         <filename>src/g-wrap/gnc.html</filename>. Examine some of the other
         reports in src/scm/report for an indication of how they are used.</para>

       <para>Some users started a table in the <application>&app;</application> wiki
         <ulink url="http://wiki.gnucash.org/wiki/Custom_Reports#The_GnuCash_API">
         Custom Reports#The GnuCash API</ulink>.
       </para>

	   <para>Because the above file only contains the syntax of the function
		 you can use the Doxygen source documentation either local after running
<screen>
./configure --enable-doxygen --enable-html-docs
make doc
</screen> on your sources or online
		 <ulink url="http://code.gnucash.org/docs/MAINT/">http://code.gnucash.org/docs/MAINT/</ulink> or
		 <ulink url="http://code.gnucash.org/docs/MASTER/">http://code.gnucash.org/docs/MASTER/</ulink>
		 to get more information about the functions.
	   </para>
     </sect2>

     <sect2 id="report-render">
       <title>Report Rendering</title>
       <para>At present, reports are produced by calling a <acronym>HTML</acronym>-generation API, which outputs
         a dialect of <acronym>HTML</acronym> and rendering this with a <acronym>HTML</acronym> widget. This has limitations,
         particularly when trying to align objects precisely, as might be necessary for
         printing onto pre-printed invoices for example.</para>
       </sect2>
     </sect1>

</chapter>
