<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-locale-pt.dtd">
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.0
  Last modified: July 9th 2006
  Maintainers: 
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Author:
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
	updated Patrick Schweiger <pks@spiffykitty.com>
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<!--
A lot of the following text is duplicated in the GnuCash help. The text here in the guide should be 
corrected to be less describing of the interface and more tutorial oriented
-->
<chapter id="chapter_bus_ar">
  <title>Accounts Receivable</title>

  <para>Accounts Receivable (or A/R) refers to products or services provided by your company for which
    payment has not yet been received.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-setup1">
    <title>Initial Setup</title>

    <para>Perform set up tasks listed in <xref linkend="chapter_bus_setup" />.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-components1">
    <title>System Components</title>

    <para>&app; has an integrated accounts receivable system. The transactions generated by the A/R system are
      recorded within the Accounts Receivable account. You generally do not work directly with this
      account. You generally work with the four integrated &app; A/R application components
      available through the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Business</guimenu> <guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu>
      </menuchoice>
      sub-menu. These four components are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Customers</guilabel> are people or companies to whom you sell products or services on
          credit.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Invoices</guilabel> represent the physical invoice you send to a customer to request
          payment. This invoice contains an itemized list of things you sold.
        </para>

        <para>In addition, GnuCash also has support for <guilabel>Credit Notes</guilabel> which represent the
          inverse of Invoices. A credit note is usually handed to a customer to correct items that
          were incorrectly invoiced or returned.
        </para>

        <para>Both document types will be set up using the same menu items. Credit notes were introduced starting
          with &app; stable release 2.6.0.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Jobs</guilabel> (optional) is where you register Customer Jobs. Jobs are a mechanism by
          which you can group multiple invoices to a particular customer.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><guilabel>Process Payments</guilabel> is used to register payments you received from a customer.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-customers1">
    <title>Customers</title>

    <para>Customers are people or companies to whom you sell goods or services. They must be registered within
      the A/R system.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-custnew2">
      <title>New</title>

      <para>To register a new customer, enter the menu
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Business</guimenu><guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu> <guimenuitem>New
          Customer</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        . Fill in customer information, such as Company Name, Address, Phone, Fax, etc.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="bus-ar-custnew">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_custnew.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>New Customer Registration Window</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>New Customer Registration Window
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-custfind2">
      <title>Find and Edit</title>

      <para>To search for an existing customer, use the
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Business</guimenu><guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu> <guimenuitem>Find
          Customer</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        window. You select a customer to <guilabel>View/Edit</guilabel> from the results of the
        search. This window is also used to look up customers when creating invoices and processing
        payments.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="bus-ar-custfind">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_custfind.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Find Customer Window</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Find Customer Window
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>If many customers match the search criteria you provide, the search can be refined by running an
        additional search within the current results. The current result set is searched when the
        <guilabel>Refine Current Search</guilabel> radio button is selected. In fact, &app; selects
        this option for you after you run the initial search.
      </para>

      <para>If the customer you are searching for does not match the supplied search criteria, change the search
        criteria, click the <guilabel>New Search</guilabel> radio button and then the
        <guilabel>Find</guilabel> button. The relevant step is the <guilabel>New Search</guilabel>
        selection. If the customer is not in the result of the original search, and you only search
        within this set, the customer cannot be found, regardless of new search criteria.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>To return a list of all registered active customers, set the search criterion to <guilabel>matches
          regex</guilabel>, and place a single dot "." in the text field area. Make sure
          <guilabel>Search only active data</guilabel> is checked, then click
          <guibutton>Find</guibutton>. The regular expression "." means to match anything.
        </para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-invoices1">
    <title>Invoices</title>

    <para>An invoice is the paperwork you send to a customer to request payment for products or services
      rendered. &app; can generate and track invoices.
    </para>

    <para>A credit note is the paperwork you send to a customer to correct products or services rendered that
      were incorrectly invoiced. &app; can generate and track credit notes via the same menu entries
      as invoices.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>This section applies to both invoices and credit notes. In order to avoid repeating everything twice
        and to keep the text easier to read it will refer only to invoices. You can apply it equally
        to credit notes. Only where the behaviour of credit notes differs from invoices this will be
        explicitly mentioned.
      </para>
    </note>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-invoicenew2">
      <title>New</title>

      <para>To send an invoice to a customer you must first create the new document. To create an invoice use
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Business</guimenu> <guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>New
          Invoice</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        . The New Invoice window must be filled in appropriately.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoicenew">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoicenew.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Creating a New Invoice</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Creating a New Invoice
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>When you click the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button, the <guilabel>Edit Invoice</guilabel> window
        opens.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-invoiceedit2">
      <title>Edit</title>

      <para>From the Edit Invoice window you can enter an itemized list of goods and services you sold on this
        invoice in a manner similar to how the account register works. For credit notes you enter an
        itemized list of goods and services you refunded instead.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoiceedit">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoiceedit.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Edit Invoice Window</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Edit Invoice Window
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>When you have finished entering all the items, you can <guilabel>Post</guilabel> and print the
        invoice.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-invoicepost2">
      <title>Post</title>

      <para>When you finish editing an invoice and are ready to print, you must <guilabel>Post</guilabel> the
        invoice. The invoice does not have to be posted immediately. In fact, you should only post
        an invoice when you are ready to print it. Posting an invoice places the transactions in an
        accounts receivable account.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoicepost">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoicepost.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Post Invoice Window</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Post Invoice Window
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-invoicefind2">
      <title>Find</title>

      <para>To find an existing invoice, use the
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Business</guimenu> <guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Find
          Invoice</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        menu item. From the results of the search, you can select an invoice to edit or view.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>Before you can edit a posted invoice, you will need to <guilabel>Unpost</guilabel> it.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>One of the design goals in &app;&rsquo;s Account Receivable system was to allow different processes
        to get to the same state, so you can reach an invoice from different directions based on the
        way you think about the problem:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can search for the customer first, then list their invoices.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can search for invoices by number or by company name.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can list invoices associated with a customer job.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-invoiceprint2">
      <title>Print</title>

      <para>After you post an invoice, you should print it and send it to your customer. To print an invoice use
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Print Invoice</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        menu item.
      </para>

      <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoiceprint">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoiceprint.png" format="PNG"
                       srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
          </imageobject>

          <textobject>
            <phrase>Invoice Print Output</phrase>
          </textobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Invoice Print Output
            </para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <note>
        <para>You can modify the appearance of the invoice, IE: add a company logo, etc. To do so, see the
          <xref
        linkend="bus-ar-invoicechange" />.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>Invoices can also be printed from the main window by selecting
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guisubmenu>Business Reports</guisubmenu> <guimenuitem>Printable
          Invoice</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        from the main menu. The resulting report window states that no valid invoice is selected. To
        select the invoice to print:
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the <guibutton>Options</guibutton> <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> button or select
            <menuchoice>
              <guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Report Options</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            from the main menu.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Select the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab of the report options dialog.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the <guibutton>Select</guibutton> button next to the <guilabel>Invoice Number</guilabel>
            field.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for the invoice as usual.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>You can also print invoices from within the Process Payment dialog. See the
        <xref linkend="bus-ar-payment1" /> for instructions on how to do so.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="bus-ar-invoicestarting2">
      <title>Assign Starting Invoice Number</title>

      <para>By default, &app; starts with invoice number 1 and increments from there. You can manually type an
        invoice number into the text box each time you create an invoice, but this gets tiring and
        sooner or later leads to duplicate numbers.
      </para>

      <para>You can change the starting invoice number if it is important you. Use
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        , access the <guilabel>Counters</guilabel> tab, change the <guilabel>Invoice
        number</guilabel> value to be one less than your desired starting invoice number and click
        the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button or the <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-jobs1">
    <title>Customer Jobs</title>

    <para>Customer Jobs are used to group multiple invoices and credit notes to the same customer. Use of the
      Customer Jobs feature is optional. The feature is useful when you have multiple
      <guilabel>jobs</guilabel> for the same customer, and would like to view all the invoices and
      credit notes related to a single job.
    </para>

    <screenshot id="bus-ar-jobnew">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_jobnew.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>New Customer Job</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>New Customer Job
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>To use customer jobs, you must create them using the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Business</guimenu><guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu> <guimenuitem>New
        Job</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      menu item. You will see the <guilabel>New Job</guilabel> window.
    </para>

    <para>To edit an existing customer job, use the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Business</guimenu><guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu> <guimenuitem>Find
        Job</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      menu item. Select the desired job in the search results, and click the <guilabel>View/Edit
      Job</guilabel> button.
    </para>

    <para>To select from the invoices and credit notes associated with a given job, use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Business</guimenu><guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Find
        Job</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      menu item. Select the desired job in the search results and click the <guilabel>View
      Invoices</guilabel> button. A window listing invoices and credit notes associated with this
      job appears. Select an invoice or credit note and click the <guilabel>View Invoice</guilabel>
      button to open an invoice editor in the main application window.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-payment1">
    <title>Process Payment</title>

    <para>Eventually, you will receive payment from your customers for outstanding invoices. To register these
      payments, use the Process Payment application found in
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Business</guimenu> <guisubmenu>Customer</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Process
        Payment</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      .
    </para>

    <screenshot id="bus-ar-payment">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_payment.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>Process Payment</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>Process Payment Window
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bus-ar-invoicechange">
    <title>Changing the Invoice Appearance</title>

    <para>The default Invoice style, as shown in <xref
    linkend="bus-ar-invoiceprint2" />, is fairly
      barren. The default invoice style leaves the top part of the form blank, so you can print on
      company letterhead paper. There are some things you can do to change invoice appearance.
    </para>

    <para>Use
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      to enter your Company informations in the <guilabel>Business</guilabel> tab of the
      <guilabel>Book Options</guilabel> window. Some of the entered informations are printed on the
      right side of invoices.
    </para>

    <para>To add a customized background, heading banner or logo to invoices, modify the invoice style sheets.
      To do this, go to
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Style Sheets</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      and select the <guibutton>New</guibutton> button in the <guilabel>Select HTML Style
      Sheet</guilabel> window that will appear. You will then see a window like this:
    </para>

    <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoicechange1">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoicechange1.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Cristian Marchi" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>New Style Sheet Window</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>The New Style Sheet window.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>Give a <guilabel>Name</guilabel> to the new style sheet (e.g. <guilabel>Custom Invoice</guilabel>)
      and select the <guilabel>Fancy</guilabel> <guilabel>Template</guilabel>. When you click the
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button, the <guilabel>HTML Style Sheet Properties</guilabel> window
      is displayed. This window presents you five sections listed in the left pane:
      <guilabel>Colors</guilabel>, <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel>, <guilabel>General</guilabel>,
      <guilabel>Images</guilabel>, and <guilabel>Tables</guilabel>. The <guilabel>Colors</guilabel>
      section allows you to change the colors of various items of the invoice. The
      <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> section lets you set fonts type and dimensions. The
      <guilabel>General</guilabel> section allows you to set the <guilabel>Preparer</guilabel> and
      <guilabel>Prepared for</guilabel> information, and to <guilabel>Enable Links</guilabel>. The
      <guilabel>Images</guilabel> section allows you to import graphics into the style sheet. The
      <guilabel>Tables</guilabel> section allows you to adjust the spacing around the tables which
      make up the invoice.
    </para>

    <para>To include a company logo, banner heading and background image, use your favorite graphics
      application such as <application>The Gimp</application> or <application>OpenOffice
      Draw</application> to save the images in either <acronym>GIF</acronym> or
      <acronym>PNG</acronym> format. Then import them into the style sheet using the
      <guilabel>Images</guilabel> section described above.
    </para>

    <para>Below is an example that imports all three types of images.
    </para>

    <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoicechange2">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoicechange2.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Cristian Marchi" width="510"/>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoicechange2.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Cristian Marchi"/>
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>HTML Style Sheets example</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>The <acronym>HTML</acronym> Style Sheets window with an example Background Tile, Heading Banner, and
            Logo.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <note>
      <para>The images are placed in the invoice as follows. The <guilabel>Background Tile</guilabel> is tiled
        to become the background image, the <guilabel>Heading Banner</guilabel> goes to above the
        invoice text, and the <guilabel>Logo</guilabel> is placed in the upper left corner of the
        invoice to the left of the Heading Banner. You will probably have to try a few different
        sized images until you get the invoices to print nicely. Some sizing suggestions are that
        the Logo should be 1 square cm (~0.5 inch), and the Heading Banner should be 15 cm (~6
        inches) wide and 1 cm (~0.5 inch) tall.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>With the style sheet configured, when you print the invoice, you select the style sheet to use from
      the <guimenu>Options</guimenu> menu. Below is the resultant invoice after applying the style
      sheet demonstrated above.
    </para>

    <screenshot id="bus-ar-invoicechange3">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/bus_ar_invoicechange3.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Patrick Schweiger" />
        </imageobject>

        <textobject>
          <phrase>HTML Style Sheets example</phrase>
        </textobject>

        <caption>
          <para>The hideous invoice which results from the graphics selected in the style sheet.
          </para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
