<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-gui-zh.dtd">
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.6.15
  Last modified: January, 2018
  Maintainers:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
               Chris Good <chris.good@ozemail.com.au>
               Christopher Lam
  Author:
  		Jon Lapham <lapham@extracta.com.br>
  Originally designed by Carol Champagne.
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<chapter id="ch_reports">
  <title>Reports</title>

  <para>&app; is a powerful double entry accounting software package that allows users to enter and track
    their money in a reliable manner. However, putting this information into &app; is only a part of
    the process. To be truly helpful, you need to be able to extract this information in meaningful
    ways. &app;'s reporting features allow you to just that.
  </para>

  <para>&app;'s reporting features allow you to display nearly any group of transactions in a wide variety
    of formats. This makes it easy to answer questions about your finances, such as <quote>How much
    did I spend on groceries last month?</quote> or <quote>How much did I earn in the previous six
    months?</quote>
  </para>

  <para>&app; includes a number of common report types, which can be modified to meet your specific needs.
    If these common reports are insufficient, it is possible to modify or even write your own custom
    reports (although this is not recommended for beginners).
  </para>

  <sect1 id="rpt_concepts">
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>There are many standard reports pre-built in &app;, all available from the
      <guimenu>Reports</guimenu> pulldown menu in the main account window.
    </para>

    <para>When you select a report from the list of reports, that report is first run with its default
      settings. Once you have opened the report, you can modify its parameters by clicking on the
      <guibutton>Options</guibutton> button on the toolbar. Under <guilabel>Options</guilabel>, you
      will see the different settings that you can change for each report. Note that for different
      reports, the options will be different.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="rpt_savedconfigsinfo">
    <title>Saved Reports Configurations Concepts</title>

    <para>Once you have modified a report to meet your needs, you may wish to save that report for reuse at a
      later point. &app; allows custom reports to be saved, using the <guimenuitem>Save Report
      Configuration</guimenuitem> command.
    </para>

    <procedure>
      <title>Save a report configuration</title>

      <step>
        <para>Go to the <guilabel>Reports</guilabel> Menu and choose the desired report.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Change the settings on the report until it includes what is needed.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Go to the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab of the report's options and change the Report Name to
          something meaningful (Do not confuse this with the Report Title.)
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Apply the changes and close the dialog.
        </para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Click the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration</guibutton> or <guibutton>Save Report Configuration
          As...</guibutton> button.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <para>This will store the report options in a file in your home directory.
    </para>

    <para>The first time you save a report with a name that has not already been saved, you can use either the
      <guibutton>Save Report Configuration</guibutton> or the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration
      As...</guibutton> button. You can modify the report name before saving it.
    </para>

    <para>Once a report has been saved with the current name, the <guibutton>Save Report
      Configuration</guibutton> button will immediately update the saved report configuration. Use
      the <guibutton>Save Report Configuration As...</guibutton> button to save the current report
      configuration with a new name.
    </para>

    <para>Saved report configurations are available for use under the
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guimenuitem>Saved Report Configurations</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      entry. They will also be available for use on multicolumn reports.
    </para>

    <para>Saved report configurations can be deleted in the <guilabel>Saved Report Configurations</guilabel>
      dialog by clicking the <guiicon>trashcan</guiicon> icon.
    </para>

    <para>To edit saved report configurations, open the report via
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Reports</guimenu><guimenuitem>Saved Report Configurations</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      , edit and apply the new options, and click <guibutton>Save Report Configuration</guibutton>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="rpt_standardrpts">
    <title>Standard Reports Overview</title>

    <para>The standard reports that are included in &app; are presented in this section. For each report, a
      short description is given, which explains what the report is intended to show and its primary
      purpose. We begin with a description of the Transaction Report, which is an all-purpose report
      with many features and settings that allow sophisticated examination of the data in a file.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="rpt_txnrept">
      <title>Transaction Report</title>

      <para>The Transaction Report is a fundamental report that allows users to retrieve a wide variety of
        useful information from the financial records. The report includes many features that allow
        powerful and flexible reporting from the single basic report.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Debit and Credit subtotals can be displayed, and within a grouping section, if debit totals &gt;
            credit totals, the group subtotal will be displayed in the debit column.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Multiple data columns enable display of transaction amounts in report currency and original currency
            in separate columns.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Additional sortkeys e.g. sort by reconcile status (unreconciled -> cleared -> reconciled), sort by
            weeks, allow additional views into the financial records.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full text filter enabled for description, notes and memo, and for account full names. This allows
            easier selection of source account names and tailored reporting. Filters can optionally
            use full POSIX regular expressions.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indenting of columns will indent the report columns for easier understanding of grouping and
            sorting. (This is now enabled by default for &app; 3.0 onwards)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Subtotal table is useful to understand the relationship in the data. This feature compiles the
            primary and secondary subtotals into a table view, allowing additional insight into
            financial records, e.g. account subtotals in different time series.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For further ideas on how to use the Transaction Report to produce common reports, see
        <link linkend='rpt_transaction'>Using the Transaction Report</link>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_grp_assetsliabs">
      <title>Assets &amp; Liabilities Group</title>

      <para>Reports in this group provide general information about assets and liabilities.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="rpt_advport">
        <title>Advanced Portfolio</title>

        <para>The Advanced Portfolio produces a report on commodity accounts (stock and mutual fund type accounts)
          using price information stored in the &app; price database and within the &app;
          transaction data. If you do not have stock price information in your file, the report will
          indicate an error. This report includes extended information about commodity holdings,
          including information about the basis, gain, and return of individual commodities.
        </para>

        <sect4 id="rpt-advport-capgains">
          <title>Advanced Portfolio Capital Gains</title>

          <para>The Advanced Portfolio report doesn’t use the capital gain splits to calculate capital gains. It
            calculates the gains from the various buy and sell transactions in the account without
            regard to whether the gains and losses are recorded or not. Any realized gain splits are
            ignored. Realized gain splits are recognized as two splits, one in the stock’s account
            with a zero number of shares and a non-zero value, the other in an income or expense
            account with a value that is the negative of the split in the stock account. These two
            splits can be in a separate transaction (as created by scrubbing) or in the same
            transaction as the sale (this will cause incorrect future scrubbing). The income or
            expense split can be split into multiple splits, say for taxable/non-taxable or
            short/long term gains, without affecting this report.
          </para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_assetbarchart">
        <title>Asset Barchart</title>

        <para>The Asset Barchart presents the value of assets on a monthly basis in barchart form. By default, the
          report displays the eight largest accounts that have specific asset types assigned to
          them, and it displays bars for the current financial period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Bars" option will display more bars in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display. Additionally, the "Show table" option
              enables the display of chart information in tabular form below the chart.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_assetpiechart">
        <title>Asset Piechart</title>

        <para>The Asset Piechart presents the value of assets on a monthly basis in piechart form. By default, the
          report shows the seven largest accounts, that have specific asset types assigned to them,
          arranged in descending order by value as of the end of the current accounting period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Slices" option will display more slices in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_avgbalance">
        <title>Average Balance</title>

        <para>The Average Balance report displays monthly averages for the current accounting period.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_balancesheet">
        <title>Balance Sheet</title>

        <para>The Balance Sheet lists Asset, Liability, and Equity account balances for all such accounts, and
          provides totals as of a given date. Balance sheets are commonly run for the last day of
          each fiscal year to give an overall sense of the financial condition of the entity.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_generaljournal">
        <title>General Journal</title>

        <para>The General Journal produces a register of all transactions (beginning to end) in order by date,
          showing the accounts and the amounts involved, and totals the Net Change by all currencies
          and assets.
        </para>

        <para>This report is not customizable by date or account, though you can include more or fewer details
          about the individual transactions, and whether to include running balances and totals for
          the credits and debits. If you need a report restricted to particular accounts, consider
          the Transaction Report or open a particular account and choose the Account Transaction
          Report.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_generalledger">
        <title>General Ledger</title>

        <para>The General Ledger produces information about all transactions for a selected set of accounts. When
          first run, this report loads no data, and the report options must be changed to retrieve
          information from the file.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_investlots">
        <title>Investment Lots</title>

        <figure id="fig-investlots" pgwide="1">
          <title>The Investment Lots Report</title>

          <screenshot id="InvestmentLotsScreenShot">
            <screeninfo>
              1720x982
            </screeninfo>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject role="html">
                <imagedata fileref="figures/Report_Investment_Lots.png"
                            srccredit="Brent McBride" width="&img-w;"/>
              </imageobject>

              <imageobject role="fo">
                <imagedata fileref="figures/Report_Investment_Lots.png"
                            srccredit="Brent McBride"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>

        <para>The Investment Lots report shows details about lots in a selected set of accounts of type
          <emphasis>Stock</emphasis> or <emphasis>Mutual Fund</emphasis> (see
          <xref linkend="invest-sellLots" />). It includes an optional capital gains summary chart
          and a table with columns for dates, purchases, sales, end balances, capital gains
          (realized and unrealized, short term and long term), and return on investment (ROI). It
          also performs optional lot validation checks.
        </para>

        <para>The report can help answer questions such as:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Which lots are best candidates for tax loss/gain harvesting?
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>What capital gains have been realized for a particular time period (i.e. this year, last year, etc)?
              Are they long term or short term gains?
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which lots held longer than 1+ years have the largest unrealized gains, and would therefore be most
              advantageous (tax-wise) if donated to charity?
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Are the lots (and related accounts and splits) well-formed?
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>For more details, see the
          <ulink url="&url-docs-C;manual/report-classes.html#investment-lots-report">Investment
          Lots</ulink> report documentation in the Manual.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_investport">
        <title>Investment Portfolio</title>

        <para>The Investment Portfolio produces a report of commodity accounts (that is, accounts with type
          "Stock" or "Mutual Fund"), giving holdings, price and value information about commodities
          in the file.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_liabbarchart">
        <title>Liability Barchart</title>

        <para>The Liability Barchart presents the value of liabilities on a monthly basis in barchart form. By
          default, the report displays the eight largest accounts that have specific asset types
          assigned to them, and it displays bars for the current financial period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Bars" option will display more bars in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display. Additionally, the "Show table" option
              enables the display of chart information in tabular form below the chart.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_liabpiechart">
        <title>Liability Piechart</title>

        <para>The Liability Piechart presents the value of liabilities on a monthly basis in piechart form. By
          default, the report shows the seven largest accounts, that have specific asset types
          assigned to them, arranged in descending order by value as of the end of the current
          accounting period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Slices" option will display more slices in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_networthbar">
        <title>Net Worth Barchart</title>

        <para>The Net Worth Barchart summarizes Asset accounts, Liability accounts, and overall Net Worth as bars
          on a graph on a monthly basis for the current financial period. This report provides a
          graphic overview of the file over time.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_networthline">
        <title>Net Worth Linechart</title>

        <para>The Net Worth Linechart summarizes Asset accounts, Liability accounts, and overall Net Worth as a
          line graph on a monthly basis for the current financial period. This report provides a
          graphic overview of the file over time.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_pricescatter">
        <title>Price Scatterplot</title>

        <para>The Price Scatterplot displays the value of one commodity relative to another commodity, for example
          the value of a stock relative to a currency. When first run, this report loads no data,
          and the report options must be changed to retrieve information from the file.
          Specifically, the "Price of Commodity" setting on the Price options tab must be changed to
          a specific commodity.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_grp_budget">
      <title>Budget Group</title>

      <para>Budget reports in &app; allow you to gather summary information related to budgets you may have
        created. In order for these reports to work, you must first create a budget. The reports in
        this group are specifically based on budget information. To use these reports, you need to
        have a budget saved in your file.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="rpt_budbalsht">
        <title>Budget Balance Sheet</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_budbarchart">
        <title>Budget Barchart</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_budflow">
        <title>Budget Flow</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_budincstate">
        <title>Budget Income Statement</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_budprofloss">
        <title>Budget Profit &amp; Loss</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_budreport">
        <title>Budget Report</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_grp_business">
      <title>Business Group</title>

      <para>Reports in this group provide general information about activities related to a business.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="rpt_customer">
        <title>Customer Report</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_custsummary">
        <title>Customer Summary</title>

        <para>Customer Summary is a customer profit report that can help with job analysis by comparing the income
          and expenses for a specific customer.
        </para>

        <para>All invoices have an Owner in &app;, so invoices that are made will show a customer and show in the
          report. When creating a Bill, the Default Chargeback Customer is blank. To use the profit
          report, this field needs an entry, since this is the tag that decides the line to which to
          attach the expense. Left blank, the bill will be assigned to "No Customer." Similarly,
          when income is entered directly in a register rather than creating an invoice, it will
          also be assigned to "No Customer."
        </para>

        <para>Thus, if this report includes an entry for "No Customer", this means that the report may be
          inaccurate, as the results are not all properly labeled.
        </para>

        <para>Possible use scenarios include:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Tracking retail sales from different cities
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tracking rental properties
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tracking types of business
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tracking commission sales
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Each of these scenarios assumes that the account structure includes breakdowns for individual
          tracked categories. Changing settings on the Income and Expense tabs under Options can
          hone the information displayed. By default all income and expense accounts are included;
          however, since &app; can't really predict the names and classification of income and
          expense accounts, it must group them all into the "No Customer" entry.
        </para>

        <para>Note that inventory-based businesses won't benefit from this report because of its nature.
        </para>

        <para>Useful options:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The Expense Accounts tab allows the selection of one or more expense accounts.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Income Accounts tab allows the selection of one or more income accounts.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The Display tab allows sorting by name, profit percentage, or amount of profit.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_easyinv">
        <title>Easy Invoice</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_employee">
        <title>Employee Report</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_fancyinv">
        <title>Fancy Invoice</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_payaging">
        <title>Payable Aging</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_prtinv">
        <title>Printable Invoice</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_recaging">
        <title>Receivable Aging</title>

        <para>This report provides a listing of all customers, their current balance, and how much they have
          outstanding from invoices over different time periods&amp;mdash;how much they owe from
          0-30 days, from 31-60 days, from 61-90 days, and over 90 days. The report also contains
          links to each customer and to their current customer report.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_vendor">
        <title>Vendor Report</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_grp_incexp">
      <title>Income and Expense Group</title>

      <para>Reports in this group provide information about Income and Expense
      </para>

      <sect3 id="rpt_cashflow">
        <title>Cash Flow</title>

        <para>This report shows the change in value for a set of accounts (the flow of cash) over a given period
          of time. By default, this report is based on accounts in Assets and Special Accounts, and
          covers the current financial period. The report enumerates all money coming in to and
          going out of the base accounts, broken down by the other account.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_equity">
        <title>Equity Statement</title>

        <para>This report can be seen as extension of the Balance Sheet report. The Balance Sheet states the
          balance of Assets, Liabilities and Equity at a specific point of time. The Equity
          Statement focuses on the Equity Accounts by showing the cash flow to and from them for a
          given period of time.
        </para>

        <para>By balancing this cash flow with income, the report shows the available capital at the beginning and
          end of the selected time period.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_expbarchart">
        <title>Expense Barchart</title>

        <para>The Expense Barchart presents the value of expenses on a monthly basis in barchart form. By default,
          the report displays the eight largest accounts that have specific expense types assigned
          to them, and it displays bars for the current financial period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Bars" option will display more bars in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display. Additionally, the "Show table" option
              enables the display of chart information in tabular form below the chart.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_exppiechart">
        <title>Expense Piechart</title>

        <para>The Expense Piechart presents the value of expenses on a monthly basis in piechart form. By default,
          the report shows the seven largest accounts, that have specific expense types assigned to
          them, arranged in descending order by value as of the end of the current accounting
          period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Slices" option will display more slices in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_expdayoweek">
        <title>Expenses vs. Day of Week</title>

        <para>Expenses vs. Day of Week presents a pie chart showing the totals for selected expense accounts
          totaled by the day of the week of the transaction. The report options enable you to make
          some adjustments (such as accounts, display options, and the date range) but the account
          selector only allows expense accounts to be chosen. The report aggregates expense
          transactions by day of week, not by any other period or category. Due to these
          limitations, the report may be considered a demonstration or an example to someone wanting
          to examine the source code for composing a useful custom report.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_incomebarchart">
        <title>Income Barchart</title>

        <para>The Income Barchart presents the value of income on a monthly basis in barchart form. By default,
          the report displays the eight largest accounts that have specific income types assigned to
          them, and it displays bars for the current financial period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Bars" option will display more bars in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display. Additionally, the "Show table" option
              enables the display of chart information in tabular form below the chart.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_incexpchart">
        <title>Income &amp; Expense Chart</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_incomepiechart">
        <title>Income Piechart</title>

        <para>The Income Piechart presents the value of income on a monthly basis in piechart form. By default,
          the report shows the seven largest accounts, that have specific income types assigned to
          them, arranged in descending order by value as of the end of the current accounting
          period.
        </para>

        <para>Several settings on this report can greatly affect the information included.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the Accounts tab, the "Show Accounts until level" option changes how the report aggregates
              account totals. Change this value to see information at deeper levels of the account
              structure.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the Display tab, the "Maximum Slices" option will display more slices in the chart, allowing
              information for more accounts to display.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>On the General tab, the "Price Source" option can significantly affect the reported value of various
              commodities included in the report.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_incstatement">
        <title>Income Statement</title>

        <para>This report lists Income and Expense account totals for a set period. By default, it shows all
          Expense and Income accounts down to 3 levels of sub-accounts for the current financial
          period.
        </para>

        <para>An Income Statement is also called a "Profit and Loss" report or "Revenue Statement."
        </para>

        <para>In earlier versions of &app;, this report was called "Profit &amp; Loss," but with version 2, the
          report was renamed "Income Statement" to use more common accounting terminology.
        </para>

        <para>The Income Statement helps show where money is coming from and where it is going for a given time
          period.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_incdayoweek">
        <title>Income vs. Day of Week</title>

        <para>Income vs. Day of Week presents a piechart showing the totals for selected income accounts totaled
          by the day of the week of the transaction. The report options enable you to make some
          adjustments (such as accounts, display options, and the date range) but the account
          selector only allows income accounts to be chosen. The report aggregates income
          transactions by day of week, not by any other period or category. Due to these
          limitations, the report may be considered a demonstration or an example to someone wanting
          to examine the source code for composing a useful custom report.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_trialbal">
        <title>Trial Balance</title>

        <para>Trial Balance lists the ending balances in all accounts as of a particular date. It is typically run
          at the end of an accounting period and is primarily used to ensure that the total of all
          debits equals the total of all credits.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_gst_statement">
        <title>Income and GST Statement</title>

        <para>The Income and GST Statement is a specialised Transaction Report designed to print Business-related
          Sales and Receipts, as well as their GST or VAT components. This report is designed for
          use in Australia, but is also usable in any jurisdictions implementing value-added taxes
          (or goods and services taxes) during regular business sales and receipts; and the business
          owner is expected to submit periodic reports of total sales, purchases, and taxes
          collected on sales from clients or paid to a supplier.
        </para>

        <para>This report makes some assumptions upon the accounts used for sales, purchases, and taxes collected
          on sales, and paid on purchases.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Net Sales must be an Income-type account
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Net Purchases must be an Expense-type account
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>GST/VAT on Sales must be a Liability-type account
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>GST/VAT on Purchases must be an Asset-type account
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There may be multiple GST accounts, e.g. reduced GST, standard GST etc. The GST accounts can be
              printed individually, or summarised for sales and purchases.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There may be multiple sales and expenses accounts, e.g. Income:Sales, Income:Grants,
              Expenses:Suppliers, Expenses:Marketing, Expenses:Insurance. These amounts may be
              reported individually, or summarised for sales and purchases.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The transactions may be entered manually as a multi-split transaction, or they may be entered via
              the Business Invoices and Bills tools.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>As an example, consider a business has the following transactions: It incurs sales of $1,000 plus 5%
          GST, receiving $1,050. It also incurs GST-exempt sales of $600. It purchases
          goods/services worth $400 plus 5% = $420. The following transactions will record the
          business activities:
        </para>

        <table>
          <title>Sample Chart of Accounts for Income and GST Statement</title>

          <tgroup cols="5" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
            <colspec colname="date"/>

            <colspec colname="desc"/>

            <colspec colname="account"/>

            <colspec colname="debit" align="right"/>

            <colspec colname="credit" align="right"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Date
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Description
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Account
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Debit
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Credit
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody valign="top">
              <row>
                <entry morerows="2">
                  01/01/2018
                </entry>

                <entry morerows="2">
                  Sales $1,000 + 5% GST
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Income:Sales
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  $1,000
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  GST on Sales [Liability]
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  $50
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Asset:Bank
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $1,050
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry morerows="1">
                  02/01/2018
                </entry>

                <entry morerows="1">
                  GST-Free Sales $600
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Income:Sales
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  $600
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Asset:Bank
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $600
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry morerows="2">
                  03/01/2018
                </entry>

                <entry morerows="2">
                  Purchase $400 + 5% GST
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Expenses:Purchases
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $400
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Asset:Bank
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  $420
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  GST on Purchases [Asset]
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $20
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>For the Income and GST Statement, the <option>Accounts</option> selected will be the Income and
          Expense Accounts, and the <option>Tax accounts</option> are used to select the GST
          accounts. The GST period is selected via the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab. The
          resulting report is shown as follows:
        </para>

        <table>
          <title>Income and GST Statement</title>

          <tgroup cols="8" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
            <colspec colname="date"/>

            <colspec colname="desc"/>

            <colspec colname="tot-sales" align="right"/>

            <colspec colname="net-sales" align="right"/>

            <colspec colname="tax-sales" align="right"/>

            <colspec colname="tot-purch" align="right"/>

            <colspec colname="net-purch" align="right"/>

            <colspec colname="tax-purch" align="right"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Date
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Description
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Total Sales
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Net Sales
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Tax on Sales
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Total Purchases
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Net Purchases
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Tax on Purchases
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  01/01/2018
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Sales $1,000 + 5%
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $1,050
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $1,000
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $50
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  02/01/2018
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  GST-Free Sales $600
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $600
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $600
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  03/01/2018
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  Purchase $400 + 5% GST
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  $420
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $400
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $20
                </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>
                  Totals
                </entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>
                  $1,650
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $1,600
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $50
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $420
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $400
                </entry>

                <entry>
                  $20
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>This report would indicate that there was a total of $50 GST collected, and $20 GST on purchases,
          therefore a $30 GST liability is payable to the authorities.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_grp_sampcust">
      <title>Sample &amp; Custom Group</title>

      <para>The reports in this group offer examples on how reports can be customized or modified to suit
        personal need.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="rpt_custommulti">
        <title>Custom Multicolumn Report</title>

        <para>This report provides a base that allows several standard and custom reports to be combined into one
          view. Note that this report opens with an empty window; you must open the options and
          designate which reports to include for display. Once the reports have been selected, the
          settings for individual reports in the multicolumn display can be edited.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_sample">
        <title>Sample Report with Examples</title>

        <para>This is a sample report that users can examine to learn how to write their own reports.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_welcome">
        <title>Welcome Sample Report</title>

        <para>This report demonstrates how the Multicolumn Report can be use to create custom dashboard-type
          reports.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_grp_miscrpts">
      <title>Other Reports</title>

      <para>Several reports are included on the main Reports menu. These are described below.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="rpt_acctsummary">
        <title>Account Summary</title>

        <para>This lists the balances of all accounts and subaccounts as of a particular date. By default, this
          report shows accounts and totals down to third-level subaccounts.
        </para>

        <para>This report gives effectively the same information as the Chart of Accounts. You can use this report
          to export and print the Chart of Accounts.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>To generate a report of account totals over a particular time period (especially if you do not close
            your books at regular intervals), you might consider using the Income Statement, or Cash
            Flow reports.
          </para>
        </note>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_balance_forecast">
        <title>Balance Forecast</title>

        <para>This creates a balance chart which aims to track asset (or any other account type) balances,
          including amounts from future scheduled transactions. The balances will include all
          regular booked amounts and future amounts from numeric scheduled transaction templates.
        </para>

        <para>This report can also add additional data charts to forecast future minimum balances. Reserve line
          can be displayed to confirm if future minimum will dip below the reserve amount. A target
          line may also be displayed above the reserve line for financial planning.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_futsched">
        <title>Future Scheduled Transactions Summary</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_taxtxf">
        <title>Tax Report &amp; TXF Export</title>

        <para>Generates a report and a downloadable .txf file of taxable income and deductible expenses for a
          particular accounting period. To download the report data, choose the Export button on the
          toolbar and choose between html and .txf downloadable versions.
        </para>

        <para>To use this report, you must use Edit --> Tax Options to identify which form the taxing authority
          uses for each income or expense account. Note that you can see but not modify the "Tax
          related" checkbox in Edit --> Edit Account.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_savedrpts">
        <title>Saved Report Configurations</title>

        <para>Selecting this will open a dialog with a list of available Saved Report Configurations. "Saved
          Report Configurations" means sets of customized settings for standard reports.
        </para>

        <para>These sets must be saved by the user before they appear here. See Report Concepts above for
          instructions on how to save report configurations.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_acctreport">
        <title>Account Report</title>

        <para>The Account Report menu entry only appears when an account register is the active tab. This report
          produces a list of all transactions in the open register.
        </para>

        <para>Note that if you conduct a search that retrieves several transactions, the results are displayed in
          a new search register, which can then be used to create a report for just those
          transactions.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="rpt_accttxnrept">
        <title>Account Transaction Report</title>

        <para>This report also only appears when an account register is the active tab. However, this report only
          lists transactions that have been selected (e.g. by mouse click) in the current register.
          If no transactions are selected, an empty report will be generated.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rpt_transaction">
      <title>Using the Transaction Report</title>

      <para>The Transaction Report can be heavily customised to produce most reports appropriate for personal
        finance and business bookkeeping purposes. It aims to retrieve and filter information from
        the database, and present transactions and totals, useful for the user and the accountant.
      </para>

      <para>The following guide to the Transaction Report will assume the user has set up the chart of accounts
        according to conventional bookkeeping practice. For example, the following describes a
        typical household book with skeleton accounts. Further accounts will undoubtedly be
        necessary.
      </para>

      <table>
        <title>Sample Chart of Accounts for the Transaction Report</title>

        <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Account Name
              </entry>

              <entry>
                Account Type
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                Asset
              </entry>

              <entry>
                ASSET (placeholder)
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Asset:Bank
              </entry>

              <entry>
                BANK
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Asset:Property
              </entry>

              <entry>
                ASSET
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Liability
              </entry>

              <entry>
                LIABILITY (placeholder)
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Liability:Credit Card
              </entry>

              <entry>
                CREDIT CARD
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Liability:Home Loan
              </entry>

              <entry>
                LIABILITY
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Income
              </entry>

              <entry>
                INCOME (placeholder)
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Income:Salary
              </entry>

              <entry>
                INCOME
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Income:Interest
              </entry>

              <entry>
                INCOME
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Expense
              </entry>

              <entry>
                EXPENSE (placeholder)
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Expense:Groceries
              </entry>

              <entry>
                EXPENSE
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Expense:Auto
              </entry>

              <entry>
                EXPENSE
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Expense:Medical
              </entry>

              <entry>
                EXPENSE
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Equity
              </entry>

              <entry>
                EQUITY (placeholder)
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                Equity:Opening Balances
              </entry>

              <entry>
                EQUITY
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Conventionally, the oldest transaction would be equity transfers from Equity:Opening Balances to
        Asset and Liability Accounts. Most subsequent transactions would be transfers from
        Income/Expense accounts to Assets/Liability accounts (representing day-to-day activity e.g.
        receiving salary, paying utility bill), or transfers between assets and liability accounts
        (representing movements between loans and assets, e.g. paying credit card bill, receiving a
        loan).
      </para>

      <para>The following use cases will be illustrated, and the options to be selected explained:
      </para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Using the Transaction Report to show previous year expenses</title>

        <para>The Transaction Report can show how much was spent on expense accounts last year. This will usually
          be the most useful basic transaction report format. To create this report:
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open the report options, from the <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab, click the Expense placeholder
              account and <guibutton>Select Children</guibutton>.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab, Choose relative dates “Start of Previous Year” and
              “End of Previous Year”.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Sorting</guilabel> tab, set <guilabel>Primary Key</guilabel> to Accounts, and
              enable <guilabel>Primary Key Subtotal</guilabel>.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set the <guilabel>Secondary Key</guilabel> to Date, and set the <guilabel>Secondary Key
              Subtotal</guilabel> to None.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Secondary level grouping</title>

        <para>The following will modify the above Transaction Report to use a secondary grouping strategy. The
          first grouping (i.e. Primary Key = Accounts, Subtotal = enabled) will group transactions
          from the same accounts, whereas the secondary grouping (i.e. Secondary Key = Date,
          Subtotal = Monthly) will also calculate monthly sums within each account.
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select options as above
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Sorting</guilabel> tab, set <guilabel>Secondary Key Subtotal</guilabel> to
              Monthly
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Using secondary grouping for periodic comparison</title>

        <para>The Display / Subtotal Table adds a subtotal summary table, which will ease comparison of accounts
          across date periods. This displays the same subtotal calculations as the main table,
          presented in a grid structure.
        </para>

        <para>In addition, if there are multiple primary-key groups (e.g. Date grouping with monthly subtotals,
          across multiple months) the subtotal table will also compute and display the primary-key
          grouping Average. The average is computed as the total amount <emphasis>per
          row</emphasis>, divided by the <emphasis>number of columns</emphasis>. This may cause
          confusion when computing monthly spend averages, for instance, if a month has no
          transactions and is not displayed in the table, it will <emphasis>not</emphasis> create a
          corresponding column in the table, therefore the average amount will not reflect a true
          monthly average.
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select options as above
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab, enable the <guilabel>Subtotal Table</guilabel>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Use filtering to limit accounts and transactions</title>

        <para>Accounts and transactions can be filtered for reporting according to account full name (e.g.
          ":Business:" will select account structure Income:Business:Sales, Income:Business:Grants,
          Expenses:Business:Rent, Expenses:Business:Utilities) or transaction description/notes/memo
          (select transactions tagged #gift). The filtering text may be either a standard string, or
          a POSIX regular expression.
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Filter</guilabel> tab, complete the <guilabel>Account Name Filter</guilabel>, or
              <guilabel>Transaction Filter</guilabel>. Optionally toggle the regular expression
              check boxes to toggle full POSIX regex matching. Regular expressions will allow more
              complex queries e.g. the transaction filter can be set to (#gift|#travel) which will
              filter transactions with either #gift or #travel. They can be complicated and are best
              learned from external guides.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Using the Transaction Report to generate a reconciliation statement.</title>

        <para>This sortkey 'reconcile status' will separate reconciled, cleared and unreconciled transactions.
          This report may be useful in producing a printable reconciliation report.
        </para>

        <para>Alternatively, the <guilabel>Reconciliation Report </guilabel> will preset these defaults and
          requires only the Accounts selection.
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Accounts</guilabel> tab, select the relevant bank or credit card account
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab, choose an appropriate date range e.g. past 3 months
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>From the <guilabel>Sorting</guilabel> tab, set the <guilabel>Primary Key</guilabel> to Reconcile
              Status, <guilabel>Primary Key Subtotal</guilabel> to enabled, and set the
              <guilabel>Secondary Key</guilabel> to Date. The <guilabel>Secondary Date
              Subtotal</guilabel> is left to None
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
